<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/12 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-17 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1948-02-00">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">Feb 1948</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Too Many People: Radio Port-au-Prince Interview</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp143743</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library Of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl> Library of Congress Microfilm 130:636</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
			<name id="PET">Petch, Mrs.</name>
			<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
			<name id="WIEJU">Wiesel, Jules</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This is a rough draft of Sanger's talk that was broadcast as a radio discussion on
			station <org reg="HH2S (Radio Station)">HH2S</org> in <place reg="Port-au-Prince, Haiti"
				>Port-au-Prince</place>. Some handwritten corrections were made by Sanger, many more
			by <person reg="Brush, Dorothy Hamilton">Dorothy Brush</person>, her traveling
			companion, including many of the questions asked by Jules Wiesel and Mrs. Petch. No
			final version of the talk was found. </p>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="Italy" level2="population policies of"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="slums"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="population policies of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>
			<title rend="underline">TOO MANY PEOPLE</title>
		</head>
		<head type="sub" rend="underline">Station HH2S--Radio Port Au Prince: Margaret Sanger</head>
		<p><emph rend="underline"><person reg="Wiesel, Jules"
			>Wiesel</person>:</emph>Introduction</p>
		<p><emph rend="underline">Sanger</emph> Thank you, Mr. Weisel. I am glad to have this
			opportunity to speak from <place>Haiti</place> on this vital quesiton of world
			population. </p>
		<p>For the first time in history people are thinking of an international program for
			population control. <add><org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org></add>It is
			significant that a <org>United Nations</org> delegate at the <org
				reg="International Health Conference, 1948">international Health Conference</org>
			said, "<q who="UNK">The control of the birth rate is as important as control of the atom
				bomb.</q>"</p>
		<p>
			<add>Congress</add>
		</p>
		<p>Population is a large and vague word-- But when you think about it <del>more
				carefully</del> it simply means people. Our leaders disagree on this problem of
			people. Some leaders want many more people to populate their countries. They give prizes
			and rewards to <add>fathers</add> mothers of big families. They think of national
			welfare in terms of how many nationals they have of military age. Other experts disagree
				<del>with this philosophy, because they</del> believ<del>e</del><add>ing</add> that
			unlimited masses of people are <add>a brake on; civilzation</add> meaningless--and
			dangerous. What this world needs, they explain are more productive, creative people
				<del>who are</del> able to <del>contribute to our civilization</del>
			<add>accelerate progress</add> These experts are alarmed at the swarming millions of
				<del>unproductive</del>, <add>dependant</add> defective human life <del>that is
			</del> multiplying with such senseless violence. They explain that this is a finite
			earth. Space is increasingly limited. Food resources are becoming alarmingly
				<del>limited.</del>
			<add>scarce</add> Must the productive <del>people </del>have less to eat in order to
			feed more and more <add>of the</add> unproductive <add>?</add>
			<del>mouths?</del>
			<add>Since</add> We have learned, <del>the experts explain that we must</del>
			<add>to</add> plan the size of our families according to our resources, the next step is
			to plan the number of people our countries can support. <gap reason="deleted"/></p>
		<p>
			<add>This very summer an international congress of investment scientists &amp;
				distinguished people alive to this danger are meeting in <place>England</place> to
				discuss <org
					reg="International Congress on Population in Relation to World Resources">world
					population and world resources</org>. Population seems like an abstract
				subject.</add>
		</p>
		<p>
			<add>Wiesel <q who="WIEJU">Are there figures to suggest how that number could be arrived
					at (2)</q></add>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: It takes 100 acres of tillable land to give meat to nine people once a day....100
			acres of grazing land to give milk to forty children once a day....And 100 acres of
			tillable land to give bread or cereal to 280 people once a day. <add> and people
				increase while the amount of land remains the same</add> Millions of people never
			have meat or cow's milk.</p>
		<p>
			<add>
				<q who="WIEJU">Wiesel: The last war than did not diminish the population by
					much?</q>
			</add>
		</p>
		<p><supplied resp="MSPP">Sanger:</supplied> There are more people on the earth now in the
			last 150 years than there were during ALL the <emph rend="underline">millions </emph> of
			years that man has lived on this planet... The earth is only <emph rend="underline"
				>so</emph> big--there's only <emph rend="underline">so</emph> much food to go
			around--only so much soil to grow it in. <add>of course </add><add>and we now have 10%
				less food per person than before the war.</add>
			<del>So we have to begin to think about our population problem.</del></p>
		<p><gap reason="deleted"/>the millions <del>who</del> were killed in the last war. . .
				<del>And</del>
			<add>but</add> still the population soared--while all the time the food to support all
			these people fell off, <add>as farm lands were ruined, sometimes terrain, by
			war.</add></p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: But why has this startling rise in population happened so fast--and
				in such a short time Mrs. Sanger?</q>
		</p>
		<p><emph rend="underline">SANGER</emph>: Modern medicine and sanititation have given us for
			the first time a genuinely effective method of death control. . . . <del>PETCH: And now
				that doctors can keep us from dying</del>
			<add>We do not die</add>as fast and as young as our ancestors used to die.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="WIEJU"><add>Wiesel: And so</add>
				<del>you mean</del>, there's nothing to stop people multiplying at a violent
				rate?</q>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: <del>You see</del><add>Before medicine</add> wars and germs killed off our
			ancestors quite effectively--so there was a real balance between the number of people
				<del>who used to be</del> born and the number who died to make more room for
			them.... But <add>not now.</add><del>wars alone don't hold down population.</del><gap
				reason="torn"/></p>
		<p>SANGER:<del> Mrs. Petch</del>
			<del>i</del><add>I</add>if this rise in population keeps up we are going to increase at
			the frightening rate of 200 million every ten years... <del>And despite</del>
			<place>Western Europe</place> is sick from the population <del>binge</del>
			<add>(orgy)</add> it began a century ago. And we're all concerned with the problems of
			teeming <place>Asia</place>--wracked by famines, constant hunger and disease. Don't
			forget as we gain more control over the death rate through our increasing medical
			knowledge--there will be still more people. There just are not resources to give people
			the food nad clothing and shelter they must have. And the more people there are--the
			less each person can expect to get. <add>The lower our standards go</add></p>
		<p>
			<q who="WIEJU"><emph rend="underline">Wiesel</emph> Yet we hear cries of alarm from many
				nations informed they are losing out in the birth rate race. In fact most European
				countries still are taking official action to encourage more babies.</q>
		</p>
		<p>Sanger Yes, while those who are alive are starving.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: But why <del>do you think that</del><add>are</add>most countries
					<del>are</del> so anxious for a high birth rate?</q>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: <del>You know <person reg="Hitler, Adolf">Hitler</person> had a powerful
				propaganda machine. I believe without realizing it people everywhere have absorbed
				his doctrine <del>despite his downfall</del> that there is an actual connection
				between numbers and power.</del>
			<add>Its not the people <del>Mrs. Petch</del> Its the militarists, leaders in congested
				countries</add></p>
		<p>SANGER: Look what happened with the Axis nations! They were all explosively
			over-populated even before World War 1. In the 1920's serious-minded Japanese and
			Italian officials tried to apply brakes to their terrific rate of growth. But the
			militarists won out. They knew that over-population made their countries ripe for
			military dictatorship and conquest. <add>What makes</add> Men want to fight
			<add>?</add>, <del>for</del>
			<add>lack of</add> bread for their children. <add>The cry for land is the cry for the
				cry for bread. The cry for babies is the cry for war.</add></p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: And then of course at <del>the very opposite extreme to the Axis we
					have</del>
				<add>There are</add> the vastly over-crowded countries like <place>China</place> and
					<place>India</place>.</q>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: Yes-- <add>Where many are too weak from lack of food even to fight to eat.</add>
			<del>we've been dreadfully confused on this problem of population.</del> China and
			India's tremendous birth rate are certainly no sign of <add>Natural</add> strength or
				<del>national virility</del>
			<add>Political power</add>
			<del>You know Mrs. Petch</del> when I hear people quote from the <title type="book"
				>Bible</title> "<q who="BIB">Be fruitful and multiply</q>"-- I want to remind them
			of another Biblical saying-- "<q who="BIB">Thou has multiplied the nation, and not
				increased the joy.</q>" That's from <title type="article">Isaiah</title> in the 9th
			chapter, 3rd verse.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: But, Mrs. Sanger <emph rend="underline">isn't</emph> there strength
				in numbers? And doesn't our national security depend on it?</q>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: If <place reg="United States">America</place>'s safety depended on numbers we
			would have <add>been</add>beaten at the start of both world wars. You know what a
			decisive factor the United States actually was in modern, technological warfare. It is
			the quality of <del><unclear>brains</unclear></del>
			<add>brains?</add> that counts. In fact our national--and international security depends
			on this!--and by quality I mean man's intelligence and ingenuity and foresight--but most
			of <add>/</add> all man's humanity. That is what will count in our fight to survive and
			achieve a stable world peace. We won the last war because we had a surplus of goods over
			and above the needs of our own daily living. We can win the peace because we have enough
			goods to keep <add>our own</add> people fed and clothed and housed. Happy, well-fed
			people <del>are not led by</del><add>do not listen to</add> warmongers. They would think
			it a poor bargain to give up their freedom to dictators who promise them bread if they
				<add>already</add>have bread--and freedom to eat it in! That's the best combination
			for peace. </p>
		<p>
			<q who="WIEJU"><emph rend="underline">Wiesel</emph> You speak of an economy of
				population for the future-- May I ask if you think we are utilizing our present
				population as effectively as we could.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<add>Sanger: No indeed.</add>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: Technically trained people are badly needed in many parts of the world. We keep
			saying that in the case of certain skills and professions, a nation will ahve to wait
			for a whole new crop of babies to grow up before the trained group are availible in
			large enough numbers. I'd like to see an International Placement Bureau--a Labor Pool of
			skills and professions. Individuals from this pool could <add>choose to</add> be sent to
			any part of the world where they are needed.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: But how could you start this Labor Pool of professions and
				skills?</q>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: Just think of all the highly trained men and women wasting away in the Displaced
			Persons Camps! It's criminal to waste people like that. If they could be made availible
			according to their skills, to the countries that need those techniques, it would be one
			way of solvign their problem.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: <del>You know Mrs. Sanger, I've lived a great deal</del><add>I
					understand that</add> in <place>Scandinavia</place>--<del>where</del> your idea
				has been attempted on a national scale. It's been very successful. Those countries
				are really a small scale model of what you hope to do on a world scale, aren't
				they?</q>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: Yes, so far only small countries with no imperialistic ambitions like the
			Scandinavian lands have attempted this planning of their people. <add>to their
				resources</add></p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: And they certainly found that it made for happiness and plenty for
				all their citizens. Everyone had a fair share of food and jobs and homes.</q>
		</p>
		<p>SANGER: When the great powers recognize the truth--that it's the caliber of people and
			NOT the quantity of people that matters, they will begin planning their populations.
			When that day comes, no nation will have more people than it's resources can take care
			of satisfactorily. </p>

		<p>SANGER: <add>and that day will come.</add>There are courageous, farsighted people
			throughout the world who believe that the time has come for less waste in people,
				<del>Mrs. Petch.</del> They are deeply concerned with the swarming millions of
			unproductive, defective human life that is multiplying with such uncontrolled velocity.
			You see once we <del>stop thinking</del> that <add>realizing brains, not</add>numbers
			mean strength we <emph rend="underline">have</emph> to change our attitudes. In modern
			war and in modern peaceful society, it takes ability and skill and education to
			function. Numbers no longer mean strength in war or in peace!</p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: <del>Where are your Conference delegates coming from Mrs.
					Sanger?</del></q>
		</p>
		<p> And while you were helping to solve their problems the countries that employed them
			would be helped back on their feet. It's an extraordinarily interesting idea, Mrs.
			Sanger.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="WIEJU">
				<del> Wiesel: In closing Mrs. Sanger may I ask you how you became so influenced in
					so <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> an abstract <del>idea as</del>
					subject as population</del>
			</q>
		</p>
		<gap reason="missing" extent="paragraphs"/>
		<p>
			<del>They have accepted Hitler's propaganda that only frowing natios are strong, and so
				they think that nations with a stable or a declining population must be "old" or on
				their way out.</del>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">
				<emph rend="underline">PETCH:</emph>
				<del>Yes--I'm afraid a great many of us believe that. But isn't there some truth in
					the idea of a growing nation?</del>
			</q>
		</p>
		<gap reason="missing" extent="paragraphs"/>
		<p><del>began to see</del> what a tremendous job control of birth could do in effecting
			world peace. If hungry, despserate people explode into war, why not begin to balance the
			number of people born with the resources availablle to care for them? Then <del> all of
				us can enjoy the good things of this world</del>
			<add>none of us need starve or do without</add>. If medical science has given us the
			blessing of controlling death, it has been generous in also giving us the means of
			controlling birth. Now we can plan both the size of our families and the growth of our
			nations. And by planning we can produce the number of people that we can best take care
			of.</p>
		<gap reason="missing" extent="paragraphs"/>
		<p>I've seen what poverty and overcrowding did in the slums of <place reg="New York, NY">New
				York</place> when I worked in them as a nurse 30 years ago. <add> And I saw how
				control of numbers brought health &amp; prosperity to a family.</add> I have just
			expanded <add> The principles operating in </add> those New York City slums <del>. Now I
				see</del>
			<add>to</add> the terrible world slums. Like all slums they breed death and hunger and
			disease--and finally war!</p>
		<p>
			<q who="PET">PETCH: So your idea has grown from one slum in one city to the
					<del>whole</del>
				<add>one slum of the one</add> world.</q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
