<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-23 JC transcribed and encoding</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-24 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2013-03-02 JC correct tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-19 CH recheck tags</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-13 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1934-01-15">15 Jan 1934</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">American Conference on Birth Control
					and National Recovery Welcoming Address</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp157134</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 125:347-349</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ML">Malthusian League</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For another version of this address, see <xref from="157134.xml">Address of
				Welcome</xref>, Jan. 15, 1934. For newspaper coverage of Sanger's comments at this
			event, see <xref from="422098.xml">Statement on the American Conference on Birth Control
				and National Recovery</xref>, Jan. 15, 1934. For partial versions of this speech,
			delivered in Washington, see Library of Congress Microfilm 131:64B, and Margaret Sanger
			Microfilm, Smith College Collections, S71:642, 645, and 647.</p>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="American"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>
			<emph rend="underline">OPENING ADDRESS</emph>
		</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>I have the honor to open the <org
					reg="American Conference on Birth Control and National Recovery">AMERICAN
					CONFERENCE ON BIRTH CONTROL AND NATIONAL RECOVERY</org>, which is held under the
				auspices of the <org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth
					Control</org>, Inc.</p>
			<p>This is the 2nd National Conference to be held in <place reg="United States">this
					country</place>--and to this I bid you a cordial and hearty welcome. It is the
				first ever held in the <place reg="Washington, DC">District of Columbia</place>,
				where we have had cooperation and help on an extensive scale.</p>
			<p>
				<add>appropriate where all our troubles began 60 years ago</add>
			</p>
			<p>(Introducing <person reg="Dryden, Lelia">Mrs. Dryden</person>)</p>
			<p>I want to now introduce you to the Chairman of the Reception Committee of the
				District of Columbia, whose help and assistance, whose guidance and sound advice,
				has helped to make this Conference the success that we hope it is going to be.</p>
			<p>I have the pleasure of introducing Mrs. John F. Dryden.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>(Response to Mrs. Dryden.)</p>
			<p>I thank you, Mrs. Dryden, on behalf of the National Committee on Federal Legislation
				and on behalf of the delegates and speakers of this Conference.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>The Birth Control movement had its beginning in this country in 1914--just 20 years
				ago. During that time there have been more than 11 State, 6 Regional, and 6
				International Conferences (besides the most recent one in <place
					reg="London, England">London</place> last November, called the <org
					reg="Conference on Birth Control in Asia">Asiatic Conference</org>, which was
				preliminary to the work <add>the international clubs</add> we are planning to do in
				the <place reg="Asia">Orient</place> in 1935. <del>Then</del> we <add>now</add>
				<del>emerge into</del>
				<add>come to</add> the 20th Anniversary of the Modern Birth Control Movement not
				only in this country but throughout the world.</p>
			<p>While the problem of population was recognized by intelligent thinkers, especially in
					<place>England</place>, since the days of <person reg="Malthus, Thomas Robert"
					>Malthus</person>, the slogan of the Neo-Malthusians was to "<q who="ML">Educate
					the Educators</q>"; while the slogan of the Birth Control movement is to
				"Educate the Masses".</p>
			<p>We have gone a good way toward <add>accomplish</add> our goal and it is safe to say
				that the masses are ready and desirous to receive this <add>B.C.</add> information
				when it is made available for their use.</p>
			<p>This knowledge should not remain the privilege of the well-to-do. It should become
				the right of the millions of poor, worried, struggling mothers who ask only the
				right to knowledge that they may free themselves from intolerable conditions akin to
				slavery, and have a chance to develop <add>bodies minds &amp; souls</add> and to
				pursue happiness for themselves and their children.</p>
			<p>Laws are in the way to this objective. We must enlighten our <del>legislators</del>
				<add>lawmakers</add> to this effect. It should be the duty of our government to
				provide for the diseased, the inefficient, the overburdened and unfit, and others
				who may desire it, the best information on contracepti<del>on</del><add>ves</add>
				available.</p>
			<p>If the Government will give the same consideration to the forgotten Woman that it has
				given to the Forgotten man--we may yet rectify the deplorable situation created by
					<add>the <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211"
						>Comstock laws</name></add> our, differential birthrate.</p>
			<p>The past twenty years have been years of struggle against injustice, intolerance,
				arrogance and <del>legal</del><add>overwhelming</add> obstacles. But in spite of
				opposition from such quarters<add>,</add> as well as from others who should have
				supported this cause, the movement has advanced rapidly and <add>has</add> gained
				millions of friends and advocates. It is gaining momentum every year, <add>&amp; in
					every country</add> and the time is not far off when this government will be
				called upon to face the question of birth control <add>for the common people</add>
				and sterilization <del>as well</del>
				<add>for the feebleminded &amp; unfit</add>. We can lay at the doors of the
				opponents of this movement a large part of the misery and poverty arising from the
				huge <del>arrag</del>
				<add>army</add> of unemployed, whose suffering, hopelessness, and loss of self
				respect have spread like an epidemic throughout the Nation.</p>
			<p>We are gathered here today, workers in the field from 25 states, to discuss some of
				the greatest problems that are now confronting a new world. Many <add>of us</add>
				believe that the advance of the birth control movement, means the advance of
				civilization, and that the direction this movement shall take from now on, shall
				decide the future of the country's welfare.</p>
			<p>We are here to help in its direction; we are here to discuss the problems constantly
				arising within the movement itself as well as from without. We are here to share our
				discoveries with each other, <add>to share</add> what we have learned from our
				experience; and we are here to awaken <add>a keener</add> realization and
					interest<add>,</add> in these problems in the public <add>and</add> to
				strengthen our faith<add>in the future</add> and to broaden our vision that it may
				embrace the entire world.</p>
			<p>When the history of the <add>BC</add> movement shall be written, high tribute will be
				paid to the courageous stand taken by the scientists of this period.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>(Introducing <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Prof. Fairchild</person>)</p>
			<p>Sociologists, economists and biologists <add>who</add>
				<del>have</del> from the beginning <add>have</add> thrown the weight of their
				influence with this movement. We have with us today many distinguished men and women
				in various fields of science--from many walks of life--and I have the pleasure to
				introduce you to one who has for many years lent the prestige of his name, and given
				of his time and energy to the advancement of this <del>cause</del>
				<add>work</add>. I am glad to say he will preside over this meeting; he will
				introduce the speakers, and will summarize the discussion... Professor Henry Pratt
				Fairchild.</p>
			<p/>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
