<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2002-08-05 KH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2002-08-5 KH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-11 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-03">Mar 1929</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Genius: Will Birth Control Diminish It?</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp226798</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Eugenics</title>, Mar. 1929</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S71:156</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<sourceNote/>
	<headNote><index level1="eugenics"/><index level1="mentally disabled"/></headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Will Birth control Diminish It?</head>
		<byline>MARGARET SANGER</byline>
		<p>To say that birth control runs the risk of excluding from life geniuses as well as
			defectives is to imply that chance is a better guide than intelligence. The total number
			of geniuses in the whole of human history is much less than one thousand. The total
			number of defectives could never be computed. The damage they have done to civilization
			cannot be counterbalanced by the benefits we have derived from genius. The garden of
			humanity has been choked by the destructive forces of uncontrolled and misdirected
			procreation. Small wonder that the potentialities hidden in the human species have so
			seldom flowered in genius. Father <person reg="McClorey, John A.">McClorey</person> may
			think it better to abandon the garden to the weeds, naively confident that geniuses will
			make their appearances regardless of heredity and environment. But no student of
			genetics, no one who has even superficially observed the achievements of scientific
			horticulture and animal breeding, can consider seriously that the road to human
			perfection can ever be attained by abandoning scientific control and reverting to a
			childish reliance upon the blind fores of uncontrolled procreative instincts.</p>
		<p>Little as we still know about genius, or about men and women of exceptional talents, we
			do know that they do not come into this world with hereditary backgrounds of imbecility,
			or feeble-mindedness.</p>
		<p>The seed of genius is hidden deep in the race. It is the most sacred duty of every parent
			and parent-to-be to recognize that he is the guardian of this seed, that
			he is, so to speak, the ancestor of a future genius.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
