<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2011-07-29 NC</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2011-09-15 EK upload + index terms</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-30 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1950-02-12">12 Feb 1950</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Response to General Douglas MacArthur</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp227963</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S72:52</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
			<name id="MACDO">MacArthur, Douglas</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This was a press release issued by the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of
				America</org>. Additional text comes from <title type="article">Mrs. Slee Says She
				was Denied Entry by U.S. Authorities</title>, <title type="journal">Kingston Daily
				Freeman</title>, Feb. 13, 1950, p. 11</p>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="government of"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="U.S. occupation of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="in Japan"/>
		<index level1="MacArthur, Douglas"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<div type="section">
			<head>STATMENT BY MARGARET SANGER</head>
			<dateline>RELEASED <date value="1951-02-13">FEBRUARY 13, 1950</date>
			</dateline>
			<p>I must refuse to accept as final the reported decision of <person
					reg="MacArthur, Douglas">Gen. MacArthur</person> that I may not come to
					<place>Japan</place> at the invitation of the Japanese. That an American can be
				barred from a perfectly proper mission by the bigotry or whim of other Americans is
				intolerable.</p>
			<p>This is not the first time I was told I could not visit Japan. In 1921 I was refused
				permission by the Imperial <org reg="Japan Government">Japanese government</org>. It
				is tragic to see that our <org
					reg="United States Supreme Commander of Allied Powers">Occupation
					authorities</org>, while mouthing democratic principles, are emulating the old
				Japanese military regime. However, in 1921 the angry protests of the people forced
				the lifting of the ban. I am confident that something of the same sort will occur in
				1950.</p>
			<p>When I asked to have Gen. MacArthur reconsider the refusal to admit me, I believed he
				meant what he was quoted as saying last July--<q who="MACDO">that birth control was
					a matter for the Japanese people and the Occupation had a policy of hands
					off.</q> I hope that this attitude will be resumed. Anything else is a denial of
				the right of the Japanese to decent and healthy family life. Anything else is a
				denial of the basic democracy which we are trying to help this people achieve.</p>
			<p>My invitation came from the press, health officials and private groups. They wanted
				me to advise them on carrying out their new laws which legalize birth control,
				because they know that it is the only way to halt the disastrous rise in
				population.</p>
			<p>If I can help them in applying their new laws on birth control, I mean to do so. I
				shall continue to work for a reversal of any ruling that seeks to stop me.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head>Mrs. Slee Says She Was Denied Entry By U.S. Authorities</head>
			<dateline><place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Ariz.</place>, <date>Feb. 13</date>. (<org
					reg="Associated Press">AP</org>)--</dateline>
			<p>
				<q who="KDF">A noted authority on birth control says she twice has been denied
					permission to enter Japan.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="KDF">Margaret Sanger Slee said yesterday she applied for permission last
					August and was turned down. In September she asked that the denial be
					reviewed.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="KDF">She said she was told a cable had been sent to the theatre commander
					(Gen. Douglas MacArthur) and he declined to review her application.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"I don't believe the refusal is consistent with a statement General MacArthur
				released to the press on July 6, 1949,"<q who="KDF">Mrs. Slee said.</q> "He said
				that United States officials would keep hands off the new Japanese law on birth
				control--that it did not come within the scope of occupation.</p>
			<p>
				<q who="KDF">A recent law permits both birth control and sterilization.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="KDF">Mrs. Slee said she had received many invitations to enter Japan,
					including a personal invitation from the Japanese minister of welfare, and one
					from Mrs. Shizue Kato, former member of the Japanese Diet.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="KDF">She had been asked to serve as consultant in organizing a group to
					promote birth control among the poorer people of Tokyo, Mrs. Slee added.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
