<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2011-08-05 NC</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-03-26 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-10 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1952-02-08">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">08 Feb 1952</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Message to the Planned Parenthood Association Chicago
					Area</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp228448</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S77:67</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger dictated this message by phone to <person reg="McKinnon, Edna">Mrs. Edna
				McKinnon</person> to be read at the annual meeting of <org>Planned Parenthood
				Association Chicago Area</org>.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Long distance call to Mrs. Edna McKinnon-</head>
		<p>Message for Annual meeting-Chicago-</p>
		<p> Please convey my congratulations to the Chicago Planned Parenthood Association on the
			splendid work accomplished. Greater horizons and greater efforts will be presented to
			your group by Dr. <person reg="Stone, Abraham">Stone</person>. The entire world, and in
			particular <place>Asia</place>, looks to us to lead them toward a planned population on
			the road to International peace.</p>
		<p>Your loyal supporters have helped us endure the struggles, discouragements and kept the
			movement advancing against religious intolerance and dogmas. More than forty-three
			countries throughout the world now have inspiring groups ready to work provided they
			have films, literature, translations. The movement has been maintained through tincup
			contributions, comparatively pennies. Today the world movement demands larger concepts,
			and efforts. We must now think in terms of millions if we would help maintain a balanced
			world population and ultimately world peace.</p>
		<p> Margaret Sanger </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
