<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2001-08-20 PB Transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-09 CH encoded</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1944-09-02">2 Sept 1944</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Russia's Rublebabies</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp232887</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">New Leader</title>, Sept. 2, 1944, p. 4</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S72:451</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For draft version see Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections, S72: 418,
			420, 422, 428, and 438. For page proofs, see Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College
			Collections S72:446.</p>
		<index level1="Russia" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Russia" level2="population policies"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>RUSSIA'S RUBLEBABIES</head>
		<byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p>
			<place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>, alarmed at her tremendous military and
			civilian losses, has fallen prey to one of the greatest fallacies in attempting to
			rebuild her population--she is going to pay her women to have babies. She is going to
			pay her gallant, courageous, uncomplaining women to give up their new found freedom and
			become breeders for the state. Women who have stood shoulder to shoulder with their men
			through the greatest crisis of Russian history, who have helped design bridges and run
			dynamos, who have assumed leadership of communes and been responsible for the food
			supplies for thousands, women who have faced the enemy in hand-to-hand battle, are now
			being asked to breed babies as fast as possible in return for cash, gifts and a medal to
			pin on their coats.</p>
		<p> Almost every nation, particularly the warrior nations, have tried the artificial
			stimulation of their birthrates at one time or another and in every case their
			population has shown little or no increase. <place>Italy</place>’s birthrate showed
			little response to <person reg="Mussolini, Benito">Mussolini</person>’s baby bonuses,
			and while <person reg="Hitler, Adolf">Hitler</person> was able to jack up the production
			of infant <org reg="National Socialist German Worker's Party (Nazi)">Nazis</org>, the
			peak which he achieved briefly in 1939 has quickly declined to below the 1933 level. In
			neither case was it possible to achieve anything like the steady increase, which has
			characterized the Swedish and Dutch birthrates where the emphasis has long been placed
			upon intelligent, responsible parenthood.</p>
		<p>
			<place>Sweden</place>, whose birthrate has been rising since 1933, has used planned
			parenthood as the foundation of its program for expansion. Swedish mothers are given
			every encouragement in the form of preferred housing accommodations for larger families,
			tax exemptions and other benefits, but they are also provided with the best medical
			advice on contraception and family planning. Sweden’s birthrate has responded because
			her women knew that while the State was eager for more babies, it made it possible for
			its women to choose the best time to bear them. Unlike Russia, Sweden never subscribed
			to a program of wholesale abortion, recognizing that adequate knowledge of contraception
			is by far the better, wiser and happier course.</p>
		<p> In Russia I pleaded for the adoption of contraception to take the place of abortion as a
			more humane and less dangerous method of birth control. But the Russian doctors showed
			little interest. They said that so long as the women had to depend upon them for
			abortions the population of Russia could be controlled. Once adequate knowledge of
			contraception was made available, the women themselves would be helpless to enforce its
			edicts. Apparently the time for such enforcement has come, for the new edict
			specifically outlaws abortion and makes no mention of providing other means by which
			women may plan their families by choice instead of by chance.</p>
		<p> The mass production of babies should never be an assembly line operation. The
			intelligent women of today are willing to lend their bodies and their emotions to such a
			project even for the most lavish remuneration, and certainly the women of modern Russia
			cannot be expected to respond to the paltry $4 or so a month that the State proposes to
			contribute to the support of each child in families numbering more than three.</p>
		<p> The edict, a complete English translation of which appears in the July 25, 1944, edition
			of the <title type="journal">Information Bulletin</title> published by the <org
				reg="Soviet Union Embassy to United States, Washington, DC">Embassy of the Union of
				Soviet Socialist Republics in Washington, D. C.</org>, is divided into five parts:
			the first provides an increase in State aid to mothers of large families beginning with
			the third child; the second increases the privileges of expectant and nursing mothers
			and offers expanded institutional facilities for the care of children whose parents are
			unable to raise them; the third introduces a system of medals and honorary titles to
			mothers of five or more living children; the fourth imposes a tax on single men and
			women and those with one or two children over 20 years of age; and the fifth makes
			radical changes in the marriage and divorce laws and prohibits abortion. </p>
		<p> Much of the edict, namely the provisions for better maternal health care for working
			mothers, the granting of leaves of absence before and immediately after the birth of a
			baby and the increase in nursery facilities to care for the children of employed
			mothers, is sound and someone in the <org reg="Soviet Union Government">Russian
				Government</org> is to be congratulated on its far-sightedness. But the main
			provisions of the edict represent the relocking of the chains of slavery which the women
			of Russia have so recently shaken loose. </p>
		<p> When I was in Russia in 1934 with my son <person reg="Sanger, Grant">Grant</person>,
			then a young medical student, we talked to leading doctors and women of all ages and
			occupations. It was one of their greatest boasts and sources of pride that Russia was
			the only country in the world where a woman could fully and completely control her own
			biological destiny by choosing the time of her pregnancy or by refusing to become a
			mother until she really wanted to have children.</p>
		<p> Childbearing in Russia was placed upon the highest and truest basis; the desire of a
			woman to have a baby because she wanted to create a new life and was prepared to love
			and care for it. The love of children has and always will be the finest, the most noble,
			and certainly the most civilized, reason for having them.</p>
		<p> The new edict, while ignoring this basic reason for childbearing, ironically provides
			for the prosecution of anyone found guilty of “humiliating the dignity of mothers.” What
			greater humiliation of motherhood is possible than to ask women to have babies for the
			State, to have babies for medals, to have babies for money; and of course for a
			dictatorship and for future wars?</p>
		<p> For the Russian government, overlooking the fact that the desire and love of child is in
			itself one of life’s greatest glories, has set about to “glorify the role of
			motherhood.” A woman with five living children is entitled to a Motherhood Medal, Second
			Class. Six children makes her eligible for a First Class Medal and with the birth of her
			seventh, eight and ninth babies she progresses through the three classes of the Order of
			the Glory of Motherhood, arriving upon the birth of her tenth as a Mother Heroine, with
			a scroll duly inscribed by the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR. (This edict
			has scored one on the <org reg="Roman Catholic Church">Vatican</org>.)</p>
		<p> To reinforce this offer of greater glory the State is to make an outright gift of 400
			rubles (approximately $80) upon the birth of the third child and increase this to 1,300
			rubles upon the birth of the fourth child together with an allowance of $4 a month for
			each of the four children.</p>
		<p> From this point the gifts and monthly allowances increase up to $1,000 outright and $60
			a month for the eleventh child, until the youngest reaches its fifth birthday. After
			that they are all on their own. A little mathematics will dispel the assumption that
			this is a generous and humane award. The offer of rubles for babies is one of the most
			degrading ways of increasing the birth rate for it appeals only to mothers who are
			already ground down by poverty and poor living conditions and who will seize upon any
			device to augment the family income.</p>
		<p> Intelligent parents will doubtless prefer to pay the relatively small tax (6 per cent of
			their income if they have no children, 1 per cent if they have one child and 1/2 per
			cent if they have two children) rather than increase their family beyond their desires
			and ability to properly feed and house them.</p>
		<p> For housing is and will continue to be a problem in Russia. Five families living in a
			five room apartment is not uncommon and a good deal more than an additional $4 a month,
			and a medal, will be needed if each family decides to heed the government’s edict.
			Actually in a family of five children the monthly allotment of 140 rubles amounts to
			about 15 cents a day for each child. The children, of necessity, will all be small and
			of an age that requires the greatest amount of shoes, winter clothing, nourishing food
			and other essentials for good health and proper development. One cannot but feel that
			fifteen additional cents a day will provide little above the slum standards in the way
			of food, clothing and shelter. </p>
		<p> It seems absurdly shortsighted to advocate increasing numbers of babies without
			providing adequate space, room and light for that increase. Even the “bourgeois”
					<org reg="Glasgow Municipal Housing Project"><place reg="Glasgow, Scotland">Glasgow</place> Municipality’s Housing
				Project</org> of thirty years ago had built houses and apartments limiting the
			number of people in each place, so as to insure space and light and warmth for those
			dwelling therein. Our own housing project in <place reg="United States">U.S.A</place>.
			has specified standards of the conditions of living space and the number who shall
			inhabit each room.</p>
		<p> The gift of rubles is doubtless supposed to be the answer to increasing needs of the
			increasing family; but as the number of infants multiplies and men and women return from
			fields of battle, the demand for living quarters will far exceed the supply. The rubles
			given will be lessened in value as the scarcity of room increases. How many children can
			be crowded into an already overcrowded home? Are provisions being made for increasing
			living quarters as the family increases? Is there to be more space, more light, more
			room and comforts for the children or just more babies? Will rubles alone provide these
			necessities? The answer is NO.</p>
		<p> But even if the government were prepared to lavish money upon the space for the children
			it wants to “buy” into the world, it cannot escape from the fact that it is rebuilding
			its postwar population from the bottom. It is rebuilding it with subsidies, which, even
			under the most generous condition, are at best an artificial and makeshift measure.</p>
		<p>
			<place reg="Moscow, Soviet Union">Moscow</place> will reply that Russia’s population has
			been decimated by the war and the urgent need is to replace it as quickly as possible by
			any means at hand. Babies and more babies are needed and there is no time to split hairs
			over the quality of the parents who produce them. But is this not the very time to be
			most concerned with the quality of the world’s future citizens? Is this not the very
			time to start out with a clean slate and avoid the mistakes which have cost us so much
			human suffering and misery in the past?</p>
		<p> During the early phases of the war when <place reg="London, England">London</place>’s
			disease and vermin infested slums were crumpled to dust, Britishers realized that the
			war which was robbing them of many of their magnificent churches and historical
			landmarks was also clearing away one of their never ending sources of infection and
			tragedy. On this cleared ground London’s slums will not be rebuilt as they were, but
			will rise as modern housing projects designed for healthier and better living.</p>
		<p> So too, should it be with the population which this war has wiped out. Every country has
			lost a priceless heritage of vigorous young men who could have fathered fine healthy
			children. Every country has witnesses the loss of blood lines it will be impossible to
			replace. But many countries have also been relived of the pressure of over-population
			which existed before the war and which in itself is one of the economic causes for armed
			conflict. The rebuilding of these populations should be done slowly and with care lest a
			generation hence we find ourselves just where we were at the outset of this war and
			discover that in our haste to make up our losses we have bred from our morons and
			erected the same old human slums instead of the finer loftier structures we could have
			planned.</p>
		<p> The day is past when a man must have many sons to till his soil and harvest his crops.
			The day is past when industry cries for an unlimited supply of cheap labor to be
			exhausted and cast aside and replaced from a bottomless human reservoir. No country
			today, unless it is consciously planning for military conquest, needs the quantity of
			population which was once considered necessary for national life.</p>
		<p> What the future will need is men and women sound in body and mind endowed with vision,
			character, imagination and integrity, easily adaptable to the new scientifically
			propelled world which lies before us. This need will be more true twenty years from now
			when today’s babies, whether they are born for rubles or for love, are grown to man’s
			estate. The world needs a generation of babies born to healthy intelligent parents who
			recognize parenthood as one of the most important and gratifying of life’s
			responsibilities, not to the type who can be talked into the creation of a new life for
			the sake of adding a few rubles to the family income and wearing a Second Class
			motherhood medal on their chests.</p>
		<p> May the Russian women arise and throw these rubles and medals into the faces of the male
			dictators who insult unborn generations as those whose claim to life is to the Russian
			ruble for a military, arrogant dictatorship. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
