<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-23 JC transcribed and encoding</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-27 JC corrections made</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1937-02-21">21 Feb 1937</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Chandler Speech Notes on Gandhi and India </supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236409</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection </bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S71:967</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<name id="GANMO">Gandhi, Mohandas K.</name>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>These notes were probably used for a speech Sanger gave at the <org>San Marcos
				Hotel</org> in <place reg="Chandler, AZ">Chandler, Arizona</place>.</p>
		<index level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="India"/>
		<index level1="Gandhi, Mohandas K."/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p><emph rend="underline"><person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Gandhi</person></emph>--<place
				reg="Wardha, India">Wardha</place>--</p>
		<p>Now 73 has been the outstanding mass leader of <place>India</place> for nearly a quarter
			of a century since 1919--</p>
		<p>He has dramatized his leadership by his campaign for the revival of hand spinning &amp;
			cottage industries &amp; the use of home spun cotton cloth. All a unique flow against
			the principal British export to India Gandhi has been a leader not only of the poverty
			stricken ignorant peasant but the chosen leader of industrialists, landlords, &amp;
			students &amp; professional classes. Middle educated classes, intellectuals also Indian
			financiers</p>
		<p>His outstanding contribution to India is that he inspired the semi-starved illiterate
			weaponless millions of India to a new confidence &amp; new hope &amp; gave them the
			value &amp; effectiveness of mass action even tho that action was passive &amp; non
			resistance. He taught them in true Hindu religion to endure beatings, starvation,
			imprisonment, physical injuries &amp; tortures, yes even death without yielding.</p>
		<p>My invitation to India--</p>
		<p>The <org reg="All-India Woman's Conference">All Indian Womans Congress</org> to keep
			getting a resolution passed to place the teaching of contraception in Public Health
			Services in all communities throughout India--a noted &amp; advanced step courageously
			out usually in any other organized womans organization in the world--Representing
			millions of Indian women all classes, all religions--on of the most brilliant groups of
			women I ever met anywhere--parallel only with the modern women of
			<place>China</place>--</p>
		<p>Met at the Boat in <place reg="Bombay, India">Bombay</place> by Courier from Gandhi &amp;
			representatives of various organizations </p>
		<p>Note from Gandhi--<q who="GANMO">"no masters, no servants"</q></p>
		<p>India a land of contrasts</p>
		<p>The highest mountains the</p>
		<p>Five thousand years of continuing--culture--</p>
		<p>Every form of organized life political &amp; social has been lived there-- &amp; over
			tried out &amp; more often abandoned-- you can find out any question you might like to
			know.</p>
		<p>Gandhi left the <org reg="Indian National Congress">Nat Congress</org> as a member in
			1934--</p>
		<p>How is it he has so much influence on the Congress</p>
		<p>Would you characterize Gandhi as one with a love of personal power?</p>
		<p>Do you think Gandhi's astuteness is expressed in the Salt March 1930--</p>
		<p>entitles him to political leadership as compared to <person reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal"
				>Nehru</person></p>
		<p>Sir <person reg="Cripps, Stafford">Stafford Cripps</person> proposal for the government
			seemed in the face of it very reasonable considering the large religious elements he had
			to contend with. Why rejected</p>
		<p><name type="law" reg="Indian Arms Act, 1878">Arms Act 1879</name> penal officers to
			possess a gun or weapon</p>
		<p>Jawaharlal Nehru--a Kashmiri Brahman son of a <person reg="Nehru, Motilal">great
				lawyer</person> &amp; political leader a member of one of the wealthiest, the
			flooded, Aristocratic families a geneology of poets, salacious aristocrats that should
				<del>part</del>
			<add>give</add> the second rate, British civil employed <del>awarded</del> a respect for
			the thousands of similar families he has come to rule--</p>
		<p>invested the <org reg="United Kingdom Government">British Government</org> was over
			central of India from the <org reg="East India Company">East India Co.</org> in 1858
			&amp; they assumed a debt of 70 million pounds in 1914-- $1,350,000</p>
		<p>As these developed for British inventory India became politically unified awaking to her
			own wrongs &amp; desires</p>
		<p>The British policy toward India throughout the 19th century was that India was to be
			reduced to an agricultural country so that an Indian market for British goods could be
			developed.</p>
		<p>This manufacturing industry had to be curtailed &amp; the production &amp; export of raw
			materials in India had to expand.</p>
		<p>This policy required the construction of R. R. roads, ports, postal &amp; telegraphic
			services, irrigation projects, educational system on the English order to train clerks
			&amp; subordinate members of the civil service--a banking system huge sums &amp; British
			capital were <gap extent="rest of draft" reason="missing"/></p>
		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
