<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-07-28 CH transcribe and encode--used the proofread copy of the 4th edition
			and edited for changes.</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-00-00">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">1922</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Family Limitation, Twelfth Edition</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp238150</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>,
				S76:978</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="LAT">Latin</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This is a major revision of Sanger's 1914 <xref from="238157.xml">Family
				Limitation</xref>; likely published in 1922. For other versions included in the
			digital edition, see <xref from="320146.xml">Family Limitation</xref>, 8th edition,
			1918, <xref from="320179.xml">Family Limitation</xref>, 9th edition, 1919, and a draft of
			revisions for <xref from="129001.xml">Family Limitation</xref>, ca. 1936. For additional
			editions, see the Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections, Collected
			Documents Series and Library of Congress Microfilm.</p>
		<index level1="abortion"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="efficacy of"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="condom"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="douche"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="instructions"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="male"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="pessaries"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="safe period"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="sponge"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="suppository"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="withdrawal"/>
		<index level1="Family Limitation"/>
		<index level1="Family Limitation" level2="suppression of"/>
		<index level1="menstruation"/>
		<index level1="women and girls" level2="sexuality of"/>
		<index level1="women and girls" level2="working class"/>
		<index level1="sex and sexuality" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="sex education" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head> FAMILY LIMITATION</head>
		<byline>By Margaret Sanger<lb/><emph rend="underline">REVISED</emph> Twelfth
			Edition</byline>
		<div type="section">
			<p>There are three methods of Birth Control:<lb/>Absolute Continence,<lb/>
				Sterilization,<lb/> The use of appliances that prevent conception.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">INTRODUCTION</head>
			<p>Birth Control or family limitation has been recommended by some of the leading
				physicians of the United States and of Europe. While the medical profession as a
				whole has not yet taken a united stand upon the subject, we know that the practice
				of birth control has already been incorporated into the private moral code of
				millions of the most intelligent and respected families in every country.</p>
			<p>There is little doubt but that its general practice among married persons will
				shortly win full acceptation and sanction by public authorities, who will encourage
				the practice among the diseased and unfit and help to direct the movement into its
				proper channels.</p>
			<p>In cases of women suffering from serious ailments, such as Bright's disease, heart
				disease, or tuberculosis, the physician usually warns the woman to guard herself
				against pregnancy. It is an established fact that two-thirds of women who die from
				the above-named diseases do so because they have become pregnant. Therefore, it is
				imperative that physicians should not only warn women suffering from these diseases
				against pregnancy, but they should see that they are properly instructed in methods
				to prevent conception. Such responsibility on the part of physicians would reduce
				the maternal mortality of the world tremendously.</p>
			<p>While the above-named diseases are not considered transmissible from the mother to
				the child, there are certain other diseases and conditions such as insanity,
				syphilis, idiocy and feeble-mindedness which are passed to the next generation.</p>
			<p>When either the man or the woman is afflicted with any one of these diseases, it is
				absolutely wrong to allow a child to be born. In such cases the man or the woman
				should be sterilized.</p>
			<p>The patient should understand that such an operation does not deprive him or her or
				sexual desire or expression. It simply renders the patient incapable of producing
				children.</p>
			<p>To conserve the lives of mothers and to prevent the birth of diseased or defective
				children are objects for which we need a sound educational campaign for Birth
				Control. </p>
			<p>We hold that children should be:<list>
					<item>1. Conceived in love.</item>
					<item>2. Born of the mother's conscious desire.</item>
					<item>3. And only begotten under conditions which render possible the heritage
						of health.</item>
				</list></p>
			<p>We want parents to be conscious of their responsibility to the race in bringing
				children into the world. Instead of a blind and haphazard consequence of
				uncontrolled instinct, parenthood must be made the responsible and self-directed
				means of human expression and regeneration.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">TO THE WORKING WOMAN</head>
			<p>The need for safe practical information of birth control is more urgent today among
				women that it has ever been before.</p>
			<p>The working man and woman have begun to realize the difficulty of supporting a family
				of eight or ten children on a wage scarcely sufficient to decently keep two or
				three. They have also begun to realize that no increase of wages, obtained through
				long days of toil or through strikes or lockouts, can keep pace with the increased
				cost of living or the cost of an ever-increasing family. </p>
			<p>It is the big battalions of unwanted babies that make life so hard for the wife of
				the workingman. It is the ever-increasing number of children, coming year after year
				into her life, that perpetuates poverty and misery and ignorance from generation to
				generation.</p>
			<p>The working mother knows through her natural instinct that she should not have more
				children than her husband's wages can support, yet she does not know what she can do
				to prevent conception. When she asks her friends or neighbors for advice, she is
				given remedies, usually unscientific, unauthoritative and unreliable, which her
				experience or knowledge warns her may be injurious.</p>
			<p>So she is thrust back upon the possibility of taking drugs for producing abortion, or
				resigning herself to all the children nature will give her, which can mean from ten
				to twenty in one woman's house. </p>
			<p>These women resent the fact that the educated women are able to obtain safe,
				scientific, harmless information of birth control, while Society condemns its use
				among the working women. Present day Society is generous in doling out pittances for
				the unfit and diseased, thus encouraging their multiplication and perpetuation,
				while it prevents and discourages the use of scientific knowledge which would enable
				women to avoid bringing into the world children they cannot feed, clothe, or care
				for. </p>
			<p>I give herewith the knowledge obtained through study and through more than fourteen
				years' experience as a trained nurse in the <place reg="United States"
					>U.S.A.</place></p>
			<p>My own experience as a mother of three children has modified some of the advice given
				in books.</p>
			<p>It is my intention to present the facts to the reader in the simplest language,
				leaving out dogmas or religious accompaniment.</p>
			<p>While there are various mechanical instruments often used to prevent conception, I
				will not give them here, because my experience has taught me that they are likely to
				cause irritation and trouble to the woman. There is sufficient information given
				here, which if followed, will prevent a woman from becoming pregnant unless she
				wishes to do so. It must not be forgotten that the best results can be obtained only
				when the woman will see that, in every case, she follows directions. She must not
				get careless, even once, for it needs only one union in twelve months, unprotected,
				to give a woman a baby each year. Therefore to protect herself from pregnancy the
				woman must use care constantly.</p>
			<p>While it may be troublesome to get up to douche, and a nuisance to have to watch the
				date of the menstrual period, and to some it may seem sordid and inartistic to
				insert a pessary or a suppository in anticipation of the sexual act, it may be far
				more sordid and the condition far worse than inartistic a few years later for the
				mother to find herself burdened down with half a dozen "accidental" children,
				unwanted, helpless, shoddily clothed, sometimes starved or undernourished, dragging
				at her skirt, while she becomes a worn out shadow of the woman she once was.</p>
			<p>It takes but a few years of continued pregnancies to break a woman's health. The
				drain on the family income is continually increasing and the standard of the whole
				family is lowered.</p>
			<p>Mothers--do not be over-sentimental in this important phase of hygiene. Learn the
				facts of pregnancy. The inevitable face is that, unless you prevent the male sperm
				from entering the womb, you are liable to become pregnant.</p>
			<p>Women of the working class should not have more than two children today. The
				conditions of society do not render possible the proper care of more than this
				number. The average wage-earner can take care of no more than this in decent
				fashion.</p>
			<p>It has been my experience that women desire only the number of children they can
				properly care for, but that they are compelled to have them from carelessness, or
				through ignorance of the methods to prevent conception.</p>
			<p>It is only the workers who are ignorant of the means to prevent bringing children
				into the world. It is also mainly their children who fill the child labor records,
				the factories, mills, jails, hospitals, poor houses. It is the workers' children who
				compete with the parents in the labor market for their daily bread, thereby reducing
				the wages of the parents--an inevitable consequence when the supply is greater than
				the demand.</p>
			<p>Women of the world arise--let us close the gates of our bodies against the diseased,
				the unfit, and bring to birth only the best, as we know it, which shoold be, at
				least, a child with a sound body and a sound mind.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">IS THERE A SAFE PERIOD?</head>
			<p>There is current among people an idea that conception can take place at only certain
				times of the month. For instance: ten days after the menstrual period, and four or
				five days before the next period. This is not to be relied upon at all, for it has
				been proven again and again that a woman can conceive at any time in the month. Do
				not depend upon this belief, for there is not reliable foundation for it. There is
				also the knowledge that nursing after childbirth prevents the return of the
				menstrual flow for several months and conception does not take place. It is well not
				to depend upon this too much, especially after the fifth or sixth month, for often a
				woman becomes pregnant again without having "seen anything" or without her realizing
				that she has become pregnant. She thus finds herself with one at the breast and
				another in the womb. Use some preventive.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">COITUS INTERRUPTUS</head>
			<p>Perhaps the commonest preventive excepting the use of the condom is "<foreign
					lang="LAT">Coitus Interruptus</foreign>," or withdrawal of the penis from the
				vagina shortly before the ejection of the semen. No one can doubt that in theory
				this should be a perfectly safe method; and we also find authorities who claim it is
				not injurious to the man, but who object to it on the grounds of lack of
				satisfaction to the woman.</p>
			<p>The claim is that id she has not completed her desire, she is under a highly nervous
				tension, her whole being is perhaps on the verge of satisfaction and she is left in
				this dissatisfied state. This without doubt, does her injury. A mutual and satisfied
				sexual act is of great benefit to the average woman, the magnetism of it is
				health-giving. When it is not desired on the part of the woman and she has no
				response, it should not take place. The submission of her body without love or
				desire is degrading to the woman's finer sensibility, all the marriage certificates
				on earth to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
			<p>During several years past, however, I have come in contact with thousands of men and
				women who have given me their confidence and experience along these lines. The
				consensus of opinion seems to be that there are many men who prefer to practice the
				method of withdrawal and have been able to control the ejaculation until after the
				woman's orgasm. If this is done, all objections affecting the woman's satisfaction
				are of course removed. But the fact remains that even in such cases, with the
				strongest control on the part of the man, we find that pregnancy does take place.
				This is often due to some slight disposal on the part of the man to a seminal
				leakage, in which the spermatozoa escape from the male organs without the man's
				knowledge and before the ejaculation.</p>
			<p>A woman's physician examined a vaginal passage and found sperm deposits when
				absolutely no ejaculation had taken place. The results of these inquiries are
				sufficient for us to say that the practice of withdrawal cannot always be counted
				upon as a safe preventive.</p>
			<p>Again, while in the quest of information regarding this practice, I have had many men
				say that their nervous system had suffered decidedly bad effects from this method
				and upon using another, at once an improved condition was felt.</p>
			<p> Here we see how very individual all methods of birth control really are. What may
				give happiness and good results to one may prove injurious to another. But coitus
				interruptus or withdrawal is by no means to be counted upon as either the safest or
				the best method of preventing conception. There are other methods more to be
				recommended. </p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">DOUCHE A CLEANSER--NOT A PREVENTIVE</head>
			<p>Although an antiseptic douche is an important factor in preventing conception, it
				should not be relied upon as a preventive method in itself. A douche is a cleanser,
				but it is not of itself to be advised as a reliable method to prevent conception.
				When one understands how conception takes place, it can be seen at once that it is
				quite possible for a woman to be in a state of pregnancy before she leaves the bed,
				or before she can reach a douche, unless the womb has been previously covered with
				the rubber pessary, or by the ingredients of a suppository.</p>
			<p>Nevertheless, every woman should learn to cleanse herself thoroughly by means of the
				vaginal douche. Some women object to the use of the suppository because of its
				lubricant effect; this can be modified greatly by the use of a warm salt douche,
				taken just previously to inserting the suppository, cleaning the parts thoroughly of
				any secretion already there.</p>
			<p>Every woman should possess a good two quart rubber douche bag, called a fountain
				syringe. Hang it high enough to secure a good, strong, steady flow.</p>
			<p>Bulb syringes, such as the whirling spray syringes have been found satisfactory by
				many women for the purpose, especially where there is no bath room or toilet
				conveniences, as the bulb syringe can easily be used in the privacy of one's bedroom
				over a vessel. Directions for use come with each syringe.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">HOW TO TAKE A DOUCHE</head>
			<p>If you have bathing conveniences, go as quickly as possible to the bath room after
				the sexual act and prepare a douche. Lie down upon the back in the bath tub. Hang
				the filled douche bag high over the tub, and let the water flow freely into the
				vagina, to wash out the male sperm which was deposited there during the act.</p>
			<p>Do not be afraid to assist the cleansing by introducing the first finger with the
				tube and washing out the semen from the folds of the membrane. One can soon learn to
				tell by the feeling when it is sufficiently clean. It is said, that the French women
				are the most thorough douchers in the world, which helps greatly in keeping the
				organs in a clean and healthy condition, as well as preventing the male sperm from
				reaching the womb to mate with the ovum.</p>
			<p>When there are no bath room conveniences--a douche can be taken over the toilet, or
				when that is impossible, it can be taken over a vessel in a squatting position.</p>
			<p>Many women have been advised by physicians to use an antiseptic douche as a means to
				prevent conception. I do not advise any woman who desires to avoid pregnancy, to
				rely upon a douche for a contraceptive. I wish to emphasize again that a douche used
				alone is not a contraceptive, because the germ from the male may already have
				entered the mouth of the womb before a woman can use a douche. Therefore it is
				absolutely necessary that some method be used to cover the womb. </p>
			<p>A douche is a cleanser. It is a means of hygiene rather than a preventive. Do not
				depend on a douche to prevent conception. Some women have been successful in using
				this for many years and then later on, to their surprise, find that pregnancy has
				occurred. The explanation is as follows:</p>
			<p>When the womb is placed high out of the vagina it is not so easy for the germ for the
				man to reach directly into the womb. In such cases it is possible for a woman to get
				up and prepare a douche before the germ from the male enters the womb. There are
				times, however, when a woman has been standing on her feet, washing or ironing or
				working, and becomes overtired. At such times the womb is pulled or dragged down
				into the canal of the vagina. At such times if intercourse takes place, it is much
				easier for the seed from the male to enter directly into the womb, unless there is
				some protection. It is at such times that a woman who has previously depended upon a
				douche as a preventive finds it has failed.</p>
			<p>May advice is--never depend upon a douche alone. It should be used after the use of a
				suppository or any other preventive.</p>
			<p>Cold water douches are not advised as there is a tendency to chill and shock the
				nervous system. A warm or moderate douche is advised.</p>
			<p>Warm soapsuds as a douche are used by women in <place>France</place> in the rural
				districts, just plain common soap, as a cleansing douche after the act.</p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">SOLUTIONS FOR DOUCHING</head>
			<p>Following are some of the solutions to be used for the douche which, when carefully
				used will kill the male sperm or prevent its entering the womb:</p>
			<p>Lysol--is a brown oily liquid which added to water forms a clear soapy solution.</p>
			<p>One teaspoonful of lysol to 2 quarts of water (warm) makes a good solution for
				douching. Mix into a pitcher or vessel before placing it in the bag.</p>
			<p>Creosol is said to be the equivalent chemically of lysol and is likely to be obtained
				at a lower cost. Directions are much the same as those for the use of lysol.</p>
			<p>Potassium Permanganate--This also makes a good solution, especially where there is a
				vaginal discharge. The special objection to this is that it stains the skin and
				clothing. This can be purchased in crystal form, and one teaspoonful dissolved in
				two quarts of water is the proper strength.</p>
			<p>Salt solution--Mix four tablespoonsful of table salt in two quarts of warm or cold
				water and dissolve thoroughly. This is good, and cheap.</p>
			<p>Vinegar solution--Many peasants in <place>Europe</place> use vinegar as an antiseptic
				almost exclusively. One glassful to two quarts of water is the strength usually
				desired. Douche afterward with clear water.</p>
			<p>Acetic acid being the sperm-killing agent in vinegar may also be used and with the
				certainty of more uniformity than can be depended upon in the various grades of
				vinegar. A good solution is one and a half teaspoonfuls of 36 per cent acetic acid
				to two quarts of warm water.</p>
			<p>Plain water douche-- This will sometimes remove the semen quite effectively without
				the aid of an antiseptic. But as the semen can hide itself away in the wrinkled
				lining of the vaginal cavity, the plain water will only impede its progress for a
				time. Some ingredient which will kill the sperm is to be more relied upon.</p>
			<p>Some women use the douche before the sexual act as a preventive. It this is done, any
				astringent such as boric acid, alum, citric acid, hydrochlorate of quinine used in
				the solution will do. Only a pint of solution is needed for this purpose, following
				the act a larger douche is used as a cleanser. This can also be done with the
				regular antiseptic douche. </p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">THE USE OF THE CONDOM OR "COTS".</head>
			<p>These are made of soft tissues which envelope the male organ (penis) completely and
				serve to catch the semen at the time of the act. In this way the sperm does not
				enter the vagina nor the womb.</p>
			<p>The condoms are obtainable at all drug stores at various prices. There are some of
				skin gut and some of rubber tissue. While the rubber condom is best known, there is
				found to be the least objection to those made of soft skin gut. The skin condom is
				made more durable and more agreeable to use, if kept in denatured alcohol. Alcohol
				sterilizes and toughens the membrane. The condom should be washed before and after
				putting it into the jar or alcohol and should be kept tightly corked. It is almost
				impossible to keep skin condoms satisfactorily if they are dried. If properly
				adjusted they will not break. Fear of breaking is the main objection to their use.
				If space has not been allowed for expansion of the penis, at the time the semen is
				expelled, the tissue is likely to split and the sperm finds its way into the uterus.
				The woman becomes pregnant without being conscious of it. If on the other hand care
				is given to the adjustment of the condom, not fitting it too close, it will act as
				one of the best protectors against both conception and venereal disease. Care must
				be exercised in withdrawing the penis after the act, not to allow the condom to peel
				off, thereby allowing the semen to pass into the vagina.</p>
			<p>It is desirable to discard the condom after it has been used once unless with certain
				precautions. If it has to be used again care must be taken to wash the condom in an
				antiseptic solution before drying it and placing it away for further use. A weak
				solution of lysol is excellent for the rubber condom.</p>
			<p>The condom should be well lubricated with oil before penetration. It should always be
				tested for holes or breaks before using.</p>
			<p>The condom is one of the most commonly known preventives in the <place>United
					States</place>. It has another value quite apart from prevention in decreasing
				the tendency in the male to arrive at the climax in the sexual act before the
				female.</p>
			<p>There are few men and women so perfectly mated that the climax of the act is reached
				together. It is usual for the male to arrive at this stage earlier than the female,
				with the consequence that he is further incapacitated to satisfy her desire for some
				time after. During this time the woman is in a highly nervous condition, and it is
				the opinion of the best medical authorities that a continuous condition of this
				unsatisfied state brings on or causes disease of her generative organs, besides
				giving her a perfect horror and repulsion for the sexual act.</p>
			<p>Thousands of well-meaning men ask the advice of physicians as to the cause of the
				sexual coldness and indifference in their wives. Nine times out of ten it is the
				fault of the man, who through ignorance and selfishness and inconsiderateness, has
				satisfied his own desire and promptly gone off to sleep. The woman in self defense
				has learned to protect herself from the long hours of sleepless nights and nervous
				tension by refusing to become interested.</p>
			<p>The condom will often help in this difficulty. There are many girls who have had no
				education on this subject, no idea of the physiology of the act, who upon any
				contact of the semen have a disgust and repulsion, from which it takes some time to
				recover. Much depends upon the education of the girl, but more depends upon the
				attitude of the man toward the relation.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">THE PESSARY--RUBBER WOMB CAP</head>
			<p>Another form of prevention is the pessary or rubber womb cap. These come in various
				forms and sizes, the Dutch Mensinga with its ten or twelve sizes, the Matrisaulus,
				used also in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> and <place>Germany</place>,
				the French cap-shaped, the <person reg="Haire, Norman">Haire</person> pessary used
				largely in <place>England</place>, and the Mizpah largely used in the U. S. A..
				While the French pessary (see cut) may be conveniently used in many cases with
				satisfaction, I fins the Mizpah still better fitting and more convenient for the
				average use. The fact that the cap can be removed and replaced at a very small cost
				adds greatly to it preference among working women. There is also an inner lip which
				prevents its slipping from its hold, when once it is in place. The loose, large
				detachable cap amkes one size (the medium) practically universal for any woman,
				whether the woman has had one or ten children. This cannot be said of the French
				pessary, which comes in three sizes and must be fitted to accommodate every change.
				If, however, one desires a French pessary, it is best to get the medium size, and
				the small ones are only for very small boned women and easily get out of place
				during intercourse. </p>
			<p>[Figure: Pessary}</p>
			<p>In my estimation a well-fitted pessary is one of the surest methods of preventing
				conception. I have known hundreds of women who have used it for years with the most
				satisfactory results. The trouble is women are afraid of their own bodies, and are
				of course ignorant of their physical construction. They are silly in thinking the
				pessary can go up too far, or that it could get lost, etc., etc., and therefore
				discard it. It can not get into the womb, neither can it get lost. The only thing it
				can do is to come out. And even that will give warning by the discomfort of the
				bulky feeling it causes, when it is out of place.</p>
			<p>Before inserting the pessary inject into the cap a small amount of boric ointment or
				a small quantity of bicarbonate of soda. This will act as a cement to help seal the
				mouth of the womb for the time being and thus doubly insures prevention.</p>
			<p>In inserting the pessary it is well to get into a position which will make the
				entrance easy. One foot resting on a low chair opens the parts up considerably, also
				a squatting position brings the uterus lower and makes the fitting of the pessary
				easier. Do not use vaseline or oils on rubber, they decay it. Glycerine or soap
				rubbed on its surface makes it smooth enough to slip easily into place.</p>
			<p>After the pessary has been placed into the vagina deeply, it can be fitted well over
				the neck of the womb. One can feel it is fitted by pressing the finger around the
				soft part of the pessary, which should completely cover the mouth of the womb. If it
				is properly adjusted there will be no discomfort, the man will be unconscious that
				anything is used, and no germ or semen can enter the womb.</p>
			<p>[Figure: Finger touching mouth of the womb a-womb; b- mouth of womb.]</p>
			<p>If you do not feel the head of the womb through the rubber then the pessary is not on
				right. It should be moved backwards a little or forward until the head can be felt
				covered. If you still cannot feel it then remove and use some other preventive, or
				take it to your physician and ask for instructions. The uterus may be turned or
				tipped back so far that a pessary could not cover the cervix.</p>
			<p>If it is properly adjusted there will be no discomfort, the man will be unconscious
				that anything is used, and no germ or semen can enter the womb.</p>
			<p>It is not always necessary to take a douche until the following morning, but it is
				always SAFER to douche immediately after the act. Take part or about a quart of an
				antiseptic douche BEFORE the pessary is removed; after removing it continue the
				douche and cleanse thoroughly.</p>
			<p>There are some well-meaning advocates of birth control who have more theories than
				practical knowledge, who urge or advise that the pessary be left in the body for
				several days and claim that in this way a douche is not necessary.</p>
			<p>The theory may work well in women who belong to the class where standing long hours
				on their feet is not necessary and where a daily bath is a tub od clear water helps
				to keep the parts clean. But my experience in the nursing field among working women
				has given evidence that the pessary cannot remain in place long when a woman stands
				on her feet, as in washing or ironing. The strain pulls the muscles of the womb down
				into the vagina and the pessary loses its hold and position. Also the constant
				contact of the rubber with the natural secretions cause an odor to emanate from the
				parts, which is not pleasant. It is not advisable to wear the pessary all the time.
				Take it out after using, and wear it only when needed. A little experience will
				teach one that to place it is a simple matter.</p>
			<p>Wash the pessary in clear cold water, dry well and play away in the box. One should
				last two years, if cared for.</p>
			<p>I consider the use of the pessary as the most convenient, the cheapest and the safest
				of prevention. Any nurse or doctor will teach one how to adjust it.</p>
			<p>The use of the pessary has many advantages over other methods of prevention. There
				are few women whose generative organs are in a healthy, normal condition, who cannot
				find one of the various kinds of pessaries to fit her convenience.</p>
			<p>While the pessary can only be used in cases where the womb is in its normal
				position--the sponge can be used to great advantage even when the womb is tipped
				back or out of its usual position.</p>
			<p> The usual sponge used for the purpose of preventing conception has a tape attached
				to it. These are to be had at nearly all drup stores. They should be soaked in an
				antiseptic solution for a few minutes before coitus and then introduced into the
				vagina as far up as they can be placed. Some physicians have recommended the use of
				the cotton plug, instead of the sponge, to be soaked in a solution of three per cent
				carbolic and glycerine, before the act. The male sperm is destroyed by the weakest
				solution of carbolic acid. Some of the peasants in Europe use the cotton plug soaked
				in vinegar for the same purpose, and find it satisfactory. In this country a boric
				acid solution has been used for the same purpose and with satisfactory results. Of
				course this requires a saturated solution, as, for instance, one teaspoonful of the
				powder to a cup of water stirred until dissolved.</p>
			<p>Sponges and cotton plugs can be recommended as safe, if followed by an antiseptic
				douche before the removal of the plug or sponge, thus preventing the sperm from
				entering the womb. The problem is: to kill the male sperm upon entering the vagina,
				or to wash it out or to kill it directly afterwards. A weak solution of alum may
				also be used for cotton plugs and sponges, also carbolated vaseline.</p>
			<p>Any objection to the use of the small tape sponge can be overcome by the use of a
				large sponge, divided into parts three or four inches in diameter and a half inch in
				thickness. Cut into parts while new--boil for ten minutes as the sponge is never
				considered hygienically clean until boiled. Push one part up into the vagina as far
				as it will go, pack it tight around the mouth of the womb so that it covers
				completely. Douche thoroughly after its removal. Always keep these parts in a
				solution of vinegar half and half of quinine. As soon as one sponge is removed and
				the vaginal canal cleansed--insert another sponge and leave for a few days. This
				will not have the same bad effects as the pessary.</p>
			<p>One of the cheapest methods of birth control is the use of a large sponge.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">SUPPOSITORIES OR SOLUABLE PESSARIES</head>
			<p>These are becoming more generally used than any other method of prevention. There is
				reason to believe these can be greatly improved upon, and the results obtained far
				more satisfactory than is at present prevalent in England especially.</p>
			<p>These may be found at any reliable pharmacy. The majority of them are made from cocoa
				butter or gelatine, which makes it necessary that they be deposited in the vagina
				several minutes before the act, in order for them to melt. Special ingredients
				negate the effect of the male seed.</p>
			<p>One of the objections to the suppository is the greasy feeling the cocoa butter
				gives. This can be overcome by douching the parts thoroughly before the suppository
				is inserted.</p>
			<p>While some women object to the suppository because of the lubricant effect, other
				women who have a tendency to a "dry vagina" approve of the suppository because of
				this tendency and effect.</p>
			<p>Get your druggist to make up any of the following: <list>
					<item>Vaginal Suppository (Sufficient for three)</item>
					<item>Acid, citric, 6 graims</item>
					<item>2 gr. Quinine Bisulphate.</item>
					<item>Acid boracic, &half; dram.</item>
					<item>Cocoa butter, 60 grains.</item>
				</list></p>
			<p>Another suppository found reliable is (sufficient for one):</p>
			<list>
				<item/>
				<item>Boric acid, 10 grains</item>
				<item>Salicylic acid, 2 grains</item>
				<item>Quinine bisulphate, 3 grains</item>
				<item>Cocoa butter, 60 grains</item>
			</list>
			<p>(For one):</p>
			<list>
				<item>Chinosol, 3 gr.</item>
				<item>Salicyclic acid, 2 gr.</item>
				<item>Quinine bisulphate, 3 gr.</item>
				<item>Cocoa butter, 60 gr.</item>
			</list>

			<p>A simple recipet which anybody can easily make is as follows (for twenty):</p>
			<list>
				<item>1 ounce cocoa butter</item>
				<item>60 grains quinine</item>
			</list>
			<p>Melt the cocoa butter, mix the quinine with it, and form into suppositories by
				letting mixture harden into cake and then cutting it up into pieces.</p>
			<p>It is advisable, in the use of suppositories, which are always to be injected before
				the sexual act, that immediately after the completion of the act a mild antiseptic
				douche be used to cleanse out the secretions. This is a procedure in the use of all
				suppositories, and while it is true that a douche is troublesome, it is certain to
				give better results in preventing pregnancy, than to depend upon the suppository
				alone. </p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">SOME QUESTIONS OFTEN ASKED</head>
			<p>1. What is the best preventive?</p>
			<p>There is no one preventive to be recommended for everyone in every case. There are
				good and harmless preventives, any one of which can be made safe, according to the
				intelligence applied in using them.</p>
			<p>I would advise the use of a recommended suppository for the first few months in the
				case of a bride, until the parts are in a condition where a pessary may be inserted
				and worn with comfort. Sometimes it is advisable to use suppositories during the
				early months of marriage, using the pessary only after children have been born.</p>
			<p>Is a douche necessary after the use of a suppository?</p>
			<p>To be certain of good results, I would advise a douche as soon as convenient.</p>
			<p>3. Are any of these methods recommended injurious to the health of the man or
				woman?</p>
			<p>The only method which physicians claim may be injurious to one or both is the
				continued practice of withdrawal. This method is generally not recommended, though
				it is practiced largely in France and England. </p>
			<p>4. Which method is safest?</p>
			<p>All are safe if you use care and intelligence in applying them.</p>
			<p>5. Which is the least troublesome?</p>
			<p>The pessary can be recommended as the least troublesome, as after it is inserted it
				may be left to cover the cervix until the next day. </p>
			<p>6. Is there a safe period?</p>
			<p>There is no absolutely safe period between the menstrual periods where intercourse
				can take place without pregnancy occurring, at least not for all women. Some women
				claim this period exists in themselves, but unless you know this positively I would
				not advise a woman to depend upon it.</p>
			<p>7. How soon after menstruation ceases should intercourse engage?</p>
			<p>This should be left, as in all cases, to the natural desire of the woman.</p>
			<p>8. Does nursing a baby prevent pregnancy?</p>
			<p>It is claimed that pregnancy does not so easily occur during the nursing period,
				especially during the first three or four months. There are many women, however, who
				have conceived, immediately giving birth to another baby eleven months after the
				other. I would not advise depending upon this at all. Use some preventive at once
				and control intelligently the time for the next baby's arrival, instead of leaving
				it to chance.</p>
			<p>9. Does fear or pregnancy affect the child?</p>
			<p>Fear affects everything. We do not yet know the effect upon the human race which the
				fear or pregnancy has caused. </p>
			<p>10. Is it harmful to take drugs during the first few weeks after menstruation has
				stopped?</p>
			<p>It is considered extremely harmful, not only to the mother, but to the child in cases
				where the drugs have not the desired effect. It stands to reason that a drug which
				is powerful enough to eject a fertilized ovum out of the uterus must have the power
				to affect other organs. We often find children wetting the bed up to a late age, as
				well as suffering from other organic weaknesses, which may be traced back to the
				mother's frantic attempt to "come around." </p>
			<p>11. Should the woman or the man take the precautions?</p>
			<p>Either or both, but preferably the woman. The methods to be used by the
				man--withdrawal and the condom--have their objections for many people. While it is
				true that the employment of either of these methods lessen the trouble for the
				woman, they also deprive her of that great sacred closeness or spiritual union which
				the full play of magnetism gives when not checked by fear, as in withdrawal, or
				interfered with, as with the use of the condom. Some sensitive men object to the use
				of these methods, as also do many women. It is for each couple to decide. Many men
				prefer to use the condom in consideration of the woman, to lessen their trouble in
				douching.</p>
			<p>12. Should a woman have joy in the union?</p>
			<p>Yes.</p>
			<p>13. Why does she not?</p>
			<p>Either because her mind is occupied with fear of the results, or because of the
				awkwardness and ignorance of the man. </p>
			<p>14. Can this be overcome?</p>
			<p>Yes; first by using a contraceptive which gives confidence so there shell be freedom
				from fear of pregnancy; second, by making the husband understand that a greater love
				and joy is created in the relation when the union is consummated only when the woman
				desires it naturally.</p>
			<p>I have given in the foregoing pages the most commonly known means of prevention.
				Persnally I recommend every poor woman who has at least one child to use a well
				fitted pessary and learn to adjust it. </p>
			<p>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">An advertisement for Sanger's books was not
					transcribed.</supplied>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
