<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-03-27 JC encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-30 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1937-01-00">Jan 1937</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>The Future of Contraception</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp308175</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">The Journal of Contraception,</title>, Jan. 1937, pp.
				3-4</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Papers Collected Document Series</title>
				C16:406</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger based this article on her address to the <org>Conference on Contraceptive Research
				and Clinical Practice</org>, on Dec. 29, 1936. For these comments, see "<xref
				from="101798.xml">Welcoming Address to the Conference on Contraceptive Research
				&amp; Clinical Practice</xref>," Dec 29, 1936, and "<xref from="421101.xml"
				>Statement at the Conference on Contraceptive Research and Clinical
			Practice</xref>," Dec 29, 1936.</p>
		<index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>" </headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>The Future of Contraception</head>
		<byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<dateline><date value="1937-01-00">January, 1937</date></dateline>
		<p>On behalf of the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org>, I have the honor and
			the pleasure to welcome you to this conference. It is not fitting that I should take the
			time of this session to tell you all that has been accomplished by the Clinical Research
			Bureau during its thirteen years of functioning. We are, however, proud of its
			achievements. We are proud that it has been a demonstration center and a teaching and
			educational center for medical students and practitioners, especially for those who have
			been unable to obtain instruction in the theory and technique of contraception in their
			medical colleges. We are happy to have given this instruction and this service to
			doctors, nurses and midwives not only from all parts of this country but from countries
			in <place>Europe</place>, <place>Asia</place>, <place>Africa</place>, in fact to
			physicians from nearly every part of the globe.</p>
		<p>But the outstanding achievement of this Bureau has been to inform, teach, instruct and
			give contraceptive information to over 56,000 women who have appealed to us for this
			advice. The records of these women may truly be looked upon as a veritable human
			laboratory for research and correlations. These records have given factual evidence
			which should remove the whole question of birth control from the hot-bed of controversy
			to the quiet calm of scientific consideration.</p>

		<p>We have been fortunate in enlisting the cooperation of competent physicians. We have
			amassed a wealth of incontrovertible evidence supporting the feasibility and the
			desirability of contraceptive practice. But we are not content to rest upon the laurels
			of these claims. We refuse to look back with satisfaction. Rather do we look forward
			with impatient, urgent demands. It is indeed a curious fact that for all the hundreds of
			thousands of women who have been advised and instructed in the more than 300 birth
			control centers now operating in the <place>United States</place> we have had to depend
			mainly upon a method discovered and perfected by <person reg="Mensinga, Wilelm">Dr.
				Mensinga</person> of <place>Germany</place> over 60 years ago. This method requires
			an individual examination, and this is precisely the reason why only a relatively small
			number of the women most in need of contraceptive advice are able to benefit by our
			efforts.</p>
		<p>The birth control movement can definitely be said to have arrived at a stage in its
			development where it can help a large part of the population who are accessible to
			doctors, hospitals and health services where properly qualified doctors are available,
			but we must go further and supply the demand of the submerged sections, those who are
			clamoring for a cheap and effective means to control the size of the family; the women
			on homesteads, on farms, in the mining districts, and the millions of women in outlying
			rural districts where medical help is not available. They cannot come to us and we must
			go to them. </p>
		<p>But before we can reach them and supply their urgent demands, before we can guarantee to
			them at least the same results as are attained by the city and urban women with the
			methods that have proved to be fairly reliable, we must find methods that are cheaper,
			easier to apply, and as harmless as these, and we must ask the scientist to come to our
			aid. We want his cooperation, his vision, his impersonal courage and wisdom.</p>

		<p>We are fortunate at last to be able to announce that a recent decision handed down by the
				<org>United States Circuit Court of Appeals</org> has declared that the <name
				type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Federal statutes</name>
			were not designed to obstruct the circulation of articles which may be intelligently
			employed by conscientious physicians for the purpose of saving life and promoting well
			being. This means the field is cleared for the discovery of inexpensive, reliable
			methods for the control of human fertility. Contraceptive research in both the
			laboratory and the clinic is now free to pursue its course emancipated from the stigma
			of prejudice.</p>
		<p>In our effort to clear away this legal rubbish, we have uncovered many obstacles, but we
			cannot go much further alone. We cannot go either upward or onward without the help of
			the scientific mind. We should place the scientist not only at the helm but on the
			bridge, as captain to guide humanity into its unknown future; and it is because of this
			consciousness of humanity that we urge your cooperation and welcome your presence here. </p>
		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
