<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2Ol2-11-06 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-10 CH OCR missing document and clean up</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Heymann, Curt L.">Curt L. Heymann</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1952-12-21">21 Dec l952</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Interview with Curt L. Heymann</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321965</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">The 'Culmination‘ of Margaret Sanger's Life Work</title>,
					<title type="journal">Los Angeles Times</title>, Dec. 21, 1952. p. B5</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp>
				<name id="HEYCU">Heymann, Curtis</name>
			</resp>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="international conferences on"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="child spacing"/>
		<index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="China" level2="birth rate in"/>
		<index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Gandhi, Mohandas K."/>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 3rd (1952 Bombay)"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="U.S. occupation of"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>The 'Culmination‘ of Margaret Sanger's Life Work</head>
		<byline>BY CURT L. HEYMANN</byline>
		<div type="section">
			<p>“The international conference of the <org
					reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">World Planned Parenthood
					Federation</org> which I helped organize and just attended in <place>Bombay,
					India</place> is the culmination of my life work," <q who="HEYCU">confided
					Margaret Sanger as we settled down for an interview in the lobby of the
						<org>Hotel Crillon</org>.</q> “I have waited 40 years for it.</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">The worlds most outstanding crusader for birth control, who had
					circled the globe to be present at this historic event of which she said it
					would influence plans for the future of the whole world, seemed to be satisfied
					with the results of her latest crusade.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">It was a trip that took her from the <place>United States</place>
					across the Pacific, first to <place>Japan</place>, then by way of <place
						reg="Hong Kong, China">Hong Kong</place> and <place>Singapore</place> to
						<place>India</place>. From <place>Asia</place> Mrs. Sanger flew straight
					back to <place>Europe</place> and she was on the last leg of her global voyage
					here in <place reg="Paris, France">Paris</place> before returning to <place
						reg="New York, NY">New York</place> and <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson,
						Ariz.</place>, where she now makes her home.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">The 40 years she mentioned were a reflection upon her four decades of
					crusading. And as she referred to them with emotion, her thoughts probably went
					back to the days before and during World War I when she fought against a
					formidable array of opponents, including the <org reg="United States Government"
						>U.S. government</org> itself.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">Those were the days when she was persecuted and suffered from mental
					anguish, served a prison term and was indicted for the violation of the <name
						type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">Comstock Act of
						l873</name> which classified contraceptive information as obscene. She left
					the country in 1914 on the eve of the trial which never came off. The indictment
					was quashed, but the Comstock Law was not changed.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="HEYCU">Three years later she and <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">her
						sister</person> served 30-day prison sentences for operating a <org
						reg="Brownsville Clinic">birth control clinic</org> in <place
						reg="Brooklyn, NY">New York</place>. But the vigorous little red—haired
					woman, one of ll children, had inherited her rebellious nature from her Irish
					father, <person reg="Higgins, Michael Hennessey">Michael Higgins</person>, and
					decided to fight for</q> “freedom of the mind from dogma and cant."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p><q who="HEYCU">On New York's Lower East Side she had nursed women whose pregnancy was
					what she called a </q>“chronic condition." <q who="HEYCU">In despair she gave up
					nursing and embarked on a powerful idea for which she was finally awarded world
					recognition.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">Wistful and fragile, Mrs. Sanger is a quiet and unassuming person.
					Now close to 70, the protagonist of a once controversial movement for which she
					fought with the courage of a lion still speaks with the eloquence of a crusader.
					But there is a contentment in her voice when she reviews the last 20 years of
					her work.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">Thanks to her efforts, birth control in the United States has been
					recognized by the <org>American Medical Association</org> and is legalized in 46
					States. Only two, <place>Massachusetts</place> and <place>Connecticut</place>,
					have laws against it. Birth control under medical supervision is sanctioned by
					many church groups. Only the <org>Roman Catholic Church</org> remains, on
					religious grounds, its principal opponent.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">In 1914, when Mrs. Sanger chose the name <org
						reg="American Birth Control League">National Birth Control League</org> for
					her young venture, she probably didn't dream that the movement would ever grow
					to world proportions. In the 30s all her efforts to win Congressional support
					and all measures contemplated to legalize the idea were defeated.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">Today, child spacing is part of public health in a number of States
					and Mrs. Sanger is honorary chairman of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation
						of America</org> which has its headquarters in New York. Herself the mother
					of three children (a <person reg="Sanger, Peggy">daughter</person> died but her
						<person reg="Sanger, Stuart"><person reg="Sanger, Grant">two
						sons</person></person> are practicing physicians in <place>Arizona</place>
					and New York) she has eight grandchildren.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">Recalling that she visited Japan 30 years ago, Mrs. Sanger told me
					that she predicted a Japanese war in <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> in
					1922, because of the country's high birth rate and Japan restricted territory,
					too small to accommodate her overpopulation.</q>
			</p>
			<p>“But then only a group of intellectuals listened to me," <q who="HEYCU">she said.</q>
				“The military turned the idea of birth control down and the subject was not to be
				discussed. Japan, at the time, had a population of 60,000,000, a birth rate of
				l,200,00 per year and a territory two—thirds as large as <place>California</place>.
				The country could have remained without war and slowly increased her birth rate, but
				evidently Japan wasn't ready for birth control.</p>
			<p>"Today, 84,000,000 Japanese must live on a much smaller territory and the nation’s
				birth rate has risen to 2,000,000 annually. Japanese women are quite conscious of
				the fact that a high birth rate meant and still means war. So they have been
				resorting to abortions. There were 1,500,000 reported abortions in Japan last year.
				That's not our idea of birth control."</p>
			<p>“<q who="HEYCU">But aren't abortions illegal in Japan?</q>"</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>“No, they are not. They are legalized under the hygienic protection law of 1949. The
				sale of contraceptives is also legal, but they are being used without general
				knowledge or information."</p>
			<p>“<q who="HEYCU">If my information is correct, you were supposed to visit Japan
					several years ago to advise on contraceptives. What prevented you from going
					there?</q>"</p>
			<p>“The occupation authorities. I was invited by the editor of Tokyo's <org>Mainichi
					Press</org> to visit Japan in 1949, shortly after the protection law was passed.
				But my American visa was refused by Gen. <person reg="MacArthur, Douglas">Douglas
					MacArthur</person> who considered my presence outside interference. After the
				end of our military occupation, Mainichi invited me again and I combined my visit to
				Japan with my trip to Bombay."</p>
			<p>“<q who="HEYCU">And what are the results of your Japanese visit?</q>"</p>
			<p>“I spent two weeks in Tokyo, <place reg="Kyoto, Japan">Kyoto</place> and <place
					reg="Osaka, Japan">Osaka</place> where three large meetings were arranged for
				me. They were open to the public and held late in the afternoon so that both men and
				women could attend. I talked at each gathering for 40 minutes on the subject and it
				took an interpreter about three hours to translate my speeches."</p>
			<p>"There were in addition round tables for professional people, physicians, nurses and
				social workers. Wherever I spoke people were very much interested and alert, much
				more so than in any other country, not excluding the United States. The poorest
				people would arrange street meetings in Tokyo and I would stand on top of a bus
				talking to them. And I would tell them that birth control means prevention--not
				interference."</p>
			<p>“<q who="HEYCU">Is birth control objectionable to Buddhism or any other Eastern
					religion?</q>"</p>
			<p>“No, it isn't. There's no remonstrance on religious grounds. And as far as the
				Japanese are concerned they saw the light of truth through war: no more political
				objections--only economic and hygienic considerations.</p>
			<p>It will take awhile for them to get organized, set up clinics, manufacture
				contraceptives and get used to the formulas which I gave them. But eventually
				they'll be used and distributed by the public health authorities."</p>
			<p>“<q who="HEYCU">I suppose the Chinese Communists are not interested in birth
					control?</q>"</p>
			<p>“No, of course not. Like all Communist countries and nations behind the Iron Curtain
				they have been giving prizes for large families, regardless of social, economic and
				hygienic conditions. That, in the <place reg="Asia">Far East</place>, is in strong
				contrast to the situation in Hong Kong and Singapore, which in the last two years
				have established excellent birth control committees and clinics.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>“Those colonies are terribly overpopulated through refugees. Hong Kong, which had a
				prewar population of 700,000, has now 2,400,000. Birth control is still private. But
				eventually it will come under public health authorities to make it more
				effective."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">“From there you flew directly to Bombay for the World Birth Control
					Conference?"</q>
			</p>
			<p>“Yes. The Indians called it the <org
					reg="International Conference for Planned Parenthood, 3rd">International
					Conference for Family Planning</org>. It was held from Nov. 21 to Dec. 2 and was
				attended by 500 delegates from l5 countries, including India. There were 21
				Americans in our delegation. Lady <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Rama
					Rau</person> was president of the conference and by unanimous vote was elected
				president for the Orient. I was made honorary president for North American and Dr.
					<person reg="Blacker, Carlos Paton">C. P. Blacker</person> of <place
					reg="London, England">London</place> became director of the <org
					reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">world federation</org>."</p>
			<p>"This is the culmination of my life's work and I firmly believe that a new leaf has
				been turned in the history book of birth control. Because for the first time Orient
				met Occident in a planned parenthood conference held in Asia on an international
				level."</p>
			<p>"In my address to the assembly I recalled my visit to <person
					reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K.">Mahatma Gandhi</person> in 1936. We talked about birth
				control in India and he agreed that some form of control would have to be instituted
				or India would remain enslaved. Gandhi thought the ideal number of children for each
				Indian family would be four."</p>
			<p><q who="HEYCU">How excessive is the Indian birth rate?</q>"</p>
			<p>"There were 5,000,000 births in 1950 and the same number in l95l--far beyond the
				country's possibilities of feeding, clothing or housing them. In Bombay alone
				thousands sleep in the streets and every Indian city tells the same story. But birth
				control and reduction of births are not enough."</p>
			<p>"The Indians must improve their land to produce more food and in order to do that
				they must increase their water supplies. But whatever they do--reduction of the
				birth rate must precede these steps."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">How do you find the birth control situation in free Europe?</q>
			</p>
			<p>"It's lagging far behind because of the last war. Chief antagonism does not come from
				the people but from the hierarchy of the Roman Catholic Church which dominates
				political action and threatens to boycott every activity of the public health
				officials wishing to give birth control information and advice."</p>
			<p>“While all Scandinavian countries, especially <place>Sweden</place>, have made the
				greatest progress, and countries like <place>England</place>
				<place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, <place>Switzerland</place> and <place>West
					Germany</place> practice birth control freely, such predominantly Catholic
				countries as <place>France</place>, <place>Italy</place>, <place>Spain</place> and
					<place>Belgium</place> have banned contraceptives."</p>
			<p>“<q who="HEYCU">Will you or the world federation help Western Europe to organize
					birth control?</q>"</p>
			<p>“No, the people of free Europe have got to fight for that liberty themselves."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HEYCU">The late <person reg="Broun, Heywood">Heywood Broun</person> once
					complained that Mrs. Sanger had no sense of humor. I asked her nevertheless to
					tell me an amusing anecdote that might have occurred on her round-the-world
					tour. Now as then she retorted with the same reply:</q>
			</p>
			<p>“I am the protagonist of women who have nothing to laugh at."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
