<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-03-02 JC encoding</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-20 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-27 JC corrections made</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-30 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate><prepDate>2015-07-22 CH correct titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Miller, Hope Ridings">Hope Ridings Miller</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1935-02-08">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">8 Feb 1935</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on American Women's Association Award</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321962</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				"<title type="article">Results Worth the Fight, Margaret Sanger Says After Her
					21-Year 'Birth Control' Campaign</title>," <title type="journal">Washington
					Post</title>, Feb 9, 1935, p. 14</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="MILHO">Miller, Hope Ridings</name>
			<name id="WELHG">Wells, H. G.</name>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
			<name id="AWA">American Women's Association</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="awards and tributes"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biographical details"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="establishment of"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>z </headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Results Worth the Fight, Margaret Sanger Says After Her 21-Year 'Birth Control'
			Campaign</head>
		<byline>By Hope Ridings Miller</byline>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">Who is this woman who won the first award for achievement given by
					the <org>American Women’s Association</org> as one who has <q who="AWA">"fought
						against almost every influence which in the past was considered necessary
						for the success of a cause?"</q> Who is this woman of whom <person
						reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person> said,</q>
				<q who="WELHG">"She has created a unique position for herself in that she has
					changed the thinking not only of her nation but of the world?"</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">She is Mrs. J. N. H. Slee, better known as Margaret Sanger, coiner of
					the words "birth control" which she has made significant. Publicized by her
					enemies as "that Sanger woman" and that "birth control fanatic"–-called by her
					friend</q>
				<q who="WELHG">"one of the greatest living women,"</q>
				<q who="MILHO">and recognized by those who neither censure nor endorse her as a
					pioneer and an outstanding personality–-Margaret Sanger has battled for her
					cause with dogged persistence for more than two decades.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">The "coming of age" of her work will be celebrated Wednesday at the
						<org>Hotel Mayflower</org> when the American birth control movement
					commemorates its anniversary.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">Perhaps no woman, in the last 21 years vitally concerned with any
					cause, has battled against greater odds than Margaret Sanger.</q>
			</p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Results Worth the Fight. </head>
			<p>"But what stormy, yet thrilling, years those have been," <q who="MILHO">Mrs. Sanger
					said yesterday in her apartment at the <org reg="Fairfax Hotel"
					>Fairfax</org>.</q> "Looking back now and considering the great change in public
				opinion toward birth control, the result has been more than worth the fight."</p>
			<p>"Every inch of the way has been gained in desperate battle, with theological
				prejudices to be overcome, ethical questions to be considered, scientific points to
				be settled. No wonder I am used to fighting by now."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">Yet there is nothing of the fighter in Mrs. Sanger’s appearance. Mild
					in manner and calm even while discussing the most turbulent of her experiences,
					she is the antithesis of the proverbial feminine champion of Amazon proportions,
					booming voice and mannish attire.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">In a blue wool dress that brought all the beauty of her reddish hair
					and hazel, amber-flecked eyes, she looked very much the attractive, unassuming
					type of woman who is serene in the face of any difficulty.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">One senses beneath that composed exterior, however, a steel that has
					sustained this courageous woman in the face of ridicule–-a steel that has
					strengthened her through arraignments and even a prison sentence and prompted
					her to continue her fight for a cause that seemed hopeless two decades ago.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="MILHO">One of the 11 children, Mrs. Sanger was interested in birth control
					long before the movement began.</q> "Very early in childhood I associated
				poverty, toil, unemployment and debts with large families. My experience with
				over-burdened mothers when I was a nurse on the lower East Side in <place
					reg="New York, NY">New York</place> crystallized my determination to do
				something to help those poor unfortunate women."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">The birth-control movement had its inception in that
					determination.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"And from then until now it has been a struggle," <q who="MILHO">she said.</q> "I had
				three children of my own to look after and very little money, but what has been
				accomplished convinces me there was reason enough for such a fight."</p>
			<p>"At times, of course, the battle has been almost unbearably difficult." <q
					who="MILHO">(Was she thinking of the eight times she had been arrested? Her
					sentence to a penitentiary? The numerous times when halls engaged for her
					lectures were closed against her at the last minute? Her encounter with the
					postal authorities relative to her publications, "<title type="journal" reg="Woman Rebel">The
						Rebel Woman"</title> and "The <title type="journal">Birth Control
						Review</title>"?)</q></p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Opened Clinic in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>. </head>
			<p>"Eighteen years ago I opened a <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">clinic</org> in the
				crowded Brownsville section of Brooklyn, where mothers could obtain information on
				birth control for a registration fee of 10 cents," <q who="MILHO">she
					reminisced.</q> "Within a few days more than 500 women applied for and received
				this information."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">Among them, however, was a police <person reg="Whitehurst, Margaret"
						>woman</person> who having been given advice by the nurses in charge of the
					clinic, returned later with five policemen who promptly arrested Mrs. Sanger and
					her <person reg="Mindell, Fania"><person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">two
							helpers</person></person> and took them to court.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"But harrowing as that experience was, it was that incident that brought my fight to
				the fore and attracted attention to the cause."</p>
			<p><q who="MILHO">The fight continued. In Mrs. Sanger’s own words,</q> "The first ten
				years were spent in divorcing the term ‘birth control’ from illegal means of
				avoiding childbirth. In other words, we devoted most of those first years trying to
				show people what birth control was not. We had to prove that it was not the taking
				of life, that it was not against nature; that it did not make for race suicide."</p>
			<p><q who="MILHO">The next period, she pointed out, was spent in educating and
					organizing those who were interested, those who understood the real purpose of
					birth control.</q> "After agitation, came education and organization. Now we are
				working for proper legislation."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">She mentioned her goal now is to bring about an amendment to the
					62-year-old <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211"
						>Comstock law</name>, which forbids the dissemination of birth control
					information as "obscene."</q>
			</p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Bill Tabled by House. </head>
			<p>"This antiquated law," <q who="MILHO">Mrs. Sanger explained</q> "prohibits even
				physicians from sending or receiving through the mails such information or necessary
				medical supplies. It is illegal to transmit the address of a clinic where
				information may be obtained, although many clinics are legally operating in a number
				of States."</p>
			<p><q who="MILHO">Mrs. Sanger pointed out, also, that the latest birth-control bill was
					tabled in the <org reg="United States House of Representatives">House of
						Representatives</org> last Monday. </q>"Tabled, without discussion," <q
					who="MILHO">she said.</q> "When that happened I was dreadfully discouraged at
				first. But now, I have a clearer picture of the situation. I realize we can
				accomplish more by throwing forces into the field where the need of birth control is
				so apparent.</p>
			<p>Once the Comstock law is amended, our fight in this country will be won, as it has
				already been won in many others. What transpires after that will be merely a matter
				of time."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILHO">Did she think it would be long before her goal was attained?</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Not another 21 years, I hope," <q who="MILHO">she laughed, for the first time during
					the interview.</q> "No, seriously, I don’t think it will be long. I can’t bear
				to think it will be 10, or even 5 years before the poorest woman can obtain the same
				information and the same contraceptive supplies any woman with enough money can get
				now from a private physician.</p>
			<p>"Surely with the turn of the tide of public opinion prejudice and opposition will be
				conquered soon, so that birth control information will no longer be available only
				to those who can pay for it. For 21 years my fight has been for the
				poverty-stricken, the inarticulate women to whom motherhood has become a burden.
				Ultimately victory will come only after every intelligent voter has been awakened to
				the importance of proper birth control legislation."</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
