<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2009/11/06 CH</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-07-02 CH clean tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-09 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-03-14">14 Mar 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">War and Population</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp400500</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Attentive Audience Hears Mrs. Sanger</title>, <title
					type="journal">Japan Advertiser</title>, Mar. 15, 1922, pp. 1 and 10</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BP">Berliner Post</name>
			<name id="JA">Japan Advertiser</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>The actual speech was not found, but this transcript was published. For shorter versions
			see, <title type="article">War and Population</title>, <title type="journal">Birth
				Control Review</title>, June 1922, pp. 106-7 and <title type="article"
				>Overpopulation is Cause of War</title>, <title type="journal">Japan Times and
				Mail</title>, Mar. 15, 1922.</p>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours” level3=”1920 (Germany)"/>
		<index level1="censorship"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="impact of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and war"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="birth rate in"/>
		<index level1="World War I" level2="and population size"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="and war"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="MS in"/>
		<index level1="voluntary motherhood"/>
		<index level1="Marxism and Marxists" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="internationalism"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and peace"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and natural resources"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="fertility of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>ATTENTIVE AUDIENCE HEARS MRS. SANGER</head>
		<div>
			<p><q who="JA">ProSperous-looking business men, well-groomed women, students, shop
					girls, coolies, a Buddhist priest or two, a number of foreigners and a battery
					of camera men composed the audience of about 500 persons which heard Mrs.
					Margaret Sanger, American birth control advocate, speak on "War and Population"
					in the <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>
					<org reg="Young Men's Christian Association">Y.M.C.A.</org> auditorium yesterday
					afternoon. It was Mrs. Sanger's first public meeting and among her most
					attentive listeneres were a liberal sprinkling of "plain clothes men" of the
						<org reg="Tokyo Metropolitan Police">Metropolitan Police</org> who were
					there to see that the speaker did not overstep the bounds permitted into a
					discussion of birth control--a subject officially banned as "dangerous" to Japan
					morals.</q></p>
			<p><q who="JA">The late date at which yesterday afternoon's meeting was announced was
					thought to have been responsible for the small audience, but no more interested
					audience could have been secured. Apparently most of those present understood
					English, for the audience, as though charmed by the clear and distinct voice of
					Mrs. Sanger, sat silent and expectant as she spoke. The usual stir came as the
					translator started on each new paragraph of Mrs. Sanger's speech, and it was
					easy to discern those who had understood Mrs. Sanger as he proceeded with the
					translation.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Speaks on War and Population.</head>
			<p><q who="JA">Two listeners were less attentive than the others. They were both typical
					women of the poorer class, aged beyond their years by the bearing and raising of
					many children in a few years; each was compelled to pace the room at the rear
					and croon to a fretful baby on her back.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<p>"I regret exceedingly that I am not allowed to speak to you this afternoon upon the
				subject of birth control." <q who="JA">Mrs. Sanger said as she started her
					address.</q> "Why this privilege has been denied me I do not know, for I have
				addressed audiences on birth control in nearly every country of
					<place>Europe</place> and in every large city in the <place>United
					States</place>. However, I am grateful for small favors and am pleased that I
				have been able to gain permission to address you on 'War and Population.' Inasmuch
				as I was unprepared to speak upon this subject, I ask tolerance in allowing me to
				use my notes in addressing you."</p>
			<p>"In a little more than 100 years Europe had about doubled her population while the
				increase in her food supply was less than 50 percent. She had been piling up huge
				debts for future generations to pay. She had piled up such conditions as slums,
				unemployment, child labor, inertness, inefficiency, dependency--and finally--war.
				The World War which started in Europe in 1914 was only a natural result of the
				manifold conditions which made such a volcanic eruption inevitable."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Social Conditions Brought War.</head>
			<p>"During the past 50 years there has been a tendency in every country in Europe to
				increase the numbers overwhelmingly in one group and to increase slowly in another.
				it is these individuals who do not let nature control their destinies. Here, the
				forces of fecundity have been mastered. In this group, whose numbers increase but
				slowly, conditions are progressive and advanced. The other group, who are at the
				mercy of the urge of generation, have increased not only their numbers, but have
				increased their problems beyond the means of development of the social conscience or
				the intelligence of the nations. In this group in every country of Europe are found
				the great problems, both social and economic, with which the world was confronted in
				1914."</p>
			<p>"In some countries, as in <place>England</place>, it was possible through
				colonization to alleviate the conditions in this group somewhat by sending the
				surplus population to <place>Canada</place>, <place>Australia</place> and other
				parts of the globe."</p>
			<p>"<place>France</place>, on the other hand, had kept her numbers more or less
				stationary and had aimed to develop quality in her people. It was to France that we
				turned for culture, for science, for advancement in almost every line of scientific
				thought."</p>
			<p>"Germany, on the other hand, was the central country in Europe which though in some
				departments was far more advanced than the others, was by the nature of that
				particular department blocked in her progress, and her conditions at home were made
				more complex and chaotic. Germany had been the first country in Europe to bring in
				the largest sources of alleviation for her population. During the dark and middle
				ages, <place>Germany</place> had relied upon infant mortality, disease and
				pestilence to keep her population within bounds. It was quite a natural event for a
				family during that period to have from 15 to 20 members, but for only one or two, or
				at the most 4 in that family to survive to full maturity. This was the course which
				nature had taken to lessen the possibility of war and to keep nations somewhat at
				peace with each other."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Checking Disease Increases Problems.</head>
			<p>"With the advance of humanitarian thought, scientific and preventive medicine,
				Germany began to check her death rate, but to increase her problems. The urge for
				expansion on the part of the increasing population in any country, when brought
				against geographical barriers, acts blindly in the direction of conflict, whether in
				colonial rivalry or territorial swarming. The opportunities for Germany’s expansion
				were strictly limited by other Powers, and the prosperity due to the opening of new
				countries had long passed its maximum. The possibilities for expansion that were
				open a century ago were fairly well exhausted, and Germany found herself with
				serious problems on her hands which meant national expansion or ultimate stagnation.
				We find then the situation in Germany to be a rapidly increasing population,
				bringing this population to full maturity at a great expense to the Government,
				through social service, old age pensions, maternity benefits, and the like. The
				necessities for feeding this population were out of her reach and made her dependent
				upon other countries for her population’s subsistence."</p>
			<p>"There was a tendency, too, toward a surplus of highly trained professional and
				technical men. The elaborate educational system of Germany was producing more
				engineers, surveyors, electrical engineers, industrial chemists and experts along
				various lines than the nation’s employers could utilize or absorb. The result was
				that such men had to be content to remain for less wages than the unskilled
				workingmen could procure or to emigrate to foreign lands where that skill and
				inventiveness became the assets of other countries at Germany’s cost."</p>
			<p>"While Germany’s birth rate was on the decline--in 1900 it was 36.5 percent--the
				number of deaths diminished by such proportion that her survivals became higher and
				her population increased in a faster proportion than it did with an increasing birth
				rate. There was an increase of from 700,000 to 800,000 souls a year, which amounted
				to nearly four millions of new individuals every five years. It was upon such
				conditions, briefly and fragmentary as they are related here, that Germany based her
				claim to a place in the sun and the right of livelihood of her surplus
				population."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">War Argument Is Population.</head>
			<p>"The <title type="journal">Berliner Post</title> in 1913 said: ‘<q who="BP">Can a
					great and rapidly-growing nation like Germany always renounce all claims to
					further development or to expansion of its political power? The final settlement
					with France and England, the expansion of our colonial possessions in order to
					create new German homes for the overflow of our population. . . .these are the
					problems which must be faced in the future.'</q>"</p>
			<p>"If one studies the comments of the press during the five years preceding the World
				War, he will be find in every instance that the argument upon which the right of any
				country to prepare for war was based upon her increasing and growing population.
				Germany in 1910 had a population of 70 millions. At the rate she was increasing she
				was bound to have in a short time double that number. It was the argument of her
				militarists and others who were making greater demands for Germany that she must
				find an outlet for her people, that Germany was hungry for trade, that she needed
				colonies, that she could not confine her growing population within her narrow
				geographical boundaries."</p>
			<p>"In one of the magazines the <person reg="Wilhelm II (Germany)">Kaiser</person> was
				quoted as having said that in 1950 Germany would possess a population of 200
				millions or something near that. It might have been supposed that councils such as
				those representing the best ranks of thinking Germans might have been adverse to
				this condition of things, but, extraordinary, as it may seem to all thinking people,
				the Marxian philosophy had taken a strong hold upon the people of Germany and
				particularly the working people during the past 25 years and inculcated the view
				point that the greater the numbers of the proletariat the higher would be their
				wages; the higher their demand in the labor market, the larger the numbers in the
				ranks of their revolutionists. So that up to the time of 1914 there was every
				tendency on the part of the thinkers of Germany--economic, social and political--to
				increase their numbers and to trust to the gods the result, that might makes
				right."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Describes Conditions in Germany.</head>
			<p>"This, briefly, is the pivotal condition of one of the chief causes of the war in Europe which started in 1914.
				We all know the results and the consequences, but none of us can foretell the
				terrific decadent consequences which Germany is yet to feel. Her best fitted manhood
				was slaughtered in the war, her mothers and children left at home in a condition of
				physical starvation from which will come the generations of the future. When I was in
				Germany in 1920 and witnessed more than 10,000 little starving infants, the results
				of the blockade and the war, I felt that it would be far kinder for Germany’s future
				and for the future peace of the world to humanely allow these little victims to
				pass away than to keep them alive to perpetuate their disease and misery. More
				than 45 percent of the women of Germany were made permanently sterile owing to the
				lack of food and improper nourishment for child-bearing."</p>
			<p>"The present conditions in Germany are extremely heavy taxes, low value of money,
				deficiency of labor in many establishments, scarcity of food and the cost of living so
				dear that the average earner lives upon a ration which means partial
				starvation."</p>
			<p>"The conclusions to be drawn from Germany are that an overcrowded nation will not be the victor in
				war and that war is no longer the way to settle international disputes. Until all
				nations recognize that there are fundamental dynamic forces at work which must be
				controlled--forces such as hunger and propagation--we cannot solve one without
				including the other--until these forces are recognized and acted upon wisely,
				the idea of international peace will remain a dream and a myth."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Appeals for Women's Freedom.</head>
			<p>"Japan has problems today increasingly as great as those of Germany in 1914. She has
				a right to have those problems solved in a rational humanitarian way, but until our
				diplomats and statesmen recognize the causes of war and make the study of the
				population question in all its manifold departments, all our <org reg="League of Nations"
					>League of Nations</org>, international conferences, agreements and
				international treaties will become proverbial ‘scraps of paper.' Men and women
				of <place>Japan</place>, I appeal to you to look into this subject thoroughly. The
				mothers and women in your country are just as desirous of wiping out poverty,
				misery, suffering and war as the mothers and women of the other nations of the
				world. I appeal to you to set your motherhood free. To make your women something
				more than breeding machines such as the women of every nation have been in some
				period of that nation’s development. The time has come for international brotherhood
				and international emancipation based upon a conscious maternity."</p>
			<p>"The advancement of hygiene and sanitation and welfare work in any country only
				increases its population problem, which means expansion through immigration or armed
				invasion. Each nation must control its population to the point where it will not be
				necessary to make aggression upon its neighbors."</p>
			<p>"The study of the population problem will reveal to you the initial cause of the
				suffering of mankind; it will reveal the cause for his struggles and divisions into
				factions and parties. It will point out the remedy to obviate these differences and
				to establish a new order of civilization."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Unchecked Procreation the Cause.</head>
			<p>"To the working man it will show that a state of oppression and tyranny can exist
				only as a result of ignorance. That the struggle between classes, capital and
				labor, and the war between nations, are the inevitable consequences of that
				ignorance. It will show that the working man has himself been the producer of these
				conditions through his unlimited procreative powers--unchecked and uncontrolled--while
				he and his brother are the initial sufferers from all the flagrant inequalities
				found in all nations today."</p>
			<p>"Let us then, friends, depart from the old methods of quantity and turn our attention
				to producing quality in our people."</p>
			<p>"It will then be possible for everyone to have independence and personal dignity;
				motherhood will be glorified, and a nation may well expect to promote for its
				population peace, justice, happiness and the international brotherhood of the
				world."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
