<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-06-26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1936-01-03">)3 Jan 1936</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Contraception</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421097</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Dissemination of Knowledge</title>,
					<title type="journal">Madras Mail</title>, Jan. 3,
				1936.</bibl>
			<bibl><title/></bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="MM">Madras Mail</name>
			<name id="TH"> The Hindu</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke to the first <org>All-India Obstetrics and
				Gynaecological Congress</org> at the <org>Museum Theater</org>
			in <place>Madras, India</place>. The speech was not found, but a
			summary was published in the press.</p>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control movement in"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="population policies of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Dissemination of Knowledge</head>
		<head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger's Address to Doctors</head>
		<dateline><date value="1936-01-03"/>Jan. 3, Madras</dateline>
		<p>“I think that the people of <place>India</place> should demand from
			the medical profession the scientific knowledge which is available
			in other countries and in medical and scientific societies regarding
			methods of birth control.”</p>
		<p>
			<q who="MM"> This remark was made by Mrs. Margaret Sanger (President
				of the <org>Birth Control International Information
				Centre</org>) in an address to members of the medical profession
				this evening at the Museum Theater. The lecture was illustrated
				with films.</q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="MM"> Mrs. Margaret Sanger said: </q>“My message to the
			medical profession in India is that it has a wonderful opportunity
			to avoid the mistakes which have been made by Western countries,
			where they have rigid laws, as in <place reg="United States"
				>America</place>, against the dissemination of birth control
			information. If, through maternity hospitals and other hospitals and
			Health Week, doctors will provide proper instruction to women as
			well as men, first for health reasons and next for social and
			economic reasons, they can help to direct the birth control movement
			along the proper channel.</p>
		<p> “The well-to-do-people in all countries have some knowledge, which
			the poor are denied. But the poor people, the sick and the diseased,
			should be the first to have it.” </p>
		<p>
			<q who="MM">The lecturer then exhibited scientific films on
				contraception and birth control as known in Western
				countries.</q>
		</p>
		<p> “One-fifth of the babies born in India,” <q who="MM">Mrs. Sanger
				continued,</q> “die before they reach their fifth year.”</p>
		<p>
			<q who="MM">The death rate among infants from the first to the
				fourth born was not heavy. But there was higher mortality among
				those born after the fourth up to the seventh. From the seventh
				to the eleventh the wastage was still more tremendous. Sixty per
				cent, of the twelfth-born children died generally in the first
				year.</q>
		</p>
		<p> “The average Indian family,” <q who="MM">Mrs. Sanger remarked,
			</q>“could support fairly about three children.”</p>
		<p><q who="MM">The lecturer added: </q> “The people should ask
			municipalities and public health agencies to open birth control
			clinics, especially for the poor who have not the means to pay for
			private advice. I would also stress that the young men and women in
			the medical schools and colleges should be given proper instruction
			in contraceptive technique.” </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
