<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/12/11 JK encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-13 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-11-18">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">18 Nov 1929</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Mt. Holyoke Lecture</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421047</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Urges Spread of Education for Relief</title>,
					<title type="journal">Mt. Holyoke News</title>, Nov. 23, 1929</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="MHN">The Mount Holyoke News</name>
			<name id="HEAAR">Heath, Arthur (Sir)</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger's speech was not located; press coverage provides details.</p>
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="conferences" level2="World Population Conference" level3="1927"/>
		<index level1="child labor"/>
		<index level1="children" level2="unwanted"/>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="efforts to reduce"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Urges Spread of Education for Relief</head>

		<p>“The United States is particular about who comes into the country from the outside. It
			has found the selective quota to be a success. Why doesn’t it try a selective quota to
			judge who should come into the country from the inside?” <q who="MHN">suggested Margaret
				Sanger, speaking on the subject of Birth Control to an enthusiastic audience in the
				Chapel last Monday evening.</q></p>
		<p><q who="MHN">Birth control, she explained, does not mean limiting the number of children
				in every family in the United States. It merely means the weeding out of the
				socially undesirable, the unwanted before their conception. The <place> United
					States</place> spent $9,000,000 in 1927 on the four D’s-- disease, defect,
				delinquency and death, and in the last three years has spent $18,000,000 in crime in
				one way or another. Of course this expense is perfectly all right as far as it goes,
				but there is the question whether it might not be more desirable to stop the reason
				for it? Birth control might not be a panacea for all crime and disease, but it would
				certainly go a long way toward curing it. </q></p>
		<p><q who="MHN"> According to Mrs. Sanger, families that do not want more children, that
				have too many already, that cannot support them should be given a fair chance to
				limit their offspring. In the United States there are seven million children under
				fourteen years of age working in factories or in the field. Many of the parents of
				these children are getting wages scarcely sufficient to support themselves, much
				less a large family. Child-labor legislation is helpful in a way, but it does not go
				far enough. Mrs. Sanger urges that the evil be checked at its root.</q></p>
		<p>There are other cases in which birth control is desirable. Transmissible diseases, such
			as epilepsy and insanity could be perhaps eliminated by this method; tubercular mothers
			and women with heart disease might be spared all the pain and suffering they are at
			present compelled to go through; subnormal children might be avoided.</p>
		<p><q who="MHN"> Mrs. Sanger mentioned the various ways of controlling and regulating the
				birth rate, and said that of course the <org reg="American Birth Control League"
					>Birth Control League</org> did not intend to force anything upon people who did
				not wish it. The primary aim of the League at present is to get Congress to lift the
				ban upon sending information regarding contraception through the mails to the
				suffering women who want it so badly, and to make it legal for doctors to be abel to
				give aid in other than diseased cases.</q></p>
		<p><q who="MHN">In closing the speaker quoted Sir <person reg="Heath, Arthur">Arthur
					Heath</person> who has declared:</q> “<q who="HEAAR">There is developing in the
				United States the greatest experiment in race building the world has ever seen, and
				birth control is an integral part of that movement</q>.”</p>
		<p><supplied resp="MSPP">A discussion of a tea held for Sanger at the Gateway and a dinner
				heald at Hillside have been omitted by the MSPP editors.</supplied></p>

		<div>
			<head>Interviewer Notes Charm of Birth Control Advocate</head>
			<p>“Birth control inspires parents to consider not only the physical welfare of the
				child, but to consider its inheritance and its potentialities as a race bearer.”</p>
		</div>
</docBody>
</doc>
