<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/04 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-22 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1936-01-17">17 Jan 1936</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421086</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Birth Control: Mrs. Sanger's Address at Bangalore</title>,
					<title type="jorunal">The Hindu</title>, Jan. 18, 1936</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TH">The Hindu</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger gave this speech to the <org>South Indian Science Association</org> at the
				<org>Central College</org> in <place>Bangalore, India</place>. <person
				reg="Pravine, Sastra Vaidya">Sastra Vaidya Pravine</person>, and <person
				reg="Rao, S. Subba">S. Subba Rao</person> presided. The speech was not found.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control</head>
		<head type="sub">Mrs. Sanger's Address at Bangalore</head>
		<dateline>BANGALORE, <date value="1936-01-16">Jan. 16</date>.</dateline>
		<p> “To you in <place>India</place> who have given to the world marvelous temples that have
			been built by your great men in the past and handed on to us (westerners) to admire- and
			we do admire them- the time is now come to make another kind of temple, the ‘human
			temple’ and the ‘human body.’ Let us begin to make our bodies fit and perfect
			instruments to house that soul that we may summon to take its place in the mystery of
			human beings.” <q who="TH">In these words, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth control exponent
				from America who is now on a tour in India, put forth a plea before a Bangalore
				audience tonight for the practice of birth control.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="TH">The meeting was held at the Central College, under the auspices of the South
				Indian Science Association and was presided over by Sastra Vaidya Pravina Dr. S.
				Subba Rao, Senior Surgeon in <place reg="Mysore, India">Mysore</place>.</q>
		</p>

		<p>
			<q who="TH"> Mrs. Margaret Sanger said that birth control was the key-not of a new moral
				and spiritual awakening. It was not only a health or economic expedient. It was a
				moral and social principle. That principle was interlocked with the spiritual
				advancement of nations and with the race as well.</q>
		</p>


		<p>
			<q who="TH">Many British Bishops and clergymen, Mrs. Sanger said, had been pleading for
				some time past that the members of the Christian faith should come forth and lead
				the movement so that it might be a constructive force in civilization and not to
				close their eyes and ears to its human appeal.</q>
		</p>

	</docBody>
</doc>
