<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/26 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-10 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1953-01-04">4 Jan 1953</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Arizona Daily Star</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>421968</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Awareness of Birth Control Growing World-Wide, States
					Pioneer in Field, Margaret Sanger Slee</title>, <title>Arizona Daily
					Star</title>, Jan. 4, 1953</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>This article included three photographs, two of Sanger at the <org
				reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 3rd">Third International
				Conference on Planned Parenthood</org>, one with <person reg="Desai, G. N.">G. N.
				Desai</person>, one with Sanger at the podium, and one of <person
				reg="Sanger, Nancy">Nancy Sanger</person>, her granddaughter. She was interviewed on
			her return from the conference.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control laws and legislation in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/></headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Awareness of Birth Control Growing World-Wide, States Pioneer in Field, Margaret
			Sanger Slee</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>"It is everywhere evident that the awareness of the need of birth control in
					<place>Asia</place> is far ahead of the material to meet that need," commented
				Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee, leader of the international birth control movement, on
				the overpopulation problem of Asia.</p>
			<p><q who="ADS">It was hard to imagine, sitting there with her in the quiet spaciousness
					of her <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place> home, that only a few weeks ago,
					she had been traveling extensively in the hot, overcrowded countries of
					Asia.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">She left her home, 65 Sierra Vista Drive in October to attend the <org
						reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 3rd">Third
						International Planned Parenthood Conference</org>, held in late November in
						<place>Bombay, India</place>. En route there she visited
						<place>Japan</place>, <place>Hong Kong</place>, <place>Singapore</place>,
					and <place>Ceylon</place>.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><q who="ADS">During her 1--day visit in Japan, Mrs. Slee was the guest of the
						<org>Mainichi Press</org>. Her agenda was a busy one, including speeches and
					discussions every day. The places she spoke were nearly always crowded to the
					walls and it was not at all unusual for audiences numbering over a thousand to
					hear her speak.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">As her ship docked at <place reg="Yokohama, Japan">Yokohama</place>,
					Mrs. Slee was impressed with the change in architecture.</q> "A city which one
				had been oriental is now completely western,"<q who="ADS"> she remarked.</q> "More
				people seemed to be in modern dress, also."</p>
			<p>"The attitude of the Japanese people has changed," <q who="ADS">Mrs. Slee stated.</q>
				"Formerly it was the desire for a number of children to guarantee the living of the
				old, and now it seems to be the desire for only two children in a family."</p>

		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Ideal Number</head>
			<p><q who="ADS">At a meeting of midwives, nurses and welfare workers, questions were
					invited as to the ideal number and spacing of children. The majority said
				"</q>Three, with three year spacing."<q who="ADS"> Over half of the group had two
					children, some had three, and only four had as many as five children.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">However over one million abortions (which are legal in Japan) are
					reported to have taken place in 1950 in that country.</q></p>
			<p>"The <org reg="Japan Government">government (of Japan)</org> recently legalized birth
				control, the first in the world to take this step. Unfortunately an adequate
				education program has not been worked out, one which stresses the important fact
				that abortion is not contraception, that there are better and safer ways of spacing
				pregnancies and limiting families," Mrs. Slee stated in a recent article on Japan
				which appeared in the Dec. 13 issue of the "<title>Nation</title>".</p>
			<p>"Nowhere in the world is there more need for planned parenthood than in Japan. The
				population, which was too great in 1922 for the land to support, was then 66
				million. But now 85 million people are depending on the land for their welfare," she
				said.</p>
			<p>"Japan is compact," <q who="ADS">Mrs. Slee remarked,</q> "and the cruel ravages of
				war are not noticable. She still has her shrines and temples, her flower gardens,
				tea-houses and beautiful theaters. She is still a land of beauty, courtesy, color
				and charm."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Travels in Ceylon, Siam</head>
			<p><q who="ADS">Ceylon and <place>Siam</place> are anxious to organize a birth control
					movement there, but as yet have not been able to do so. While in <place
						reg="Bangkok, Siam">Bankgok</place>, Mrs. Slee talked with 50 young women
					doctors who were eager for the information. </q> "Singapore and Hong Kong," <q
					who="ADS">she said</q> "have clinics established under the British
				government."</p>
			<p><q who="ADS">While in India, Mrs. Slee had dinner with <person
						reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Nehru</person>. He expressed to her that child
					welfare in India must be accomplished on a mass scale and that hunger is the
					first thing to be defeated.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">Fourteen nations attended the conference held in Bombay where the <org
						reg="International Committee for Planned Parenthood">international committee
						for planned parenthood</org> organized into an <org
						reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">international
						federation</org>. <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Lady Rama Rau</person>
					was elected director of the <place reg="Asia">Orient</place> by unanimous vote,
					and Mrs. Slee was named director of <place>North America</place>.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">The organization has <place reg="London, England">London</place> as its
					headquarters and plans its next meeting for 1953 in <place
						reg="Stockholm, Sweden">Stockholm</place>.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">A gift of $2500 was sent by Tucson women to set up the first research
					clinic for Planned Parenthood in India. Actually this clinic, which has now been
					set up, is the first clinic for research purposes only, in all of Asia.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">Dr. <person reg="Radhakrishnan, Sarvepali">S. Radhakrishnan</person>,
					vice-president of India, gave a speech at the conference which particularly
					impressed Mrs. Slee. One of the most important points of the speech was his
					courageous statement taking issue with <person reg="Gandhi, Mohandas K."
						>Gandhi</person>, who advocated abstinence, self-control and rhythm as the
					only means for limiting population; since anything else, Gandhi believed, was an
					interference with nature.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">Dr. Radhakrishnan pointed out that self-control and abstinence is an
					interference with nature. Rhythm, too, he observed, is an interference with
					nature, and by the use of rhythm,once recognizes a justification in the marital
					relationship apart from parenthood, just as one would by the use of
					contraceptives.</q></p>
			<p><q who="ADS">A magazine reporting the progress of the planned parenthood movement is
					available to any interested person at no charge. Entitled "<title type="journal"
						>Population Bulletin</title>," the magazine may be obtained by writing to
					501 Madison avenue, <place reg="New York, NY">New York city</place>.</q></p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
