<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/17 AS</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-14 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Milburn, Betty">Betty Milburn</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1959-04-04">4 Apr 1959</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Around Your Home: Interview With Margaret Sanger</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421961</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Oriental Art Dominates Home of Mrs. Slee</title>, <title
					type="journal"> Tucson Daily Citizen, Apr. 4, 1959, pp. 48-49</title>
			</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TDC">Tucson Daily Citizen</name>
			<name id="WRIFR">Wright, Frank Lloyd</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="planned parenthood"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Oriental Art Dominates Home of Mrs. Slee</head>
		<byline>By <person reg="Milburn, Betty">BETTY MILBURN</person></byline>


		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Interesting people just naturally have interesting houses.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">And Margaret Sanger Slee is no exception.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">She lives in a delightfully unusual house in <place reg="Tucson, AZ"
					>Catalina Vista,</place> surrounded by treasures she and her late husband
				collected from all over the world.</q>
		</p>

		<p>"In 1952, I asked <person reg="Wright, Frank Lloyd">Frank Lloyd Wright</person> to design
			a house for me. He asked <q who="WRIFR">'on how many acres?,'</q> and when I said a 150
			by 135 foot lot, he gasped with horror and declined," <q who="TDC">laughed Mrs.
				Slee.</q></p>
		<p>"So then I asked <person reg="Brown, Arthur">Arthur Brown</person> to be my architect.
			Now, of course, I'm delighted that Mr. Wright declined, because Mr. Brown did a perfect
			house for me-exactly what I wanted!"</p>

		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Slee explained that she does not care for boxes or square, regular
				rooms.</q>
		</p>

		<p>"And I didn't want to look out and see the ground. I wanted to see sky, flowers and
			trees."</p>

		<p>
			<q who="TDC"><person reg="Caffrey, H. E.">H. E. Caffrey</person> was the contractor and
				Mrs. Slee did the interior decor.</q>
		</p>

		<p>"I just put in the house the things I owned," <q who="TDC">she said.</q></p>

		<p>
			<q who="TDC">And what fabulous things they are! She collected them throughout a lifetime
				spent traveling throughout the world, as the founder of and crusader for planned
				parenthood and also as the wife of an <person reg="Slee, J. Noah H.">oil
					executive</person> who had lived in the <place reg="Asia">Orient</place> since
				1910.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Slee's home is of contemporary design, and makes use of such 20th
				century techniques as curved fiberglass walls and stainless steel mantles. Yet its
				contemporary simplicity makes it a perfect background for exquisite furnishings and
				art objects of all ages and cultures.</q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
