<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-05-02 JK initial tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-08 CH proof tags again</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1946-00-00">1946</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control, 1945</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421953</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title> (1946), p. 126-27</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For other articles in the <title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title> series,
			see <xref from="320973.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1941</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320974.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1942</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320975.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1943</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320976.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1944</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320978.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1946</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320979.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1947</title></xref>;
				<xref from="321981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1948</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320981.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1949</title></xref>;
				<xref from="321980.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1950</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320983.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1951</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1952</title></xref>;
				<xref from="321984.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1953</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320985.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1954</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320986.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1955</title></xref>;
				<xref from="421076.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1956</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320987.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1957</title></xref>;
				<xref from="320988.xml"><title type="article">Birth Control, 1958</title></xref></p>
		<index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control.</head>
		<p>The activities of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>, Inc. (formerly
			the <org>Birth Control Federation of America</org>), through its 347 state leagues and
			committees and 599 clinics, were given material support and stimulation by events of
			1945, which found child spacing services either through clinics or referral systems.
			available in every state except <place>Connecticut</place> and
				<place>Massachusetts</place>. These were in 1945 the only states retaining legal
			barriers which prevented physicians prescribing birth control under any condition.</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Legal Decisions.-</emph> Two pertinent decisions were handed down in
			1945 by the district court of appeals in <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington,
				D.C.</place> The first, a permanent injunction barring the postmaster general from
			interfering with the mailing of the <org reg="Consumers Union">Consumer's Union</org>
			<title type="book">“Report on Contraceptive Material</title>”; the second, overruling
			the postmaster general’s mailing ban on <person reg="Popenoe, Paul">Paul
				Popenoe</person>'s pamphlet, <title type="book">“Preparing for
			Marriage.”</title></p>
		<p> In Connecticut a bill to permit physicians to prescribe birth control for patients in
			poor health was killed in committee, although a <org
				reg="Roper Center for Public Opinion Research">Roper</org> survey made just previous
			to the bill’s introduction revealed that 85% of the state’s adult voters were in favor
			of changing existing laws.</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Medical and Public Health.- </emph><person reg="Herrick, William W."
				>Dr. William W. Herrick</person>, president of the <org>New York Academy of
				Medicine</org>, <place reg="New York, NY">New York city</place>, headed a committee
			of 40 of the city’s distinguished physicians who presented a program on “Responsibility
			for the Health of Tomorrow’s Family” at the federation’s 24th annual dinner. Dinner
			speakers included <person reg="Williams, R. C.">Dr. R. C. Williams</person>, assistant
			U.S. surgeon-general, <org reg="United States Public Health Service">U.S. public health
				service</org>; <person reg="Schumann, Edward A.">Dr. Edward A. Schumann</person>;
			and Lt. Col. <person reg="Grinker, Roy R.">Roy R. Grinker</person>, medical executive,
			Army Air Force Convalescent hospital, <place reg="St. Petersburg, FL">St. Petersburg,
				Fla</place>. A luncheon address by <person reg="Roosevelt, Eleanor">Mrs. Franklin D.
				Roosevelt</person>, before a symposium of social agencies interested in postwar
			family health, including planned parenthood, was broadcast over a national network.</p>
		<p> Temperature chars to assist in determining optimum fertility were made available to
			physicians by the federation’s medical committee, to aid in the treatment of
			infertility. This phase of the planned parenthood program was increased with
			establishment of added infertility services or referral systems in various parts of the
			country. </p>
		<p>From a study of 7,000,000 births, <person reg="Yerushalmy, Jacob">Dr. Jacob
				Yerushalmy</person>, principal statistician of the U.S. public health service,
			published a report advocating an optimum interval between births to decrease the number
			of stillbirths.</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Research. - </emph>To stimulate research in the field of human
			fertility, the <org reg="Lasker Foundation"><person reg="Lasker, Albert D."
					>Albert</person> and <person reg="Lasker, Mary">Mary Lasker</person>
				foundation</org> made the first of its two annual awards of $500 each to the
			scientist and public health official making significant contributions during the year.
			Awards for 1945 went to <person reg="MacLeod, John James Rickard">Dr. John
				MacLeod</person>, department of anatomy, <org
				reg="Cornell University Medical College">Cornell University Medical college</org>,
				<place reg="Ithaca, NY">Ithaca, N.Y.</place>, for research in the motility of the
				<org>Mississippi state board of health</org> for including planned parenthood in his
			state’s public health program to improve infant and maternal health. </p>
		<p><emph rend="bold">Education. - </emph>The publication of two new patient pamphlets,
				<title type="book">“Planning to Have a Baby?”</title> and <title type="book">“The
				Soldier Takes a Wife”</title> contributed materially to the large amount of
			literature requested during the year. <title type="book">“To Those Denied a
				Child”</title> and <title type="book">“Population and Peace,”</title> a reprint of
			an address by Dr. <person reg="Fairchild, Henry Pratt">Henry Pratt Fairchild</person> at
			the <org>University of Virginia</org>, were also in great demand. Quantities of
			technical manuals and other planned parenthood literature were sent on request to
			physicians, educators, health officer, clergymen and social workers.</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Social Work. -</emph>
			<org reg="National Association of Social Workers">National Social Work Advisory
			</org>committee was organized to give professional advice on the social work program.
			The <org reg="Young Women's Christian Association">Y.W.C.A.</org> announced its
			resolution favouring “the principles of planned parenthood.” Planned parenthood
			literature was included by the <org>National Publicity council</org> in its mailings to
			social agencies throughout the country, many of which ordered further literature for
			distribution. </p>
		<p><emph rend="bold">Work With Negroes. -</emph> A second consultant on work with Negroes
			was added to the national staff, and several state organizations employed Negro field
			workers and included Negro members in their executive committees. A model clinic, the
				<org reg="Hannah Stone Planned Parenthood Centre">Hannah Stone Planned Parenthood
				centre</org>, was established in <place reg="New York, NY">Harlem </place>district,
			New York city, to aid in reducing stillbirth, infant and maternal mortality, which is
			twice that of other parts of the city. Following an intensive study, the <org>National
				Congress of Colored Parents and Teachers</org> drew up a discussion outline of
			planned parenthood to be distributed to Negro community groups.</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Religion.-</emph> A syllabus on marriage and family counseling was
			published by the federation’s <org> National Clergyman’s Advisory council </org>and made
			available for us in seminaries, community training schools and to individual clergymen.
			Army and navy chaplains made wide use of the G.I. pamphlet, <title type="book">“The
				Soldier Takes a Wife,”</title> and the library of congress translated the pamphlet
			into braille for blinded veterans. The <place>Illinois</place> league for planned
			parenthood added 500 ministers and rabbis to its Clergyman’s Advisory committee and a
			number of other state organizations established similar committees.</p>
		<p>
			<emph rend="bold">Press and Radio. -</emph> Eighty articles reflecting favourable
			planned parenthood attitudes appeared in national popular and technical magazines during
			1945. The announcement of the federation’s two new pamphlets, (see <emph rend="italics"
				>Education</emph>, above) attracted considerable newspaper comment, and wire
			services carried the story throughout the country. Cordial relations with many local
			radio stations were strengthened and both <org>National Broadcasting Company</org> and
			org system carried important annual meeting speakers. The <org
				reg="Mutual Broadcasting System">Mutual Broadcasting system</org> requested a
			speaker to discuss <title type="book">“The Soldier Takes a Wife”</title> during a
			national news cast. The <org reg="Houston Maternal Health Center"><place
					reg="Houston, TX">Houston (Texas)</place> Maternal health centre</org> produced
			a 15 minute transcription which is available to all planned parenthood groups for local
			broadcast. </p>
		<p>International. -Interest in planned parenthood showed new gains throughout the world with
			the ending of World War II. In <place>England</place>, governmental inquiries disclosed
			that economic and national insecurity, not the knowledge of birth control, was the
			determining factor in the declining birth rate. <place>China</place> and
				<place>Japan</place> took official steps to adopt birth control measures to help
			solve their problems of overpopulation. Students of demography reported that
				<place>India</place> must include birth control in its health program if the high
			infant and maternal mortality was to be reduced. The western world learned of a ruling
			of the <person reg="al-Husseini, Haj Amin">grand mufti of <place>Egypt
			</place></person>in 1937 grating legal and religious permission for the practice of
			birth control. (See also <title type="article">BIRTH STATISTICS</title>.) (M. Sr.)</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
