<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Wiggins, Alliene">Alliene Wiggins</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1949-05-04">04 May 1949</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">San Angelo Comments</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421932</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">"M. Sanger Strikes at Evil that Breaks Up
				Happiness"</title>, <title type="journal">San Angelo Evening Standard</title>, May
				4, 1949</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SAES">San Angelo Evening Standard</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke at a dinner in <place reg="San Angelo, TX">San
				Angelo</place>, sponsored by the annual meeting of the <org>Planned Parenthood
				League of Texas</org>. The dinner meeting was held at the <org>St. Angelus
				Hotel</org>. For her speech to the State Planned Parenthood Convention, see <xref
				from="421931.xml">Preparation of Parenthood for World Peace</xref>, May 5, 1949.</p>
		<index level1="planned parenthood"/>
		<index level1="Europe" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Europe" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"/></headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>M. Sanger Strikes At Evil Which Breaks Up Happiness</head>
		<byline>by ALLIENE WIGGINS Standard-Times Staff</byline>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The only cause for social betterment today that will remain in textbooks
				and histories 500 years from now will be that of birth control.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">This was the opinion of Mrs. Margaret Sanger, famed crusader for the
				movement, who spoke informally Wednesday night at the dinner held at the St. Angelus
				Hotel, following a reception at the home of Mr. and Mrs. Howard Cox.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger, a gray-haired, attractive woman, is the kind of individual
				whom one sees and thinks: Here is a real person. </q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The reaction of last night's dinner guests to her speech was evidence that
				she affects most people in the same manner. The audience rose to applaud her when
				she was introduced by George Ripley of Dallas.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The speaker remarked that she had long since curtailed her attendance at
					<org reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org>
				meetings in <place reg="United States">America</place>, spending most of her time in
					<place>Italy</place>, <place>Germany</place>, and <place>Japan</place>, where
				she felt the birth control advocacy was more sorely needed. But that,</q> “The famed
			feminine wiles of southern womanhood, of which I’ve heard all my life [] me. I was
			convinced by letter than the San Angelo organization could not have this state meeting
			without my presence; that it needed my advice and encouragement. And what do I find? One
			of the most efficient organizations possible, and with such an enviable record,” <q
				who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger said. <place>Europe</place> has always offered less barriers
				to her movement; and today, the question of population is of </q>“overwhelming
			concern because it is increasing far beyond the resources of the countries.” </p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">In closing Mrs. Sanger called the group's attention to the problems that
				Great Britain faced today in regard to over-population and the dilemma that country
				finds itself in. The commonwealth countries, as Australia, Canada, and New Zealand,
				have offered their less populated lands for emigration of England's increasing
				persons, but with the stipulation that only the healthy, energetic, and capable will
				be admitted. The Labour government turned thumbs down, as it would leave England
				with the sick, incompetent and aged persons, she explained.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The Texas League is privileged to have Mrs. Sanger as a speaer at their
				meeting as she has not attended a state conference in several years.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Making her home in Tucson, Mrs. Sanger is now primarily interested in
				clinical research and the international situation with relation to the planned
				parenthood movement. For the past three years she has worked in the Scandinavian
				countries and England to help in reconstructing the birth control work, which
				well-established before World War II, was done away with during the Nazis
				regime.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Europe has always offered less barriers tot he movement; and today, the
				question of population is of </q>"overwhelming concern because it is increasing far
			beyond the resources of the countries."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">At a conference in England last year, 34 countries were represented,
				showing the extent of the interest in this movement.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">There are 18 million people in England and Wales today whom the two
				countries can not feed properly. In the vastly over-populated countries such as
				India and China, there is the immediate problem of starvation or immigration. Mrs.
				Sanger is working now with as intense a zeal as in her primary crusade in the United
				States to help alleviate this problem.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The Planned Parenthood League, which emerged in its present form in 1939,
				is now an accepted institution in every state except Massachusetts and Connecticut.
				It is against the law in Massachusetts for a doctor to give any contraceptive means
				to a mother even if the birth of another child would mean her death. In a recent
				election, 75,000 citizens signed a petition placing the question of the removal of
				these restrictions on the ballot, but the opposition, firmly entrenched in the press
				and radio, defeated the movement. There are, however, about 1,280 national and state
				organizations which have endorsed the movement.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The medical profession has fully endorsed the movement which Mrs. Sanger
				has advocated for many years as a scientific method to attain better health for the
				nation's mothers and families. Her struggle began in 1909 when her nursing
				experience with a poverty-stricken mother, who caused her own death by trying to
				stop the coming of another child, filled her with resolve to strike at the root of
				the evil which was breaking the health of mothers throughout the country. Her
				crusade against government, religious, and press opposition since that time is an
				exciting and inspiring story of a determined woman who sees the need of a social
				reform and fights for it against all obstacles. </q></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
