<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1949-05-02">02 May 1949</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">El Paso Comments</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421937</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">"U.S. Health Plan Seen as Foe of Planned
				Parenthood"</title>, <title type="journal">El Paso Herald Post</title>, May 2, 1949,
				p. 20</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="EPHP">El Paso Herald Post</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger provided the press with comments while in <place reg="El Paso, TX">El
			Paso</place>, staying with <person reg="Goetting, Betty-Mary">Betty-Mary
				Goetting</person>. For a speech she gave in San Angelo later that wee see <xref
				from="421931.xml">Preparation of Parenthood for World Peace</xref>, May 5, 1949.</p>
		<index level1="planned parenthood"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="disputes within"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Connecticut"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Massachusetts"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>U.S. Health Plan Seen As Foe of Planned Parenthood</head>
		<p>
			<q who="EPHP">Socialized medicine is a serious threat to the planned parenthood
				movement, Mrs. Sanger, world pioneer of the movement, said in El Paso today.</q>
		</p>
		<p> “A medical program under government control would permit pressure groups hostile to
			planned parenthood to stifle the movement through political pressure,” she said. </p>
		<p>“Already in the state public health programs of <place>Massachusetts</place> and
				<place>Connecticut</place> certain doctors have been forbidden the use of hospital
			facilities because political blocs objected to their being in favor of planned
			parenthood,” she added.</p>
		<p><q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger was the house guest of Mrs. Charles Goetting of Rosedale
				Addition in the Lower Valley. Mrs. Goetting is honorary president of the
					<org>Planned Parenthood Center of El Paso</org> at 1926 Arizona street.</q></p>
		<p><q who="EPHP">Members of the local Planned Parenthood Center, headed by <person
					reg="Fletcher, Anna M.">Mrs. A. Ransford Fletcher</person>, president, will
				accompany Mrs. Sanger to <place reg="San Angelo, TX">San Angelo</place> for the
				state planned parenthood convention to be held on Wednesday and Thursday.</q></p>
		<p><q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger will speak there on "Preparation of Parenthood for World
				Peace."</q></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
