<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-04-02 JK initial tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Wiggins, Alliene">Alliene Wiggins</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1949-05-05 ">05 May 1949</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Preparation of Parenthood for World
					Peace</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421931</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Takes Stand Against
					Socialized Medicine</title>, <title type="journal">San
					Angelo Evening Standard</title>, May 6, 1949</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SAES">San Angelo Evening Standard</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke before a state meeting of the <org>Planned Parenthood
				League of Texas</org>, held in <place reg="San Angelo, TX">San
				Angelo</place>, at the <org>Cactus Hotel</org> on May 4 and 5.
			For remarks Sanger made at a dinner on May 4, see <xref
				from="421932.xml">San Angelo Comments</xref>, May 4, 1949.</p>
		<index level1="planned parenthood"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement"/>
		<index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="physically disabled and diseased"
			level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Takes Stand Against Socialized Medicine</head>
		<byline>by ALLIENE WIGGINS Standard-Times Staff</byline>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Margaret Sanger, whose name broke into the headlines
				in the early 1900s as an advocate of birth control, and who is
				now honorary chairman of the <org>Planned Parenthood Federation
					of America</org>, opposed socialized medicine in an address
				at the state meeting of the <org>Planned Parenthood League of
					Texas</org> Thursday in San Angelo.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger advised those interested in the planned
				parenthood movement to avoid and prevent socialized medicine.
				The stand against socialized medicine was made incidentally as
				she spoke at luncheon on the work of the organization and of her
				foreign field work in <place>Europe</place>.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES"><person reg="Rice, Mrs. L. M.">Mrs. F. M.
					Rice</person> of <place reg="Dallas, TX">Dallas</place>,
				state president, conducted all business sessions of the two-day
				convention which closed here Thursday afternoon with the
				election of new officers. <person reg="Snodgrass, Marie">Mrs.
					Scott Snodgrass</person> of San Angelo, currently first
				vice-president, is the new president-elect and <person
					reg="Fletcher, Anna M.">Mrs. A. R. Fletcher</person> of
					<place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso</place> was elected
				secretary. <person reg="Halff, Catherine">Mrs. Hugh
					Halff</person> of <place reg="San Antonio, TX">San
					Antonio</place> will continue serving as second
				vice-president. <person reg="Schmid, Clara Forres">Mrs. W. A.
					Schmid</person> of <place reg="Fort Worth, TX">Fort
					Worth</place> is retiring secretary.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger began her address by saying 40 per cent of
				the people of the world today are not being fed properly. This
				problem combined with that of overpopulation, is of prime
				importance in the world today.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Citing <place>Germany</place>, <place>Italy</place>,
				and <place>Japan</place> as examples of nations forced to seek
				lands to provide resources for their over-supplied citizenry,
				Mrs. Sanger pointed out that today the population of Japan is
				increasing at more than a million a year--this in a country
				smaller than the state of <place>California</place> and with few
				resources. These people will have to be supported for the next
				20 or 25 years, and unless the birth rate is curtailed the
				problem will be an endless one.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">In countries such as Japan, a national educational
				program on birth control should be introduced. To show the
				eagerness of the people for a solution to this problem, Mrs.
				Sanger told how, in 1921, landing in a port in Japan, she was
				greeted by a group of Japanese women who had heard a radio
				broadcast of hers concerning birth control. These women told her
				they were not interested in most women’s rights movements but
				Mrs. Sanger’s reform was one keenly needed by their country
				women. However the military leaders in Japan, interested in
				building up armies, opposed the presentation of any methods
				limiting population. </q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger defined birth control as the </q>
			“conscious control of the birth rate by means which prevent the
			conception of life.” <q who="SAES"> Thus, life is not destroyed
				because life is never conceived. Conscious control is not a
				limitation because controls are placed on all phases of modern
				life. For example, traffic is controlled but it still comes and
				goes.</q></p>

		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger believes that the control of the birth
				rate is what is lacking throughout the world today. The planned
				parenthood movement strives to direct this problem into channels
				where the medical profession can advise on the methods of
				controlling the birth rate.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Three of the prime aims of the planned parenthood
				movement were given by Mrs. Sanger. To prevent people who have
				transmissible diseases from having children is one of the
				greatest questions in the world. Institutions are full of people
				who should never have been conceived. Feeble-minded, defective
				people should in many cases be sterilized as a protection to
				society by preventing the continued birth of misfits who will
				become state wards. Standards as to health and mental ability
				are placed on immigrants coming into our country, but there are
				no stipulations as to the fitness of the individuals within this
				country who reproduce and help populate the land.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Another aim of birth control is to let mothers, who
				have a temporary disease such as tuberculosis, recover before
				another pregnancy occurs. One-fourth of the women who die from
				pregnancy during a disease knew they have the disease before
				becoming pregnant.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The spacing of children, which Mrs. Sanger believes
				has helped the movement more than anything else, was the third
				aim mentioned. Babies should be spaced according to the health
				of the mother, and the number of babies should depend upon the
				earning ability of the father. She quoted from a medical journal
				that stated that spacing resulted in stronger babies and
				healthier mothers. For the young couple entering marriage, birth
				control gives them an opportunity to adjust themselves to
				marriage before starting their family.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">Mrs. Sanger urged members of the League not to forget
				that the primary cause of the movement was to get to the poorest
				strata of people, to help them in solving their problem of large
				families, poor health, and limited income. The goal of the
				movement is not to let the peculiar kind of birthrate now
				existing (few children among families who can support them; many
				children among poor families), continue; but to arouse public
				health agencies as to their responsibility to society with
				regard to the kind of people who have children.</q>
		</p>

		<p>
			<q who="SAES">There is</q> “no other organization today so important
			to our children or our children’s future,”<q who="SAES"> Mrs. Sanger
				believes. The movement will</q> "build sounder marriages, better
			health, and a better world; laying the foundation for the greatest
			civilization the world has ever known.” </p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES"><person reg="Tweedy, Florence D.">Mrs. Mellick
					Tweedy</person>, of San Angelo, who worked with Mrs. Sanger
				in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> in 1917,
				introduced her. Mrs. Sanger recognized <person
					reg="Ripley, Katie Rice">Mrs. George Ripley</person> of
				Dallas, Mrs. <person reg="Nelms, Agnese Carter">Agnese
					Nelms</person> of <place reg="Houston, TX">Houston</place>,
				and <person reg="Goetting, Betty-Mary">Mrs. Charles
					Goetting</person> of El Paso as three Texas women who have
				done unselfish and untiring work in pioneering the birth control
				movement.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SAES">The Thursday afternoon business session, which
				concluded the two-day meeting, included reports by the following
				state officers: President, Mrs. L. M. Rice of Dallas; first vice
				president, Mrs. Scott Snodgrass of San Angelo; second vice
				president, Mrs. Hugh Halff of San Antonio; and secretary, Mrs.
				W. A. Schmid of Fort Worth.</q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
