<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-30 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1937-07-19">19 Jul 1937</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on National Committee on Federal
					Legislation for Birth Control Report</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421918</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">"More Clinics Urged for Birth
					Control"</title>, <title type="journal">New York
					Times</title>, Jul. 19, 1937</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="article">Auto Caravans Urged to Help Birth
					Control"</title>, <title type="journal">New York
					Herald-Tribune</title> Jul. 19, 1937. </bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
			<name id="NYHT">New York Herald Tribune</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger released a press statement to coincide with
			an <org
				reg="National Committee for Federal Legislation for Birth Control "
				>NCFLBC</org> report. Quotes were drawn from news coverage,
			duplicated portions not quoting Sanger were omitted.</p>
		<index
			level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"
			/><index level1="Comstock Laws"/><index
			level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/><index
			level1="birth control methods"/><index level1="birth control"
			level2="distribution of information about"/></headNote>
	<docBody>

		<head>MORE CLINICS URGED FOR BIRTH CONTROL</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p><q who="NYT">A ten-fold increase in existing birth-control
					centers to 3,000 is recommended by Mrs. Margaret Sanger,
					birth-control leader, in a report on the seven years' work
					of the <org>National Committee for Federal Legislation on
						Birth Control</org>, which will be issued today by the
					organization's executive committee.</q></p>
			<p><q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger recommends also that visiting nurses
					should be sent into isolated homes remote from medical
					service to teach birth-control measures. The committee
					making the report recently was dissolved after the United
					States Circuit Court of Appeals upheld birth control under
					medical direction. The executive committee comprises <person
						reg="Timme, Ida Haar">Mrs. Walter Timme</person>,
						<person reg="Hepburn, Katharine Houghton">Mrs. Thomas N.
						Hepburn</person>, <person reg="Barker, Marion B.">Mrs.
						Alexander C. Barker</person>, and <person
						reg="Brush, Dorothy Hamilton">Mrs. Alexander C.
						Dick</person>.</q></p>
			<p>“This decision,” <q who="NYT">wrote Mrs. Sanger, referring to the
						<org
						reg="United States Court of Appeals For the Second Circuit"
						>Circuit Court ruling,</org>
				</q>“has opened the way to a far more fundamental goal--the
				inclusion of birth control in public health programs and the
				carrying of contraceptive information to neglected mothers in
				isolated regions. We must help the mothers who as yet are not
				reached through public health channels. We urge caravans of
				education and help for mountain women, farm women, mothers in
				distant homesteads, mothers in all districts, city and country,
				who are neglected.</p>
			<p> “We should send an organization of birth-control-instructing
				nurses to visit the homes of these underprivileged mothers. Just
				as members of the <org
					reg="Visiting Nurse Associations of America">American
					Visiting Nurses Association</org> have gone into the homes
				to help through bedside work, so would we like to see an army of
				equipped, sympathetic, understanding nurses take up this task of
				educating and instructing mothers in contraceptive techniques
				and thus free them from the constant fear which haunts their
				lives.” </p>
		</div>


		<div type="section">
			<head>Auto Caravans Urged to Help Birth Control</head>
			<p><q who="NYHT">Extension of birth control clinical service by
					motor caravans to women of the farms and mountain regions of
					America was urged yesterday by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth
					control leader, in a series of recommendations advocating a
					ten-fold increase in birth control activities in the United
					States in the next year.</q></p>
			<p><q who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger estimated that 320 birth control
					centers were functioning at present in America, nearly all
					of them in large population centers. In addition,
					approximately 7,000 hospitals and 10,000 other agencies
					where medical aid is sought by mothers are now legally free
					to give contraceptive advice and information as a result of
					recent decision of the United States Circuit Court of
					Appeals</q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Caravans of Education</head>
			<p>This decision,<q who="NYHT"> Mrs. Sanger said, </q>"has opened
				the way to a far more fundamental goal--the inclusion of birth
				control in public health programs and the carrying of
				contraceptive information to neglected mothers in isolated
				regions."</p>
			<p>"We must help the mothers who are not yet reached through public
				health channels. We urge caravans of education and help for
				mountain women, farm women, mothers on distant homesteads,
				mothers in all districts, city and country, who are now
				neglected."</p>
			<p><q who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger said letters received from rural
					communities indicated there were tens of thousands, perhaps
					millions of women unable to go to a clinic or obtain
					contraceptive information from existing
				organizations.</q></p>
			<p>"We should send an organization of birth control instructing
				nurses to visit the homes of those underprivileged mothers,"<q
					who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger declared.</q> "Just as members of the
				American Visiting Nurses Association have gone into the homes to
				help through bedside work, so would we like to see an army of
				equipped sympathetic, understanding nurses take up this task of
				educating and instructing mothers in contraceptive techniques
				and thus free them from the constant fear which haunts their
				lives.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Advocates 3,000 Clinics</head>
			<p><q who="NYHT">Expressing the belief that at least 3,000
					contraceptive clinics were needed in the United States, Mrs.
					Sanger stated:</q></p>
			<p>“Only by adequate effort to save the lives of women and to
				promote maternal and child health can the community atone for
				the deaths of a million mothers during the six decades while the
					<person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Comstock</person> laws were
				interpreted as preventing birth control even under medical
				auspices. Those who won the legal fight for birth control must
				now move fast, and keep moving; for women and children are still
				needlessly dying. Their lives may be saved if contraceptive
				facilities become adequately available in every community.” </p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
