<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-04-09 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-30 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-13 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1937-09-22">22 Sept 1937</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Japanese Invasion of China</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421915</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="journal">Los Angeles Daily News</title>, Sept. 22, 1937</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="LADN">Los Angeles Daily News</name>
			<name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger released a press statement in <place reg="Honolulu, HI">Honolulu</place> after her
			trip to <place>China</place> was canceled by the Japanese invasion. The complete
			statement was not found and newspaper coverage has been substituted.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to" level3="international"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"
			level3="negative consequences of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="in Japan"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="population policies of"/>
		<index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="regulation of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Exponent of Birth Control Despairs of Orientals</head>
		<div>
			<p><q who="LADN">Japanese bombs are blowing up Chinese who "should never have been
					born," and yesterday Margaret Sanger, world-famous birth control leader, sadly,
					turned her back on her Oriental birth control campaign and headed for Los
					Angeles. Miss Sanger left here July 24 to carry a birth control crusade to the
					Orient, long considered a "</q>danger spot<q who="LADN">" of the world by birth
					control advocates because of the Orient's failure to adopt birth control.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="LADN">On <place reg="Shanghai, China">Shanghai</place>, where Miss Sanger
					hoped to drop scientific words, Japanese have relentlessly been dropping
					bombs.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="LADN">Yesterday, Miss Sanger was in Honolulu, waiting to sail for <place
						reg="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</place> on the <name type="ship">S. S.
						Lurline</name>, which arrives at Los Angeles Harbor September 30. </q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="LADN">From Honolulu Miss Sanger sent these comments:</q> “Population
				pressure is a cause of war, and <place>Japan</place>, <place>Italy</place> and
					<place>Germany</place>, through failure to control their birthrates, are
				justifying predictions that they would become the world’s ‘danger spots’.” </p>
			<p>
				<q who="LADN"> Hostilities halted Miss Sanger's campaign to help curb overpopulation
					among the Chinese and Korean masses, but she nevertheless carried out extensive
					propaganda in Japan. </q>
			</p>
			<p> “Japan had 64,000,000 persons when I was there in 1922, and since then the
				population has increased steadily from 800,000 to 1,000,000 a year,” <q who="LADN"
					>she said</q>. “But despite the annexation of <place>Manchukuo</place>, Japan is
				still land-hungry. It has become, with Germany and Italy, a destroyer of
				civilization through ruthless waging of arrogant warfare against innocent, peaceful
				peoples.</p>
			<p> “All these nations refuse to control their birthrate, and they refuse to give to
				women the simple knowledge that could save the lives of untold thousands of women. </p>
			<p> “Women’s progress in Japan has been retarded- the women have not been able to
				maintain the advances they had made as far back as 1922. Reactionary forces, soon
				after the earthquake, set up a strong, bureaucratic, militaristic government, and
				since then women have not been allowed the natural freedom of evolutionary progress.
				Women are not granted degrees in their colleges and universities, and of all the
				women who have been allowed to attend medical universities, only 16 have been
				granted medical degrees, through ‘special dispensation.’”</p>
			<p>
				<q who="LADN">Miss Sanger praised the action of the Chinese Medical Association, in
					urging recognition of contraception as a part of public health, as an
				</q>"outstanding event." </p>
			<p> “In Japan,” <q who="LADN">she said</q>, “a campaign of public health is just raising
				its head, and a new health institute which will provide an opportunity for mothers
				in outlying districts to receive medical aid, but not birth control aid, will open
				next year. But one can never foresee what may happen in a militaristic country, and
				so the future is still dark and overclouded.” </p>
			<p> Mrs. Sanger sailed on the S. S. Hoover with a broken wrist, suffered when she fell
				on a stairway. Passengers, she said, were disappointed to find that it was not a war
				casualty. </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head> Mrs. Sanger Assails ‘Population’ Nations</head>
			<byline> She Cites Japan as a Present Aggressor That Has Refused to Limit Its Births </byline>
			<p><q who="NYT">Population pressure due to lack of birth control has made Japan, Italy,
					and Germany menaces to world peace, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth control leader,
					said in a letter made publish yesterday by the Birth Control Clinical Research
					Bureau, 17 West Sixteenth Street</q>.</p>
			<p>
				<q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger, returning from a tour of the Far East interrupted by
					Sino-Japanese hostilities, is expected to sail from Honolulu for Los Angeles on
					Saturday.</q>
			</p>
			<p> “As far back as 1925,” <q who="NYT">she wrote</q>, “Professor <person
					reg="Thompson, Warren">Warren Thompson</person>, in his brilliant analysis of
				the population problem, named Italy, Japan and Germany as ‘danger spots’ of the
				world. Japan is fulfilling that prophecy, and not only are these countries the
				danger spots of the world, but they are the destroyers of our civilization through
				their ruthless method of waging arrogant warfare against innocent, peaceful peoples. </p>
			<p> “All of these three nations refuse to control their birth rates and they also refuse
				to give to their women and to their mothers the simple knowledge which could save
				the lives of thousands upon thousands of these women and avoid the destitution,
				misery and enslavement of large masses of their population.”</p>
			<p>
				<q who="NYT">Mrs. Sanger said Japan</q> “is keenly disappointed over the natural
				resources of Manchukuo and is still land-hungry.”</p>
			<p>
				<q who="NYT">The most encouraging featuer of her trip, she said, was the gathering
					to celebrate the opening of the first modern birth control clinic in Japan,
					under <person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto">Baroness Ishimoto</person>.</q>
			</p>

		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
