<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/23 VS initial tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-02 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1939-03-02">2 Mar 1939</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Talk with the Husbands of El Paso Mothers' Health
					Clinic Patients </supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421949</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mother Should Have Privilege Of Spacing babies, Mrs. Sanger
					Tells El Paso Husbands</title>, <title type="journal">El Paso Times</title>,
				Mar. 3, 1939</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="article">Says Birth Control Doesn't Kill Life</title>, <title
					type="journal">El Paso Herald Post</title>, Mar. 3, 1939</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="EPT">El Paso Times</name>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
			<name id="EPHP">El Paso Herald Post</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger's talk was not found; newspaper coverage was used instead. For her speech the
			night before, see <xref from="421941.xml">El Paso Mothers' Health Clinic Speech</xref>,
			Mar. 1, 1939. </p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="in marriages"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="economic benefits and risks of"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="educational benefits of"/>
		<index level1="child spacing"/>
		<index level1="family planning, principles of"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="reforms"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="men" level2="reproductive choices and decisions"/>
		<index level1="planned parenthood"/>
		<index level1="reproductive responsibility"/>
		<index level1="transmissible disease"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mother Should Have Privilege Of Spacing babies, Mrs. Sanger Tells El Paso
			Husbands</head>
		<div>

			<p><q who="EPT"> Birth control is not abortion, is not illegal and is no longer
					guesswork, Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, leading
					advocate of birth control, assured 15 <place reg="El Paso, TX">El Paso</place>
					husbands at a meeting in the <org reg="El Paso Mother's Health Center">Mothers’
						Health Center</org>, 1820 East Rio Grande Street, Thursday night, when she
					appealed that mothers for the sake of their own health be given the right to
					space the births of their children.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">A mother’s body is depleted of many important chemicals at the birth of
					her child, and it requires six months for her to return to normal, Mrs. Sanger
					said. It is a crime for these mothers to become pregnant again before their
					bodies are normal, she maintained.</q></p>
			<p> “Every woman, rich or poor, robust or delicate, should have the right to space her
				children at least two years apart in order that she may be properly rested before
				renewing the ordeal of childbirth,” <q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Cites Patriotism</head>

			<p><q who="EPT"> Four out of seven tuberculosis women have died in pregnancy, she said.
					Women suffering from tuberculosis, heart trouble, goiter, high blood pressure
					and other diseases should not have children, yet they might marry and live happy
					lives without them, she said.</q></p>
			<p><q who="EPT"> Persons, fathers or mothers, with communicable diseases certainly
					should not have children, she insisted. There is more patriotism in spacing
					children or not having any, she said, than there is in bearing children
					haphazardly or children afflicted.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Decidedly in favor of early marriages, Mrs. Sanger said she is not in
					favor of adolescents having children. Boys between the ages of 14 and 23, and
					girls between the ages of 12 and 22 are in that adolescent period when the
					nervous system is under an intense strain and the bones are still developing.
					They should postpone parenthood until their own bodies are completely developed,
					she said.</q></p>

		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Should Wait Few Years</head>

			<p><q who="EPT"> Even more mature newlyweds should postpone parenthood for a few years,
					she said, and spend the first two years becoming acquainted and adjusted to
					insure many years of happy married life.</q></p>

			<p> “We are more ignorant about women today than we are about cows and chickens,” <q
					who="EPT">she said.</q> “A farmer can write to the <org
					reg="United States Department of Agriculture">Department of Agriculture</org>
				and get information about his cows and chickens and hogs, how to make them healthy,
				heavier and bear strong offspring. But let someone write and as how a woman might
				control births and raise stronger and healthier children and no information is
				forthcoming, or if it is, it is to the effect that you are breaking the law or being
				immoral.”</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Birth control does not, as is frequently argued, make women sterile,
					she said. Statistics from birth control clinics show women practice birth
					control for periods of years and still have children when they want them and
					when they can afford them, she said.</q></p>

			<p> “Birth control is no longer guesswork,” <q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> “We know
				now what birth control will do.”</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head>SAYS BIRTH CONTROL DOESN'T KILL LIFE</head>
			<p><q who="EPHP">Fifteen husbands sat in the neat living room of the Mother's Health
					Center at 1820 East Rio Grande street last night and listened to Mrs. Margaret
					Sanger, noted birth control advocate, tell of the meaning and the purpose of
					birth control as sponsored by the Birth Control Federation of America. The men's
					wives are patients at the birth control center.</q></p>
			<p><q who="EPHP">After her talk the husbands crowded around Mrs. Sanger thanking her and
					asking her questions about her work. The group stayed at the Center and talked
					to the nurse, <person reg="Gillespie, Mrs.">Mrs. Gillespie</person>, after Mrs.
					Sanger left.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Tells of Arguments</head>
			<p>"<q who="UNK">I have read your books,</q><q who="EPHP">one many told her.</q></p>
			<p><q who="EPHP">Another rode in the automobile with Mrs. Sanger and <person
						reg="Goetting, Betty-Mary">Mrs. Charles A. Goetting</person>, president of
					the local board for the Center, and asked questions and told of arguments
					against Mrs. Sanger with which he had been confronted. Mrs. Sanger listened with
					interest. </q></p>
			<p> “It is untrue that practice of birth control kills life or that it makes people who
				practice it sterile,” <q who="HP">Mrs. Sanger said at the meeting.</q></p>
			<p> “There is no life at the time that birth control is practiced. The thing we beg of
				the wives who are in no condition to bear children is to take the trouble to prevent
				conception. We know now that birth control is no longer guess work. We know what it
				will do.</p>
			<p> “No woman with tuberculosis, bad kidneys, heart disease and other diseases, should
				become pregnant,” <q who="HP">she said.</q> “No couple should have children when
				either has a disease.</p>
			<p> “We say that every woman should have the right to space her children, whether she is
				rich or poor, well or sick. Two years is the minimum spacing for children. Three
				years is better. Birth takes chemicals out of a woman’s body.</p>
			<p><q who="EPHP">All couples should wait one or two years after marriage to have
					children to give themselves time to get acquainted, to have spiritual and mental
					adjustment, she said. She favors early marriages.</q></p>
			<p> “There would be fewer separations if couples followed this rule,” <q who="HP">she
					said.</q></p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
