<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/19 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-14 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Warman, S. C.">S. C. Warman</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1959-08-11">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">11 Aug 1959</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied>The Church and Birth Control</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421986</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">"Safe, Sure Birth Control Means Seen in 10 Years"</title>,
					<title type="journal">Tuscon Daily Citizen</title>, Aug. 12, 1959</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TDC">Tucson Daily Citizen</name>
			<name id="LINSA">Lindamood, Samuel J. Jr.</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke at a dinner held at the <org>Mountain View Presbyterian Church</org> in
				<place reg="Scottsdale, AZ">Scottsboro, AZ</place> along with <org
				reg="Planned Parenthood Clinic of Tucscon">Planned Parenthood of Tuscon</org>
			members Rev. <person reg="Lindamood, Samuel J. Jr">Samuel J. Lindamood</person>, Jr.,
				<person reg="Nelson, Lois">Lois Nelson</person>, and <person reg="Kincaid, Della"
				>Della Kincaid</person>. For additional newspaper coverage of this speech, see <xref
				from="422105.xml">The Church and Birth Control</xref>, Aug. 11, 1959.</p>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="pill"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Safe, Sure Birth Control Means Seen In 10 Years</head>
		<byline>By S. C. WARMAN</byline>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Ten more years should bring safe, sure and cheap means of birth control,
				Mrs. Margaret Sanger, founder of the Planned Parenthood Movement, said last night at
				Mountain View Presbyterian Church.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger was referring to the development of a hormone type pill. She
				said it was proving effective in experiments, but was not ready for the general
				market.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"That is what we need for worldwide progress,"<q who="TDC"> she said.</q></p>
		<p><q who="TDC">In one of her rare public appearances here since coming to live in <place
					reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place> 15 years ago, Mrs. Sanger said at the meeting in
				the church patio,</q> "This is my first invitation to your church and I appreciate
			it deeply."</p>
		<p>Mrs. Sanger appeared on the platform and answered about a dozen questions put to her, but
			attempted no speech.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">The speakers on Planned Parenthood in Tucson were the Rev. Samuel J.
				Lindamood Jr., associate pastor; Mrs. Lois Nelson, a board member of the <org
					reg="Planned Parenthood Clinic of Tucson">local association</org>, and Mrs.
				Delia Kincaid, executive secretary.</q>
		</p>
		<p>Mrs. Sanger said she was a nurse in <place reg="New York, NY">New York City</place>.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger appeared on the platform and answered a dozen questions put to
				her, but attempted no speech.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">She was presented by the Rev. Mr. Lindamood, who said:</q>
			<q who="LINSA">She is a person we can admire very greatly. She is a pioneer who has
				overcome persecution with great grace."</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">The chairman's question to Mrs. Sanger was what had started her in the
				planned parenthood career.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger said she was a nurse in New York City.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"I saw the difference (in living conditions) among parents who could space their children
			from those who could not," she said. </p>
		<p>"I began a crusade and was surprised by the difficulties," <q who="TDC">she added.</q> "I
			became aware of federal laws, and state laws and religious prejudice."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Still a world traveler for the <org
					reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">International Planned
					Parenthood</org> movement, Mrs. Sanger recently returned from a second visit
				this year to the <place reg="Asia">Far East</place>. She said <place>Japan</place>
				had cut its birth rate in half the past two years, but that Red <place>China</place>
				"had the word from <place reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place> to take down the signs
				and quit making the materials (for birth control).</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">She said birth control movements were spreading in <place>India</place> and
				other nations of <place>Asia</place>.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger candidly admitted that Japan relied heavily on abortions in
				reducing its birth rate. However, the public health service in Japan, she said, was
				seeking to protect the health of women by spreading information about safer means of
				spacing children.</q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="TDC">In the <place>United States</place> she said</q> "the careless ones who know
			nothing are the ones having the children they can't care for."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Nelson said the Tucson Planned Parenthood clinic had been in operation
				here for 25 years. Mrs. Kincaid said the clinic now at 55 E. Jackson St. is open
				from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. daily. She said three clinic sessions are held weekly for
				women referred to it by doctors, ministers, or interested people and those who come
				in.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Mrs. Kincaid said the clinic is open to the public.</q>
		</p>

		<p>About a hundred attended the meeting, which began with a supper. Previous supper meetings
			have been held on the subjects of segregation and divorce.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
