<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-04-15 JK initial tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-31 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1938-10-18">18 Oct 1938</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Importance of Birth Control in Public Health Plans</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421922</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">"Advocates of Birth Control Await Mrs. Sanger's
					Talk"</title>, <title type="journal">Memphis Commercial Appeal</title>, Oct. 19,
				1938</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="MCA">Memphis Commercial Appeal</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger's speeches in Knoxville and Nashville were not found; newspaper coverage was used in its place.</p>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="southern region"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="public health programs"/>		
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Advocates of Birth Control Await Mrs. Sanger’s Talk </head>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, leading crusader for birth control for 25 years, is
				expected to outline the public health programs of birth control in <place>North
					Carolina</place> when she visits <place reg="Memphis, TN">Memphis</place>
				tomorrow.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">Mrs. Sanger will speak at 8 o'clock tomorrow night at the <org>Fairgrounds
					Casino</org>. The lecture will be free to the public. It is sponsored by the
					<org reg="Memphis Birth Control Committee">Birth Control Committee of
					Memphis</org>.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">On her present trip Mrs. Sanger spoke several times in North Carolina where
				the <org reg="North Carolina State Board of Health">State Board of Health</org> has
				completed the first year of its program to disseminate birth control knowledge
				through public clinics. The lecturer's friend and associate <person
					reg="Blodgett, Marguerite Barstow">Mrs. Stephen Whitney Blodgett</person> of
					<place reg="Fishkill, NY">Fishkill, N.Y.</place> in Memphis now to assist in
				arrangements for the talks here said Mrs. Sanger would describe fully the North
				Carolina plans.</q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="MCA">Mrs. Sanger spoke yesterday in <place reg="Knoxville, TN">Knoxville</place>
				on “The Importance of Birth Control in Public Health Plans.”</q>
		</p>
		<p>“Birth control is safe, wise, economical, and wanted by poor mothers,”<q who="MCA"> she
				declared. Catholic leaders of Memphis have attacked her theories and are forming
				opposition to proposals of state legislation to liberalize Birth Control Laws. They
				have branded birth control as an "immoral, physically injurious practice. . .
				contrary to the <title type="book">Bible</title></q>.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">At Nashville last night, Mrs. Sanger declared the South was the</q> “most
			promising section of the country for birth control.” </p>
		<p>“Now that people are getting over their squeamish attitude toward the subject that has
			been so long misunderstood,”<q who="MCA"> Mrs. Sanger said,</q> “the South offers the
			greatest field for development of birth control.”</p>
		<p> “The large native born population in the South--97 per cent according to statistic
			reports--and the fact that with the exception of about three large centers the people
			are mostly Protestant make the South the most promising section of the country” <q
				who="MCA">for this movement.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">As in her visits to <place reg="Chattanooga, TN">Chattanooga</place>,
				Knoxville, and <place reg="Nashville, TN">Nashville</place>, Mrs. Sanger will meet
				privately with physicians here to discuss birth control methods, Mrs. Blodgett said.
				She will speak at 8:30 o'clock Friday night to a negro audience at the
					<org>Metropolitan Baptist Church</org>, 761 Walker.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">The lectures will deal principally with theory, social and economic
				aspects, and moral argument for birth control, while specific methods will probably
				be discussed at the doctors' meeting, Mrs. Blodgett said. She is in Memphis aiding
				in the arrangements being made by her sister, <person reg="Long, Elizabeth Barstow"
					>Mrs. J. P. Long</person>, head of the local committee.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">It was Mrs. Sanger's work as a nurse in hospitals, private homes and the
				slums of New York that led her to spread the doctrine that </q>"mothers must have
			children only when health and pocketbook permit."<q who="MCA"> She fought through bitter
				years of hostility from governments, publications and churches, and in the face of
				social ostracism and even imprisonment until she won recognition for her ideas as
				worthy of study by legislative bodies.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="MCA">The slight, quietly-dressed, soft-spoken woman carries on a vast
				correspondence with women all over the world.</q></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
