<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-15 JC transcribe and encoding</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-10 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1934-05-24">24 May 1934</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Associated Press Interview</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422044</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Midstream with Modern Women: Margaret Sanger Heads the
					World's Largest Birth Control Clinic</title>, <title type="journal">Scranton
					Republican</title>, May 25, 1934, p. 13 </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SR">Scranton Republican</name>
			<name id="DRYLE">Dryden, Lelia</name>
			<name id="UNK">Unknown</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>The event discussed was likely the <org>American Conference on Birth Control and National
				Recovery</org>, held in Washington in January 1934, and hosted by Lelia Dryden.</p>
		<index level1="Sachs, Sadie"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="awards and tributes"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="need for"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Midstream with Modern Women: Margaret Sanger Heads the World's Largest Birth Control
			Clinic</head>
		<dateline>
			<place reg="Washington, DC">WASHINGTON</place>, <date>May 24</date> (<org
				reg="Associated Press">AP</org>).--</dateline>
		<p>
			<q who="SR">The huge banquet hall in a <org reg="Mayflower Hotel">luxurious Washington
					hotel</org> was filled with persons in formal clothes. The speakers table was
				banked with flowers. An orchestra played softly.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SR">Then entered the woman in whose honor the meeting was called. She was
				alight, with coppery-yellow hair and a half-shy smile. She wore a bright Spanish
				shawl over her white satin dress. There was a cheer.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="DRYLE">"Ladies and gentlemen,"</q>
			<q who="SR">said the <person reg="Dryden, Lelia">toastmaster</person> raising a glass of
				water,</q>
			<q who="DRYLE">"I give you Margaret Sanger."</q>
			<q who="SR">Six hundred glasses were raised.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="DRYLE">"Margaret Sanger,"</q>
			<q who="SR">the speaker went on with a droll smile.</q>
			<q who="DRYLE">"She's a bit of a martyr, a bit of a Tartar, and a bit of a darling,
				too."</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="SR">The guests broke into laughter, and a merry, Celtic smile appeared on Mrs.
				Sanger's face.</q>
		</p>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">'Before Bodies are Broken'</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">Contrast that scene, year 1934, with another year, 1909.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">A youthful nurse was sitting at the bedside of a <person
						reg="Sachs, Sadie">young Jewish mother</person> in <place reg="New York, NY"
						>New York</place>'s lower east side. The mother had tried to stop the birth
					of another child, whose coming she believed would have wrecked her
					poverty-stricken home. For days and nights Margaret Sanger sat at her side,
					struggling with impending death. The woman recovered, but later Mrs. Sanger was
					called to the same house. She arrived just in time to close the woman's eyelids,
					and pull the sheet over her face.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">Mrs. Sanger plodded home, dazed, clutching her nurse's case. Her <person
						reg="Sanger, William">husband</person> and three <person reg="Sanger, Peggy"
						>children</person> were asleep. She stood at a window, thinking until dawn.
					She visioned hundreds of poverty-stricken mothers in New York facing more and
					more children--and then death. The sun rose.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Now I know what I must do," <q who="SR">she said aloud.</q> "I'm through with
				nursing broken bodies. It's only a palliative. I'm going to strike at the
				root--before the bodies are broken."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">That morning started perhaps the most amazing career of crusading ever
					conducted by an American woman.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="SR">She was called "obscene." Her work was termed a "public nuisance." She
					faced irate judges, rode to jail in "Black Marias," fled to
						<place>Europe</place>, spreading her message:</q> "Mothers must have
				children only when health and the pocketbook permit.</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">Today she heads the world's largest <org
						reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau">birth control clinic</org> in
					New York. She has spoken all over the world. Some church conferences, once her
					bitter critics, have voted approval of her crusade.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Sons in Medical School</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">Mrs. Sanger still has that charming little Irish lilt in her voice. She
					laughs easily. She looks and acts like 35, instead of her 51 years.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">She has established headquarters here for the <org
						reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">birth
						control committee on federal legislation</org> which seeks to make it legal
					to use the <place>United States</place> mails for sending birth control
					information.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">She is married for the second time. Her husband is <person
						reg="Slee, J. Noah H.">P. Y. Slee</person>, a white-haired manufacturer who
					has become as popular as his wife in the circle of scientists and liberals who
					surround Mrs. Sanger. Her <person reg="Sanger, Stuart"><person
							reg="Sanger, Grant">two sons</person></person> are in medical
					school.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">She dictates letters to the thousands who write to her from all over the
					world.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Says We're Behind Europe</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">The pathetic letters of poor mothers still bring tears to her eyes.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Look," <q who="SR">she says, tossing over a pitiful plea from a woman in a small
						<place>Texas</place> town.</q> "The family is starving and another baby is
				coming."</p>
			<p>"The doctor in that town probably knows little about birth control," <q who="SR">says
					Mrs. Sanger. </q>"To get information he would have to take a train to the
				nearest large city with a clinic. Isn't it ridiculous?"</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SR">She reads the letter a second time, and a gentle look spreads across her
					face.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"You know, we have gone no further here than the sum total of the information I
				collected in Europe in 1914," <q who="SR">she says.</q> "Now I hear that <place
					reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>'s clinicians are ahead of the rest of the
				world."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
