<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-28 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015--05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 LH edits</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH check entry</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-07-02 EK correct proof and update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-01-29">19 Jan 1921</docDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-01-29">29 Jan 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Is Modern Marriage Conducive to Happiness?</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422078</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Wary of U.S. Agents</title>, <title type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Jan 20, 1921, p. 22</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>As the actual speech was not found, a newspaper summary was used as the copy text. For a similar speech of the same
			name, see <xref from="422079.xml.">"Is Modern Marriage Conducive to Happiness?"</xref> Mar. 29, 1921.</p>
		<index level1="adolescence"/>
		<index level1="marriage"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="age at"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="and procreation"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="reforms"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="sex and sexuality" level2="and marriage"/>
		</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MRS. SANGER WARY OF U.S. AGENTS</head>
		<p><q who="BDE">From 25 to 65 is the marrying age for man, according to Mrs. Margaret
				Sanger, birth control expert, who expressed her opinion on the question "Is Modern
				Marriage Conducive to Happiness?" in the <org>Brownsville Labor Lyceum</org>, 225
				Sackman st., last night.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">Young women who swarmed the hall in a seething mass of humanity besieged
				Mrs. Sanger with questions as to how birth control may be effected. Her answer was
				that several years ago she maintained "open house" in the <place reg="Brookyln, NY"
					>Brownsville</place> section for the express purpose of making birth control a
				tenet in the creed of every housewife and business girl in the community, only to
				find herself in jail as the outcome.</q></p>
		<p>"<q>Though it was wholly worth while,</q>" <q who="BDE"> Mrs. Sanger declared,</q> "<q>I do not
			care to repeat the experiment; and as agents of the <org
				reg="United States Department of Justice">Department of Justice</org> are always out
			to hear me, I shall refrain from telling you these things.</q>"</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">There are five "distinct reasons," the speaker pointed
				out, why</q> "<q>marriage today is almost universally a failure."</q> <q who="BDE">These,
				she said, were</q> "<q>Marrying entirely too young in life, the coming of children too
			quickly, venereal diseases, fear of pregnancy and lack of birth control knowledge, and
			the crudeness of man.</q>" <q who="BDE">That even barbarians are more tender in their
		treatment of women than American men was one of the charges which Mrs. Sanger made.</q></p>
    <p>	
    	<q who="BDE"> Dancing, giddiness, giggling are but the natural inclinations of
				adolescence which run well into the twenty-second year of any girl, the speaker
				explained. To allow her to marry before she has completed that period, she said, was
				for the pent-up nature to rebel at 30, to exercise her natural inclination to dance
				and to play and, consequently, to set gossiping tongues in motion.</q></p>
		<p><q who="BDE">The marriage vow</q> "<q>to love until death do us part</q>" <q who="BDE">was
				scoffed at by Mrs. Sanger.</q> "<q>It is as absolutely impossible for two persons to
			promise to love forever as it would be for them to promise to live forever. Love must be
			nurtured and tended as a flower,</q>" <q who="BDE">she claimed.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">The third cause for marital unhappiness in her list Mrs. Sanger
				characterized as </q> "<q>that haunting dread in the lives of women,</q>" <q who="BDE">and
				declared that </q> "<q>most divorces may be traced down to this constant fear of child
					birth.</q>" <q who="BDE">The most important cause of all, Mrs. Sanger claims, is</q> "<q>man's
			crudeness.</q>"</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">The reasons for marriage, Mrs. Sanger holds, are</q> "<q>for convenience and
			sex attraction. Sex attraction plus mutual understanding is the only sure foundation for
			happiness,</q>" <q who="BDE"> she concluded.</q></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
