<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-28 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 LH edits></prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-10-27">27 Oct 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Jail Interview with the Brooklyn Daily Eagle</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422082</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger, After Night in Jail, Has New Worries</title>,
					<title type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Oct 27, 1916, p. 22</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE"> Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="raid"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests, trials, and imprisonment"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger, After Night in Jail, Has New Worries</head>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE"> Appearing remarkably fresh, despite what she described as a night long
				fight against rats and vermin in the <org>Raymond Street Jail</org>, Mrs. Margaret
				Sanger, the birth-control advocate whose <org reg="Brownsville Clinic">clinic</org>
				at 46 Amboy street was raided yesterday and who was placed under arrest.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE"> Mrs. Sanger has just begun to fight, she says. As soon as the present
				charge against her is disposed of, she intends to return to her clinic and continue
				in her work of spreading birth-control information among women.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE"> Mrs. Sanger was interviewed in a small room just off the tier on which her
				cell is located. She is in cell No. 1.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"I'm glad you came," <q who="BDE"> she said,</q> "but before we begin to discuss my
			arrest I wish to tell you something. Please- for my sake and for the sakes of the other
			women detained here- let me describe the horrible conditions of this jail. I do not see
			how the people of <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"> Kings County</place> can tolerate such
			conditions. The blanket which covers my iron cot is dirty. Creatures of all manners and
			kinds invaded my cell. They came in vast numbers. There is no soap with which to wash my
			hands. I am only mentioning a few of the defects. Put me on record, please, as saying
			the women of Kings County should invade this place and clean it out."</p>
		<p>"Now I can talk of my arrest. How do I regard it? As an invasion of my personal rights.
			It is an outrage and the day will come when this community will realize that Margaret
			Sanger long ago tried to show it the light. I shall continue in my work. After my trial
			and the final disposition of my case I am going back to my clinic." </p>
		<p> "They cannot stop me by placing me under arrest. Some time or other I will have regained
			my liberty. Then Margaret Sanger is going back to violate that law all over again. The
			charge in the newspapers that I was exhibiting and offering for sale a box of pills is a
			vicious lie."</p>
		<p> "I admit we did sell to the <person reg="Whitehurst, Margaret">woman detective</person>.
			We knew who she was. <person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">Mrs. Byrne</person>, my sister,
			is a hot-headed Irish girl and she deliberately urged the detective to buy. We framed
			the two dollar bill and wrote across the bill. 'Received from a spy.' It was laughable
			to see the woman's face when she returned and saw how she had been tricked." </p>
		<p>"That woman detective is beyond me. Perhaps she did only her duty, but personally I would
			rather scrub floors for my bread than earn it by fighting my sisters."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">Mrs. Sanger will talk with her counsel this afternoon and will arrange
				immediately for bail. She intended to remain in jail until the trial, but the
				illness of Miss <person reg="Mindell, Fania">Fania Mindell</person>, her assistant,
				who was arrested with her, has prompted her to abandon that plan and get bail
				immediately. </q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
