<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-15 JC transcribed and encoding</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Toomey, Elizabeth">Elizabeth Toomey</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1955-05-10">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">10 May 1955</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the United Press</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422065</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Says Crusaders Still Needed</title>, <title
					type="journal">San Mateo Times</title>, May 10, 1955, p. 18</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TOOEL">Elizabeth Toomey</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="on jails and prisons"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Says Crusaders Still Needed</head>
		<byline>By ELIZABETH TOOMEY</byline>
		<dateline><place reg="New York, NY">NEW YORK</place> (<org reg="United Press"
			>UP</org>).--</dateline>
		<p><q who="TOOEL">We have plenty of causes worth fighting for today, one of history's most
				famous women crusaders declares, but the crusading spark in modern women is
			</q>"dampened down."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TOOEL">There was no reproof in her tone, but Margaret Sanger admitted during an
				interview here that if she were young again she'd be out fighting for one of several
				social evils that she thinks need correcting.</q>
		</p>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Initiative Missing</head>
			<p>"This isn't the age for it really,"<q who="TOOEL"> Mrs. Sanger said in a gentle
					voice.</q> "A good deal of the initiative that belonged to my generation has
				been dampended down. You talk to young college women now and they say there isn't
				anything to do."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">Mrs. Sanger, the founder of the birth control movement in this
					country and still a world force in spreading her beliefs to other nations, is a
					serene 71 years old.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">Forty-one years ago she fled to <place>England</place> to escape a
					federal indictment.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Militant Feminist</head>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">Her name belongs on a list of militant feminists along with such
					women as <person reg="Anthony, Susan B.">Susan B. Anthony</person>, <person
						reg="Nation, Carrie">Carrie Nation</person> and <person reg="Mott, Lucretia"
						>Lucretia Mott</person>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">In fact, people are inclined to associate her a little too much with
					history to suit Mrs. Sanger. They're often surprised to find she is still
					alive.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Young people think the fight for birth control took place a long time ago," <q
					who="TOOEL">Mrs. Sanger said.</q> "Many times they confuse my name with <person
					reg="Sangster, Margaret">Margaret Sangster</person>, and they assume I'm
				dead."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">(Margaret Sangster was a novelist and poet who died in 1912.)</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Federal Indictment</head>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">Mrs. Sanger was a nurse, the wife of an <person reg="Sanger, William"
						>architect</person> and the mother of <person reg="Sanger, Stuart"><person
							reg="Sanger, Grant"><person reg="Sanger, Peggy">three
							children</person></person></person> when she went to work in earnest to
					make birth control a legal and public issue in 1912. Two years later the <org
						reg="United States Government">federal government</org> indicted her for
					sending birth control information through the mail. she fled to England when
					"the people versus Margaret Sanger" case was cancelled.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">A biography of her life, "<title type="book">The Margaret Sanger
						Story</title>," was just published by Doubleday, and Mrs. Sanger is busy
					planning a trip to Japan next fall to bring that nation into the <org
						reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">International Federation
						of Planned Parenthood</org>. She came here last week from her home in <place
						reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Ariz.</place>, to attend the federation's
					convention.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">Asked what cause she might lead today, if she were young again, Mrs.
					Sanger said,</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Women's Prisons</head>
			<p>"Women's prisons, I think. You could clean up a good deal of wrong there. That is,
				assuming these other things had been achieved, like women's suffrage and birth
				control."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="TOOEL">The tireless crusader did spend a month in a <place
						reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>
					<org reg="Queens County Penitentiary">jail</org> some 30 years ago, and after
					that wrote some bitter letters to public figures about the treatment of the
					women prisoners. But the birth control movement claimed all of her time.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"You must have faith in it,"<q who="TOOEL"> she said, referring to the first
					qualification for any reform movement.</q> "I still have it."</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
