<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 LH edits</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH clean up </prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1938-02-21">21 Feb 1938</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Message to the El Paso Mothers Health Center</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422058</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Message to the El Paso Mothers Health Center</title>, <title
					type="journal"> El Paso Herald-Post</title>, Feb. 21, 1938, pp. 1 and 7 </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="EPH"> El Paso Herald-Post</name>
			<name id="TUCHE">Tucker, Helen</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="and physicians"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="establishment of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control Clinic on Southside Urged </head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> The <org>El Paso Mother's Health Center</org> board of directors,
					affiliate of the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> of <place
						reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, today opened its formal campaign for
					funds for the second fiscal year.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> Part of the fund will be used to open a South Side clinic, <person
						reg="Goetting,
			Mary Betty"> Mrs. Charles A. Goetting</person>, board
					chairman, announced.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH">The Mother's Health Center at 1820 Rio Grande street, organized under
					the direction of Margaret Sanger, internationally known birth control advocate,
					will celebrate the first anniversary April 1 with the annual meeting of the
					board and contributing members. Mrs. Sanger will be here for the meeting. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> The board will have a tea today at the clinic for workers. Membership
					blanks will be distributed and the campaign outlined by <person
						reg="Rawlings, Laura Boynton">Mrs. J. Mott Rawlings</person>. Workers will
					seek funds from El Pasoans for the next two weeks.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> Mmes. <person reg="Hensely, Emma">Emma Hensley</person>, resident
					nurse, and <person reg="Tucker, Helen">Calvert C. Tucker</person>, member of the
					educational committee, will give brief talks on the progress of the work.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> Mmes. <person reg="Harvey, Maude P.">Charles M. Harvey</person> and
						<person reg="Schwartz, Hedwig M.">Maurice Schwartz</person> will pour
					tea.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> Mrs. Goetting will read the following message to the directors from
					Mrs. Sanger, ill in <place reg="Tuscon, AZ"> Tucson</place>, who planned to
					attend the meeting today:</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Please accept my deep regret on my inability to be with you and help raise money for
				your campaign. Only doctors' strict orders prevent same. Your report of achievement
				put many older clinics to shame. Naturally, I am proud of you all because I
				witnessed your initiation in first battle for motherhood for mothers of El Paso.
				Your undaunted courage and vision inspires me. I wish more women in this country had
				your spirit. Can you not get a far-sighted philanthropist in you vicinity to buy a
				house as a permanent headquarters for your organization to which mothers of El Paso
				may look as a temple of Hope? Congratulations and best wished for your continued
				success." </p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Asks Further Aid</head>
			<p>
				<q who="EPA"> Mrs. Goetting today for the board thanked the doctors who have donated
					their time, business concerns, for their contributions and "others who have
					helped the charity to prevent charity."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> She asked for continued co-operation "in a project which will lessen
					the relief burden in El Paso and aid married women desiring contraceptive advice
					who are financially unable to pay a doctor."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> Total number of patients in the clinic since April are 604, new
					patients advised, 308, and revisits, 365, the board reported. New patients are
					not advised on account of sickness, pregnancy, or reference to a private
					physician, 31.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> Mrs. Tucker in her talk today emphasized the birth control movement is
					not an effort to limit the number of children to a one-child or two-child family
					system.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="sub">
			<head> Directors</head>
			<p>
				<q who="TUCHE">"It means making it possible for a woman to have the number of
					children consistent with and in consideration of four things,"</q>
				<q who="EPH"> said Mrs. Tucker.</q>
				<q who="TUCHE">"Those things are: the mother's health, the child's possible
					heritage, physical and mental, the father's earning capacity and the standards
					of living desirable to maintain." </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPH"> Directors include: <person reg="McAlmon, Katherine">Mrs. George C.
						McAlmon</person>, first vice chairman; <person reg="Ratburn, Beatrice P.">
						Mrs. Donald Ratburn</person>, second vice chairman; <person
						reg="Perrenot, Jane R.">Mrs. Preston Perrenot</person>, secretary; <person
						reg="Howell, Romaine">Mrs. Ben R. Howell</person>, corresponding secretary;
						<person reg="Matkin, George">George Matkin</person>, treasurer; <person
						reg="Safford, Helen">Mmes. Henry T. Safford</person>, <person
						reg="Alexander, Vance">Frank O. Alexander</person>, <person
						reg="Dutton, Edna">L. O. Dutton</person>, <person reg="Matkin, Rebecca"
						>George Matkin</person>, <person reg="Norwald, Mrs. Otto">Mrs. Otto
						Norwald</person>; advisory board, <person reg="Blair, Mrs. W. R."> W. R.
						Blair</person>, <person reg="Burges, Ethel S.">Richard Burges</person>,
						<person reg="Evans, Macie B.">Joe Evans</person>, <person
						reg="Hardie, Mary T.">Mrs. Bradford Hardie</person>, <person
						reg="Norton, Clara M.">Fred W. Norton</person>, <person
						reg="Scott, Lillian">Louis A. Scott</person>, <person
						reg="Staten, Lillie M.">Mrs. Buleson Staten</person>; medical advisory
					board, Drs. <person reg="Black, Arthur P.">Arthur P. Black</person>, <person
						reg="Green, J. Leighton">J. Leighton Green</person>, <person
						reg="Jordan, Gerald H."> Gerald H. Jordan</person>, <person
						reg="McCamant, T.J."> T.J. McCamant</person>, <person
						reg="Rawlings, J. Mott"> J. Mott Rawlings</person> and <person
						reg="Rogers, Will P.">Will P. Rogers</person>. </q>
			</p>

		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
