<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-11-13 MC transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-30 MC enter corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-07-02 EK correct proof and update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-11-13">13 Nov 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Brooklyn Daily Eagle</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422083</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">'Wide Open Again' Says Mrs. Sanger; Defies the
					Police</title>, <title type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Nov. 13,
				1916, p. 3</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
			<name id="BOYED">Boylan, Edward</name>
			<name id="GOLJO">Goldstein, Jonah J.</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="need for"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="New York" level2="birth control laws"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="state"
			level3="NYS Criminal Code, Section 1142"/>
		<index level1="law breaking and direct action"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="on jails and prisons"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="New York" level2="birth control laws"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="New York" level2="birth control laws"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>"WIDE OPEN AGAIN" SAYS MRS. SANGER; DEFIES THE POLICE</head>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, the birth-control champion, who was arrested for a
				violation of the <name type="law" reg="New York State Penal Code, Section 1142">
					Penal law</name> in that she imparted birth-control knowledge to women, and
				whose case has not yet been disposed of, bade defiance to the police and Section
				1142 of the Penal law today by reopening her <org reg="Brownsville Clinic"
					>clinic</org> at 46 Amboy Street. Mrs. Sanger is out on bail and now awaits
				trial in the <org reg="Kings County Court of Special Sessions">Court of Special
					Sessions</org>. Her defense is that any law forbidding the imparting of 0
				information on the subject of birth control is unconstitutional. So far, the <org
					reg="King's County District Attorney">District Attorney's office</org> has not
				specified whether she is under arrest on a charge of violating Section 1142 of the
				Penal law or not. The failure to do so before <person reg="Steers, Alfred"
					>Magistrate Steers</person> in the <org reg="Tenth District Court, King County"
					>New Jersey avenue court</org>, and later in the <org
					reg="Kings County Court of Special Sessions">Adams street court</org>, resulted
				in several bitter arguments between <person reg="Kellogg, Herbert"> Assistant
					District Attorney Kellogg</person> and <person reg="Goldstein, Jonah J.">Jonah
					J. Goldstein</person>, her counsel. As yet the section violated has not been
				specified and she is held simply on information.</q>
		</p>

		<p>
			<q who="BDE">She received twelve visitors today between the hours of 11 and 12. She
				opened her clinic at 10 o'clock, but it required an hour, she said, for the
				information to spread through <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brownsville</place>.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"<q>I am back again,</q>" <q who="BDE">she said to an <emph rend="italic">Eagle</emph>
				man and she smiled as she said it.</q> "<q>They may arrest me any moment, but what
				is the use. I shall return to this place and openly carry out the purpose of my
				clinic. That law is unconstitutional. The poor women of Brownsville need me. The
				poor women of <place reg="New York, NY">Greater New York</place> and the
					<place>United States</place> need me. I am only Margaret Sanger, but someone is
				destined to find out that Margaret Sanger will not be frightened off. They will also
				learn that a woman fighting for what she believes and knows is right does not know
				the meaning of fear or defeat.</q>"</p>
		<p>"The <org>Raymond Street Jail</org>, with its varied assortment of weird and awesome
			vermin, I'll admit, is enough to frighten anyone, but my mission and my work can even
			bid defiance to seven Raymond street jails."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">"What are you doing here this morning?" was asked.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"<q>Doing? What would you suppose I am doing. I am giving the women who come to my place
				the information they desire--the information they need.</q>"</p>
		<p>"<q>You may say for me that I intend to stay here as long as the police will let me. If
				they take me out, it will be under arrest and against my protest. When I regain my
				liberty, I will come right back. That is Margaret Sanger's message to the thousands
				of women who need her.</q>"</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">Although she is back in her clinic, and admits she has again violated the
				law, conditions are somewhat changed. The <org reg="New York City Police Department"
					>police</org> have confiscated the various things she had in the clinic before
				her arrest. Conditions also differ in that, today, the front door, previously
				unlatched and smooth-moving on its well-oiled hinges, is locked. To enter the women
				go in through the hall at the side and gain entrance to the clinic through a side
				door. Asked if this was a precaution against a sudden raid, Mrs. Sanger, said Miss
					<person reg="Mindell, Fania">Fannie Mindell</person>, her assistant, had gone to
				the printers to order some hand bills and signs inviting the women of the section to
				come to the clinic, and there register their protest against Section 1142, and that
				she had carelessly locked the door--from outside.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">When it was called to her attention that Miss Mindell did not look as
				though she needed a guardian to keep her from doing needless things and was not at
				all absent-minded, she laughed and declared she had given her reason for having the
				side door locked.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">Officially, the <org reg="New York City Police Department">Eleventh Inspection District</org> and <person
					reg="McElroy, William">Inspector McElroy </person> did not know the clinic was
				again in operation. A man who said he was <person reg="Kelly, Thomas">Lieutenant
					Kelly</person> declared he had no record of the clinic being open and that
				Inspector McElroy was out on a tour of the district.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">However, <person reg="Boylan, Edward">Detective Boylan</person>, who
				figured in the arrest with <person reg="Barry, Edward">Sergeant Barry</person> and
				Mrs. <person reg="Whitehurst, Margaret">Margaret Whithurst</person>, knew all about
				it. Boylan called at the clinic shortly before 12 o'clock. He did not appear at
				ease, Mrs. Sanger said.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BOYED">"Are you at it again, Mrs. Sanger?"</q>
			<q who="BDE">he asked.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"<q>What does this look like?</q>" <q who="BDE">was her questioning reply.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BOYED">"What are you doing here?"</q>
			<q who="BDE">was his next question.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"<q>What do you think?</q>" <q who="BDE">responded Mrs. Sanger.</q> "<q>I am here--wide
				open and intend to remain here as long as I can.</q>"</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BOYED">"Oh!"</q>
			<q who="BDE">gasped Boylan as he backed out of the place.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">The district attorney's office would make no comment today beyond saying
				that the matter was entirely up to the police. <person reg="Goldstein, Jonah J."
					>Jonah J. Goldstein</person>, counsel for Mrs. Sanger, did not know she had
				resumed operations until informed by The Eagle man.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="GOLJO">"Well I'll be ---. You have to admire that woman's pluck. She did not
				consult me,"</q>
			<q who="BDE">he said.</q>
			<q who="GOLJO">"I presume she believes the law is unconstitutional and intends to go
				right on with her work. My job is to show the unconstitutionality of the law and
				that I will do if I possibly can. Mrs. Sanger is a woman of great determination. She
				believes in herself. Say, don't you admire her grit? Open again. Well, I'll be ---.
				Open again."</q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
