<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-20 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1937-01-31">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">31 Jan 1927</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Planned Parenthood</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422052</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article"> Birth Control Advocate Cites Appalling Increase in Unfits;
					Urges Scientific Plan Adoption</title>, <title type="journal">Fitchburg Sentinel</title>, Feb. 1, 1937, p. 1</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="FS">Fitchburg Sentinel</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's speech was not found; newspaper coverage has been used in its place.</p>
		<index level1="physically diseased or disabled" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="educational benefits"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control Advocate Cites Appalling Increase in Unfits; Urges Scientific Plan
			Adoption.</head>
		<p>"The adoption of a scientific plan for birth control is civilization's only hope of
			surviving the appalling results of civilization's interference with nature's plan for
			the elimination of the unfit," <q who="FS">declared Margaret Sanger, foremost advocate
				of birth control, before a record breaking audience at the Community forum in the
					<org reg="First Universalist Church of Fitchburg">First Universalist
					church</org> Sunday afternoon.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="FS">Long before the time scheduled for Sanger's talk, every seat in the
				auditorium was taken. All available chairs and extra seats were pressed into use and
				standing room was at a premium when the famous advocate of planned parenthood was
				presented to the audience by Rev. <person reg="Kapp, Max A.">Max. A. Kapp</person>.
				Selection by a piano, violin and cello trio and songs by the <org
					reg="Leominster Aeolian Male Quartet">Aeolian male quartet</org> of <place
					reg="Leominster, MA">Leominster</place> preceded the lecture and were well
				received.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="FS">In her opening remarks Mrs. Sanger warmly congratulated the people of <place
					reg="Fitchburg, MA">Fitchburg</place> for maintaining and supporting the public
				forum.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"There never has been a time in our history when it has been to necessary for our people
			to gather and discuss problems which confront our civilization. No place offers a better
			opportunity for such discussion than the public forum," <q who="FS">she said.</q></p>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Social and Moral Awakening</head>
			<p> </p>

			<p>
				<q who="FS">Referring to the title of her address, "Planned Parenthood," Mrs. Sanger
					contended that no subject of equal importance had been left so long in obscurity
					and none had gained such wide discussion in the past 10 years.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Birth control--conscious control of the birth rate by means that prevent
				conception of life--is the keynote of a new social and moral awakening," <q
					who="FS">Mrs. Sanger averred.</q> "A birth rate consciously controlled is all
				that separates us from the animals," <q who="FS">she added.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="FS">Mrs. Sanger contended that</q> "there always was a control of the birth
				rate until civilization upset the balance. Disease, pestilence, floods, disasters
				and wars did the work in the past ages. In the past, nature was the controlling
				force that brought us down to our present civilization through the test of the
				survival of the fittest. </p>
			<p>"The charity and philanthropy of our civilization have saved and nurtured the unfit
				that nature would have eliminated. We have made it possible for these to live and
				propagate and we now find that they are increasing much faster than the fit and
				intelligent types.</p>
			<p>"At the present time one-third of the fit are employed in taking care of these
				incompetents who contribute nothing to society. The billions spent in caring for
				these millions of incompetents is placing an appalling burden on the shoulders of
				tax payers. </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub"> Unfit Propagating More Unfit</head>
			<p> "If the senseless saving of the unfit for the propagation of increasingly more unfit
				and unemployable is to continue then we had better at once change the places with
				those in the institutions for the insane and feeble-minded and let them out to run
				the country. </p>
			<p>"We have made no intelligent effort to control this appalling increase in the unfit
				and unemployables and to lessen the burden upon the fit chiefly because of fear of
				theology and of dogmas of the middle ages trying to regulate our lives today," <q
					who="FS">she said.</q></p>
			<p><q who="FS">The speaker declared that <place reg="United States">America</place> has
					the highest maternal death rate of any country and is the only one having laws
					barring contraceptive appliances.</q> "We cannot hope to lower this death rate
				until it is possible for the mother to get the best possible advice on contraceptive
				methods and clinics under the direction of the public health departments, the place
				where it should be available," <q who="FS">she said. </q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Seven Birth Control Reasons</head>
			<p>
				<q who="FS">The speaker gave seven cardinal reasons for birth control and listed
					them as follows: Transmissible diseases, diseases not transmissible but
					incapacitating the mother; sub-normal children, due to a strain in one parent or
					the other; spacing of children to permit the mother to maintain her health;
					adolescent parents and lastly the desirability that parents should be given at
					least two years in which to become spiritually acquainted before assuming the
					problems and duties of parenthood. She declared there can be no spiritual union
					between husband and wife until the fear of pregnancy is abolished.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="FS">There are only three possible controls of population, Mrs. Sanger
					contended. The death rate may be increased or the birth rate may be controlled.
					The third is the emigration of a part of the population. With the latter
					eliminated there remains only the choice of an increased death rate or a
					controlled birth rate.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="FS">The speaker declared that statistics showed that the birth rate among
					people on relief is 65 per cent higher than the rate among those employed.</q>
				"These people do not want to have any more children than they can support but they
				do not know how to avoid it," <q who="FS">she maintained.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="FS">Referring again to the tremendous increase in the number of insane,
					feeble minded and unemployables Mrs. Sanger declared that sterilization has got
					to come if we are to hold our own against the insane and incompetents.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
