<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-28 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 LH entered corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1933-02-16">16 Feb 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Letter to the Brooklyn Daily Eagle</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422087</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Comments On Our 'Overabundance'</title>,
					<title type="journal">The Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Feb. 16, 1922, p.
				16</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE">The Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
			<name id="BLEWI">Blehl, William A.</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Congressional Bills"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Comments On Our 'Overabundance'</head>
		<p>"Editor Brooklyn Daily Eagle:"</p>
		<p>"In your issue of <date value="1933-02-13">Feb. 13</date> a letter from Mr. <person
				reg="Blehl,
			William A.">William A. Blehl</person> needs correction.</p>
		<p>"The birth control bill S.4436 aims to allow physicians, hospitals and clinics only to
			use the <place reg="United States">U.S.</place> mails and common carriers to send and
			receive such contraceptive articles, books and supplies as are needed."</p>
		<p>"It is an error to say the bill aims to reduce the population to overcome the present
			economic condition. The fact of the matter is that the passage of this bill would
			decrease tremendous misery, worry and anxiety in the lives of the poor mothers who go to
			hospitals and clinics for their medical advice, because they can seldom afford to
			consult a private doctor." </p>
		<p>"Mr. Blehls's childish announcement,<q who="BLEWI">there is an overabundance of food
				supplies and a further depletion of and a further depletion in population would only
				result in a still more overabundance</q> does not ring true. If there is an
			overabundance of food what good does it do the millions of hungry men and women walking
			the streets looking for jobs to buy it?"</p>
		<p>"Large populations have not thus far in the history of mankind done more for civilization
			then plunge humanity into wars, hunger, disease, plunder, and crime. To talk nonsense at
			this time, with the economic facts of history before us is not only an expression of
			ignorance-- it is malicious! Let those who want a big population make it possible for
			every child born and alive today to have a chance to live before they pratter about
			'overabundance' and increase.'" </p>
		<signed>MARGARET SANGER Nat. Chairman, <org
				reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for
			Birth Control"
				>N.C.F.L.B.C.</org></signed>
		<dateline><place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>,<date value="1933-02-20">Feb.
			16</date></dateline>
	</docBody>
</doc>
