<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 CH proofread tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-07-14 EK correct proof and update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-01-24">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">24 Jan 1922</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Plans for Japan and China</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422075</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">"Protection Planned at Birth Control Talk"</title>, <title
					type="journal">New York Times</title>, Jan. 25, 1922, p. 36</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
			<name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922 (China)"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="China" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>PROTECTION PLANNED AT BIRTH CONTROL TALK</head>
		<p>
			<q who="NYT">When Mrs. Margaret Sanger speaks on birth control in the <org>Lexington
					Avenue Opera House</org> on Feb. 5 she will be surrounded by a committee of men
				and women who expect to see that she gets a hearing, that there is no unlawful
				interference and who will be ready to qualify as witnesses in case of trouble. The
				meeting will be a farewell demonstration for Mrs. Sanger, who announced yesterday
				that she soon would sail on a three monthS lecture tour of <place>China</place> and
					<place>Japan</place>. Arrangements were made yesterday at a meeting of those
				interested in the subject at the home of Mrs. <person reg="Rublee, Juliet Barrett"
					>Juliet B. Rublee</person>, 242 East Forty-ninth Street.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"My plans," <q who="NYT">said Mrs. Sanger,</q> "have been made for a three months' tour
			of Japan. I am requested to lecture in several universities throughout both Japan and
			China. There have been during the last year and a half more than twenty-five
			representatives of the Japanese government who have made world tours, seeking solutions
			for Japan's immediate problems. I am informed that twenty-one of the twenty-five
			investigators have returned to Japan with the message that the birth control movement in
				<place reg="United States">America</place> has a most important message in the world
			today and one which Japan should listen to with open mind. </p>
		<p>"I am, therefore, invited to come there under the auspices of a <org reg="Kaizo"
				>group</org> of patriotic citizens. I am informed that there is a great deal of
			interest and preparation being made for my coming. The <person
				reg="Ishimoto, Shidzue Kato">Baroness Ishimoto</person> is anxious that I shall give
			her instruction on how to open birth control clinics for the poor women of Japan.</p>
		<p>"I am also requested to go to China, and arrangements are being made by some of the
			officials who represented China at the <org reg="Washington Naval Conference"
				>disarmament conference.</org>"</p>
		<p><q who="NYT">The announcement by Commissioner of Accounts <person reg="Hirshfield, David"
					>David Hirshfield</person> that he would investigate birth control along with
				alleged police interference has pleased advocates of the plan, for they believe that
				the Commissioner will accomplish what they are trying to do--get the subject before
				the people</q>.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
