<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-15 JC transcribed and encodingk</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Miller, Joy">Joy Miller</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1961-05-13">13 May 1961</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the Associated Press</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422066</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger, Nearing 80, Is Still Birth Control
					Crusader</title>, <title type="journal">Corsica Daily Sun</title>, May 13, 1961,
				p. 5</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="MILJO">Miller, Joy</name>
			<name id="HIGMI">Higgins, Michael</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biographical details"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="descriptions of"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger, Nearing 80, Is Still Birth Control Crusader</head>
		<byline>By JOY MILLER</byline>
		<dateline><place reg="New York, NY">NEW YORK</place>, <date value="1961-05-13">May 13</date>
				(<org reg="Associated Press">AP</org>)--</dateline>
		<p>
			<q who="MILJO">She sits quietly with folded hands, looking like a modern <person
					reg="Whistler, James McNeill">whistler</person>'s <person
					reg="Whistler, Anna McNeill">mother</person>.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="MILJO">Her floor-length silk muumuu is red, but somehow it goes with her Irish
				red hair that needs only slight tinting as she nears 80. She's gently placid, almost
				frail.</q>
		</p>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="MILJO">But just ask Margaret Sanger if she has mellowed. The blue eyes flash
					with the old fire that kept her embattled birth control movement going in its
					early years.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Of course I haven't mellowed," <q who="MILJO">she snaps.</q> "Back when I was
				actively crusading I felt everyone simply had to believe what I said. I still do. I
				don't see how any thinking person could feel differently about birth control."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Finds Times Changed</head>
			<p>
				<q who="MILJO">Then, humor getting the upper hand, she recalls:</q>
			</p>
			<p>"When I started out, I had to be very careful what words I used. The whole subject
				was taboo. Even my <person reg="Higgins, Michael">father</person>--and outspoken
				Irishman who brought me up to do my own thinking--said to me one day: <q who="HIGMI"
					>Margaret, can't you find some other subject in the world to talk about but the
					bedroom?"</q> And he whispered when he said 'bedroom'."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILJO">But times have changed. The dignified little woman who was jailed at
					least nine times and had her first clinic raided by police as a public nuisance
					is in <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> this week receiving an
					international tribute from science and government leaders gathered for a <org
						reg="World Population Emergency Campaign">conference</org> on the "world
					population crisis."</q>
			</p>
			<p>"I take the scientists' word,"<q who="MILJO"> she says, </q>"when they say there's
				not going to be enough to take care of all the people. And birth control, if
				practiced on a wide scale, is the only solution. I'm not advocating any one method,
				but all methods."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILJO">In the past few years Mrs. Sanger has been living quietly in <place
						reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson, Ariz.</place>, but the election of <person
						reg="Kennedy, John F.">John F. Kennedy</person> brought her into the news
					again. She was moving to <place>England</place>, she declared, unless the
					President showed whether he was not dominated by the <org>Roman Catholic
						Church</org>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MILJO">Now she says: </q>"I've been told that he and his <person
					reg="Kennedy, Jacqueline Bouvier">wife</person> are sympathetic, that they
				understood the cause. He may not do anything about it; I don't expect him to promise
				anything. But if the <org reg="United States Government">government</org> would come
				out and say it was standing behind the movement, it would be a great help to the
				little overpopulated countries of <place>Asia</place> that still admire us. It would
				have helped if <person reg="Eisenhower, Dwight D.">President Eisenhower</person> had
				done it."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Started As Nurse</head>
			<p><q who="MILJO">Mrs. Sanger, one of 11 children in a poor family, later worked as a
					public health nurse in New York slums. It was then, unable to bear the sight of
					overworked mothers and their sad little children who kept coming one after
					another, she set out to </q> "free the motherhood of the world."</p>
			<p>"The most hopeful thing our work has done," <q who="MILJO">she says, </q>"is that
				years ago women came in to our clinics and said I'm in trouble."</p>
			<p>Now they come in and say I'm going to have a baby. Isn't it wonderful?"</p>
			<p><q who="MILJO">She has two sons and eight grandchildren, and reflects: </q>"I've had
				a rich life and found people very understanding."</p>
			<p><q who="MILJO">Although she's made many speeches--</q>"for years there it was three a
					day"<q who="MILJO">--she has never got over her fear of speaking in
				public.</q></p>
			<p>"I like to talk to men, though, because they're thinkers. And they're up against the
				problem of supporting their children. But when they come up to me and say they just
				can't help having so many children because they just love children, I look them up
				and down and say: "What do you earn?"</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
