<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-07-03 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-02 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-18 EK correct proof and update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1914-04-11">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">11 Apr 1914</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on <emph rend="italics">Woman Rebel</emph>
					Case</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422005</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">New York Evening Journal</title>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">April 11, 1914</supplied>, p. 1</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NYEJ">New York Evening Journal</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p/>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Postal Codes"/>
		<index level1="women and girls" level2="enslavement of"/>
		<index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
		<index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>FREE-THINKING EDITOR DEFIES GOVERNMENT TO SUPPRESS HER PAPER</head>
		<p>"I intend to continue making public my ideas through my paper if I have to go to jail for
			it."</p>
		<p>This was the defiant statement made today by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, of no. 34 Post avenue,
			editor and publisher of <title type="journal">"The Woman Rebel,"</title> a monthly
			newspaper which the Federal authorities have just decided, is unmailable. Deputy
			Attorney-General <person reg="Lamar, William H.">Lamar</person> has communicated the
				<place reg="Washington, DC">Washington</place> decision to the <org
				reg="New York Post Office">New York post office</org>.</p>
		<p>"No Gods; no masters," <q who="NYEJ">is the motto of "<title type="journal">The Woman
					Rebel</title>," which, Mrs. Sanger says, is published for</q> "an advanced,
			thinking frankly speaking feminine clientele"</p>
		<p>"Inform the working people and you will place a great weapon in their hands," <q
				who="NYEJ">she declared today to an <title type="journal">Evening Journal
					reporter.</title></q> "It is a woman's duty to have an ideal and to speak and
			act in defiance of conventions."</p>
		<p>Over on the other side, I noticed the difference in the manner in which children are
			raised. In <place>Scotland</place> you see a woman with a flock of children at her heels
			crying for bread. In almost all of the cities, children are treated as dogs and not as
			individuals. In almost all of the cities, except those of <place>France</place>,
			children are treated as dogs and not as individuals. In France, where it is lawful to
			give out information on this character, everyone seems glad to have children, but not
			too many of them. Every encouragement is given to childbirth.</p>
		<p>"Over here we seem to have no consideration for children. We breed them wholesale,
			especially in the poorer sections of the city where children amount to no more than dogs
			in the street."</p>
		<p>"I believe that woman has been enslaved by the machinery of the world, by sex
			conventions, by motherhood, by wage slavery, by middle-class morality, by superstition
			and by custom. Too many children in a poor family mean starvation and children that are
			of no account."</p>
		<p><q who="NYEJ">Mrs. Sanger belongs to the <org reg="Industrial Workers of the World">I.W.W.</org> <person reg="Goldman, Emma">Emma Goldman</person> is one of the contributors to her paper.</q></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
