<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 LH enter corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-13 CH reg doc titles</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-17 CH enter proofread corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-02-18">18 Feb 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Japanese Population Increase</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422074</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Birth Control or War, Claim</title>, <title type="journal"
					>Oshkosh (Wisc.) Daily Northwestern</title>, Feb. 18, 1922, p. 2</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
			<name id="ODN">Oshkosh Daily Northwestern</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>No complete version of the statement was found; newspaper coverage was used instead.</p>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="politics in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>BIRTH CONTROL OR WAR, CLAIM</head>
		<byline>(By Robert A. Donaldson, United Press Staff Correspondent.)</byline>
		<dateline><place reg="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</place>--</dateline>
		<p>"If <place>Japan</place> continues its present increase in population and does not resort
			to birth control, there will be but one result--war."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ODN">This was the declaration today of Mrs. Margaret Sanger, president of the
					<org reg="American Birth Control League">American birth control league</org>,
				who has been refused a passport visa by the <org reg="Japan Consulate">Japanese
					consulate</org> here on orders from <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"If in barring me from entering Japan the <org reg="Japan Government">Japanese
				government</org> is signifying its refusal to consider the birth control idea, Japan
			leaves herself open to the suspicion that she is preparing for war,"<q who="ODN"> she
				added</q>.</p>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">"Invited" She Says.</head>
			<p>"I was invited by several members of the Japanese government and by the <org
					reg="Kaizo">Kaizo group</org> to come to Japan and deliver five lectures on the
				birth control movement.</p>
			<p>"Then, with the aid of Baroness <person reg="Kato, Shidzue Ishimoto"
					>Ishimoto</person>, who is in sympathy with my aims, I had planned to establish
				a series of birth control clinics throughout Japan."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ODN">Mrs. Sanger will continue her trip to <place reg="Asia">the
						orient</place>. She hopes to be able to enter Japan merely as a traveller.
					Failing that, she will continue her trip to <place>China</place> and
						<place>India</place>, where she has lecture engagements.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"The militaristic group in Japan," <q who="ODN">she said</q>, "is strongly opposed to
				me and my principles."</p>
			<p>A quota of 100,000,000 as the population for Japan has been set by this group. There
				are 57,000,000 now. They say that with a population of 100,000,000 they 'will have the
				right to speak in world affairs.'"</p>
			<p>"The 'right to speak' as voiced by the militarists can be interpreted but in one way.
				The power to speak in a way that with their immense population, will brook no
				argument."</p>
			<p>"If Japan refuses to take birth control, if she will not accept it as her national
				policy, I think her plans and intentions are obvious."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
