<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/05/28 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-12 EK correct proof and index</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-03 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-10 CH reg doc title</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-10 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Martyn, Marguerite">Marguerite Martyn</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-05-20">20 May 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">St. Louis Post-Dispatch Interview (Excerpts)</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422019</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Marguerite Martyn, <title type="article">"Mrs. Sanger, Who Defies Federal Law,
					Outlines Her Work for Birth Control Among the Poor"</title>, <title
					type="journal">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</title>, May 21, 1916.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SLPD">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>On her arrival in <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place>, Sanger gave several
			similar interviews to local reporters. The editors have omitted background details
			written by Marguerite Martyn.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="need for"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="nurses and nursing" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="as a nurse"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="biographical details"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="descriptions of"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="speaking tours" level3="1916 (U.S.)"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger, Who Defies Federal Law, Outlines Her Work for Birth Control Among the
			Poor</head>
		<byline>By Marguerite Martyn</byline>
		<dateline>
			<date value="1916-05-20">May 20, 1916</date>, <place reg="Washington, DC"
				>Washington</place></dateline>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="SLPD">Coming to <place reg="St. Louis, MO">St. Louis</place> to give three
					lectures--Monday night at <org>Victoria Theater</org>. Tuesday noon at the "<org
						reg="St. Louis City Club">City Club</org>. Tuesday evening, the <org
						reg="St. Louis Town Club">Town Club</org>. Mrs. Sanger is managed by a
					committee whose personnel is a mystery. They dare not stand beside her openly.
					But possibly that may be before she departs.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">May Be Hailed as Pioneer.</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SLPD">In years to come it may be history will have it that here was a woman
					especially endowed and especially called to the delivery of a message.
					Undoubtedly her personality has gone far to lend conviction of her sincerity</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLPD">Yet when I met her in her room at the <org reg="Jefferson Hotel"
						>Jefferson</org> she did not seem exceptional in any particular.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SLPD">She has small, delicately modeled, but not especially regular
					features; a high, smooth brow, under a wealth of silky blue-black hair. Her hair
					and long dark lashes are most attractive. She has a calm, assured, unhurried
					manner. Her speech betrays the idiosyncrasy of dropping the final gs. As the
					publisher of her magazine, called the <title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>,
					you'd never identify her.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Be sure to say that I am married and have three children," <q who="SLPD">was her
					first remark.</q> "My <person reg="Sanger, William">husband</person> is an
				artist. When we were first married he still was having quite a struggle to get
				along. So I continued at my profession and we waited five years before we decided to
				have a baby."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Arms Yearned for Baby.</head>
			<p>"My <person reg="Sanger, Henrietta Wolffberg">husband's mother</person> came to live
				with us then, so I could go on working. We waited another five years before we asked
				for and received another baby. By this time we had become so safely established that
				as soon as my arms began to yearn to be filled again, inside of <unclear resp="MSPP"
					>20</unclear> months, our last baby was born."</p>
			<p>"I have no message for the rich woman or the middle class woman," <q who="SLPD">said
					Mrs. Sanger.</q> "They already find information on this subject easily available
				through their doctors. It is the poor woman, the one whose income is still too
				limited to provide properly for a child, and the woman already overburdened with
				children, whom I seek to relieve and to whom I feel responsible."</p>
			<p> "<q who="SLPD">How do you limit the channels into which your information shall go?"
					I asked of her.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"With the organization of responsible committees, who can investigate each individual
				case," <q who="SLPD">she responded.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"Personally, I think everybody is entitled to all the knowledge that is available, as
				it is abroad."</p>
			<p>"It is therefore necessary that these committees be comprised of reputable physicians
				or nurses. I prefer nurses as disseminators of the information myself, because they
				have the opportunity for more individual observation. But medical men object."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Wants Doctors' Support.</head>
			<p>"And my great aim, of course, is eventually to get the endorsement of the <org
					reg="American Medical Association">National Medical Association</org>.</p>
			<p>"It was in my work as a trained nurse I so often was confronted with this problem
				that I decided finally to rebel."</p>
			<p>"Much of my work was in the slums. It seems to me the responsibility is ours, not the
				ignorant mothers' nor the brutal fathers'," <q who="SLPD">she said.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"It is becoming more and more customary for women of the working class to continue at
				their wage earning after marriage. And surely this is an improvement upon the day
				when women were obliged to marry in order to be supported. Why shouldn't the young
				wife as well as the young husband help in the first establishment of a home? The
				birds prepare their nests together."</p>
			<p>"And you observe, too, they do not think of having a family without a nest to rear it
				in."</p>
			<p>"I have been watching with great satisfaction the outcome of my theories among many
				happy young pairs in the factory towns where I have talked or sent my
				pamphlets."</p>
			<p> "<q who="SLPD">Isn't there always the danger that the wife may become reconciled to
					her childlessness and the husband reconciled to her contributing to the income,
					and the possibility of a family becomes more and more remote?" I suggested.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"No," <q who="SLPD">she responded, her eyes suffused with tenderness, even a little
					blinded, I thought, by sentiment.</q></p>
			<p>"On the contrary, every normal married couple want children. A child planned for and
				prepared for and waited for until a full sense of responsibility is arrived at, is
				certainly appreciated."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
