<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 MC correct tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-01-10">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">10 Jan 1922</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Over-Population</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422081</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger on Birth Control</title>, <title type="journal"
					>Reading Times</title>, Jan. 11, 1922, p 2</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
			<name id="RT">Reading Times</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger also gave this speech at an afternoon meeting on Jan. 10th at the residence of
			Mrs. A.D. Nelson. The evening speech was sponsored by the Labor Lyceum.</p>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="need for"/>
		<index level1="child labor"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger on Birth Control</head>
		<p>
			<q who="RT">Mrs. Margaret Sanger made two addresses in <place reg="Reading, PA"
					>Reading</place> yesterday on "birth control." The first was of a semi-private
				nature. The second was open to all. </q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="RT">A goodly company of women gathered in the afternoon at the residence of
					<person reg="Nelson, Mary B.">Mrs. A. D. Nelson</person>, 1025 Fairview avenue,
				Wyomossing, to hear Mrs. Margaret Sanger.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"This is what we call an organization meeting," <q who="BT">she said in opening. It seems
				to me from the interest that has been shown here in Reading at the three previous
				meetings that there is a great deal of interest in the subject of birth
			control.</q></p>
		<p>"We come here, and we have large overflowing meetings, and then we go away and there is
			nothing left and nothing done. It is not just right to arouse interest in a great cause
			like this without following it up with some further steps, practical knowledge and
			setting minds straight toward the right goal of idealism.</p>
		<p>"The whole subject of this movement is to direct the forces of motherhood in the right
			direction. We not only want to control birth and to decrease the quantity among the
			unfit and the diseased and the poor, but we also want to improve the quality of the
			human race. Let us never forget that we have a two-fold object in this work. </p>
		<p>"It is going to be the object of the <org>American Birth Control League</org> to
			formulate and establish birth control clinics throughout this country. We want to go
			into the south where in those states the white people are numerous and in many ways more
			badly treated than the colored people.</p>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Oppose Child Labor</head>
			<p>"We want to go into these states in which child labor still exists, and we want to
				make child labor an unnecessary thing in these states within a very few years. We
				are going to do that, not by passing laws against child labor, which are prolific.
				We are going to give those mothers instruction in means of preventing conception, so
				that the mother will not have more children than she can take care of. We want to go
				into the industrial sections of every state in this nation and organize the interest
				that is already there. </p>
			<p>"Now we do not want to do it from outside. We want the aid of those members of the
				community who are in sympathy with us, who believe in birth control, and who believe
				that the application of this information when directed properly will be a good thing
				for that community."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="RT">Mrs. Sanger claims that her plan will reduce the infant mortality rate,
					as the mother will have only the number of children she can take care of, first
					accordance with the mother's health, second in accordance with the father's
					income. She also says it will encourage young people to marry earlier, to work
					together, to consider the responsibilities of parenthood before they bring a
					child into the world. It will automatically reduce prostitution and venereal
					diseases, as it has done in <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place> and
						<place>New Zealand</place> and in countries where there has been organized
					effort to give instruction in birth control.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Branch Organized</head>
			<p>
				<q who="RT">Prominent local people showed their interest in the subject of birth
					control by forming a branch of the American Birth Control League at the home of
					Mrs. Nelson, Wyomissing. A <org
						reg="Berks Country Birth Control Federation">temporary organization</org>
					was formed which will be followed by a month of educational work after which a
					permanent organization will be formed with the purpose of establishing clinics
					in Reading to instruct parents in this subject.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="RT">Rev.<person reg="Williams, L. Griswold"> L. Griswold Williams</person>
					pastor of the <org>Universalist Church of Our Father</org>, was elected
					president of the temporary organization. The other officers are: Vice president,
					Mrs. <person reg="Welfy, Ella A.">Ella Welfy</person>; recording secretary, Mrs.
						<person reg="Stuber, Adda J.">Raymond Stuber</person>; executive secretary,
					Mrs. A.D. Nelson; treasurer, <person reg="Nelson, Albert D.">A.D.
						Nelson</person>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="RT">The organization will conduct its work along educational lines for
					community betterment until Monday, Feb. 6, when a public meeting will be held at
					which time the permanent organization will be formed. Mayor <person
						reg="Stauffer, John">Stauffer</person>, who has shown interest in work along
					the lines of medical help, was present at the meeting yesterday.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">The Evening Meeting</head>
			<p>
				<q who="RT">Rev. Mr. Williams opened the public meeting in <org>Odd Fellows
						hall</org> last night at which Mrs. Sanger was the speaker. Mr. Williams
					stated that as representative of a liberal Christian church he could heartily
					approve of the movement as a deeply religious and essentially moral
					movement.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="RT">Mrs. Sanger, who was in Reading before and drew large audiences, was
					well received by the audience which completely filled the auditorium and
					balconies. She explained the purposes of the league and the necessity for birth
					control. Then she told of the arguments used by those opposed to the movement
					and refuted them.</q>
			</p>

		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
