<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/07/15 AS encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-08-15 CH proof and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-05 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-10 CH clean up docs title</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-06-14">14 Jun 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">California Civic League Address</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422036</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Eager Hundreds 'Hitch' Chairs to Hear Message</title>,
					<title type="journal">Oakland Tribune</title>, June 15, 1916, p. 1 and <title
					type="article">Birth Control Lectures End</title>, <title type="journal">San
					Francisco Examiner</title>, June 14, 1916, p. 7</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SFE">San Francisco Examiner</name>
			<name id="OT">Oakland Tribune</name>
			<name id="CARMR">Carter, Mrs. A.C.</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke to the Califorina Civic League in Oakland on Jun 14, 1916. She may have
			given the “<xref from="128002.xml">Woman and Birth Control</xref>," Apr-July 1916, but
			must have altered it given the fact that California women had the vote in 1916.
			Summaries from two newspapers have been included below.</p>
		<index level1="California" level2="birth control movement in"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<div>
			<head>EAGER HUNDREDS 'HITCH' CHAIRS TO HEAR MESSAGE</head>
			<head type="sub">Audience is entirely for Mrs. Sanger at Civic Center</head>
			<p>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Descriptions about the audience at the meeting have been
					omitted. Eds.</supplied>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">Whatever might be found amusing about the audience's first arrival and
					its first attitude, there was nothing absurd about Mrs. Sanger. Her audience was
					entirely for her and with her. The president of the Oakland Center, <person
						reg="Carter, Mrs. A. C.">Mrs. A. C. Carter</person>, expressed the Center's
						"<q who="CARMR">sympathy and admiration and support of her.</q>" <person
						reg="Goldman, Emma">Emma Goldman</person>, it would seem, is the only one of
					the brilliant birth control advocates who hasn't become popular.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">But Mrs. Sanger is not like Emma Goldman. She is slight and feminine to
					look at. Though she spoke with intensity of the injustice of undesired
					motherhood and the misery of unfortunate working women with dozens of children,
					she gives an impression of personal warmth. Her attitude is scientific--cold.
					She is a nurse and a teacher who knows how to reach crowds with her high ringing
					voice, her earnestness, her knowledge of conditions.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">She spoke of the success of clinics in <place reg="Netherlands"
						>Holland</place> where family limitation is taught, of how the Hollanders
					height had increased, the health of women had increased, and how infant
					mortality had dropped to the lowest in the world, and she drew contrasts.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">She spoke of the heavy infant mortality, of children born to families
					that could not care for them, of child labor and of the social evil. And she
					blamed it all upon ignorance of the measure she advocates.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">THE OBJECTION</head>
			<p>"The principle objection in the minds of most people against such knowledge," <q
					who="OT">she commented rather acidly,</q> "is the idea that women's morals might
				suffer. Solicitude over women's morals has always been a cloak to cover the age-long
				consipiracy to keep her in bondage. In <place>Spain</place>, where I visited last
				year, the greater portion of the 11,000,000 illiterates are women. Why? Because if
				they learned to read, they might learn something.</p>
			<p>"One travels on donkeys over bridle paths in Spain--because roads and railroads would
				make communication easy. They would bring women and girls into the city where they
				would become immoral."</p>
			<p>"Do we think our railroads have more immoral than the Spanish women?"</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">TO CONQUER LAWS</head>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">Later in her speech, Mrs. Sanger in her soft blue gown leaned forward to
					tell women that the only way they might develop their individualities was to
					"learn to conquer nature's laws that have kept her in bondage," just as man has
					learned to conquer the sea with ships and the land with trains and such
					things.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">In order to accomplish a general conquest, however, they were urged to
					bring about a repeal of the law still existing in this country alone--making her
					sort of instruction a crime punishable by imprisonment.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">ARRAIGNS CENSORSHIP</head>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">Throughout the speech she was continuously applauded and especially when
					she arrainged the censorship of the post office and <person
						reg="Roosevelt, Theodore">Roosevelt</person>'s ideas of morality.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"It was never indended that the post office should pass political, religious and
				moral judgement. It was supposed to be a mechanical and not an ethical institution,"
					<q who="OT">she added. This was in explaining why she had defied the law and how
					she had been arrested as a result. Also how thousands of telegrams--including
					many from English celebrities such as <person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G.
						Wells</person>, <person reg="Schreiner, Olive">Olive Schreiner</person>, and
					other free thinkers had helped.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">For she is not unconscious of her courage. Mrs. Sanger let them know she
					had started knowing the consequence, perhaps of her mission. As in San
					Francisco, she compared herself with Roosevelt, asking who was more moral--she
					who urged small families, or he, who wished upon the working men and woman many
					children.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">So much applause followed that it was evident that the Rooseveltian
					theory would never win him many of the women's votes.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">Moreover, when all the evil effects of large undesired families had been
					related--from poverty to prostitution, and all the excellent results of "better
					and fewer" children--the meeting ended with one onslaught toward the back of the
					room where various pamphlets written by Mrs. Sanger were piled high between the
					ivory pillars.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="OT">It was a long time before the sale of the pamphlets ended. They were
					sold, by the way, by men.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>BIRTH CONTROL LECTURES END</head>
			<q who="SFE">
				<p><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> says she looks to the
					women of <place>California</place> to take the first steps that will place
						<place reg="United States">this country</place> on the same basis with
						<place reg="Europe">European countries</place> in the matter of birth
					control.</p>
				<p>She declared yesterday in her talk before the <place reg="Oakland, CA"
						>Oakland</place> center of the <org>California Civic League</org> in
						<org>Hotel Oakland</org> that the women of California, with the power of
					suffrage, could bring about the repeal of the laws against the dissemination of
					information about birth control, and by so doing could set the pace for the
					whole country along this line.</p>
			</q>
			<p>"This is my last appearance here," <q who="SFE">said Mrs. Sanger.</q> "I leave
				to-morrow for <place reg="Portland, OR">Portland,</place> on my way to the East
				again. I shall return in October and I hope that by that time you women will have
				made decided progress toward getting the laws repealed that now forbid your
				physician to tell you the vital facts of life.</p>
			<p>"When I return to California and find that California women have accomplished this I
				shall immediately begin the installation of scientifically conducted clinics, where
				this information can be given to the working women--in other words, to those who
				need it most and who find it hardest to obtain."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
