<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 CH proofed tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-29 CH entered tag corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>correct proof and update index</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-13 CH reg doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-08-09">9 Aug 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Japanese and War</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422071</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Advocate Finds Japs Talk War</title>, <title
					type="journal">Kansas City Kansan</title>, Aug. 9, 1922, p. 1</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="KCK">Kansas City Kansan</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For a similar statement, see "<xref from="422070.xml">Interview with the International
				News Service</xref>," Sept. 5, 1922.</p>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922 (World)"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="politics in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="and war"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>BIRTH CONTROL ADVOCATE FINDS JAPS TALK WAR</head>

		<dateline><place reg="London, England">London</place>, <date value="1922-08-09">Aug.
				9</date>.--</dateline>
		<div type="section">
			<p>"They talk war and nothing but war in <place>Japan</place>."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="KCK">This was the lasting expression left on the mind of Mrs. Margaret
					Sanger, who has returned to <place>Europe</place> en route for <place
						reg="United States">America</place> after an extensive tour in the <place
						reg="Asia">east</place> under the aegis of the <org
						reg="International Birth Control Association">International Birth Control
						association</org>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="KCK">Mrs. Sanger traversed the east propagating an unknown and very delicate
					subject and was accompanied only by her <person reg="Sanger, Grant"
						>twelve-year-old son</person>. She returns to western civilization proud and
					happy with her accomplishments.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Japanese Are Interested.</head>
			<p>"I found the Japanese most interested in the subject," <q who="KCK"> said Mrs.
					Sanger.</q> "At first they were skeptical. I had to grope my way to find what
				angle of the situation most appealed to them. It was different from the
				American."</p>
			<p> "You know in America the American husband is just a big baby where the health of his
				wife is concerned, and therefore it was easy to get the sympathy of every American
				when it was pointed out to them that the health of their wives was impaired if they
				bore over three babies."</p>
			<p>"That angle was lost on the Japs. The health of their wives was nothing to them. They
				were listless when I played on that point. They still have the old eastern idea that
				the women are merely created for their pleasure and the reproduction of their
				species."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>Family Costs Vital.</head>
			<p>"But on the questions of economics they were all agog. It is just as expensive to
				rear and educate a large family in Japan as it is in <place>New York</place>, and
				the matter of cost roused the Oriental conscience to a great degree."</p>
			<p> "Then they became most interested in the subject. They questioned me on all angles
				of the problem. The most delicate points they wanted discussed to the most academic
				degree. With me they were very frank, but never objectionable, and afterward when I
				convinced them that our methods neither meant the taking of life nor demanded
				husbandly restraint they were with me to a man."</p>
			<p>"The result was that before I left Japan we had formed an <org
					reg="Japan Birth Control League">association</org> with branches in every big
				city and clinics were in the process before I left."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
