<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-08-18 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-11-12">12 Nov 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Introduction for Harold Cox </supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422111</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Birth Control: What It Is, How it Works, What it Will Do:
					Proceedings of the American Birth Control Conference Held at the Hotel Plaza,
					New York, November 11, 12, 1921</title> (New York: 1921), p. 111</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp>
				<name/>
			</resp>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger introduced Harold Cox, who spoke on "War and Population" during the third session
			of the <org reg="American Conference on Birth Control, 1st">First American Birth Control
				Conference</org>.</p>
		<p>For other speeches and comments made at this conference, see "<xref from="229953.xml"
				>Opening Address</xref>," "<xref from="422109.xml">Summary of the Second
				Session</xref>,""<xref from="229952.xml">The Use of the Pessary</xref>," "<xref
				from="422111.xml">Comments</xref>," "<xref from="238254.xml">The Morality of Birth
				Control</xref>," and "<xref from="231277.xml">Closing Remarks</xref>"</p>
		<index level1="Cox, Harold"/>
		<index level1="conference" level2="American Birth Control Conference" level3="1921 (1st)"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>

		<p>When we were planning for this conference, we recognized that it was vastly important to
			bring to this conference some one who would guide our activities for the future. The
			work that we have been able to do so far in the <place>United States</place> has been to
			propagate the idea of Birth Control in its relation to health, to individual economics,
			to woman's freedom, also the historical and legal aspects of the Birth Control movement.
			But today, with the great international crisis upon us, it seemed to us necessary to
			have some one who could tell us how we should conduct our work in relation to the
			international problem of the work, so I went out to seek the man whom I consider the
			greatest authority on population, and that is Mr. <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold
				Cox</person>, whom I take pleasure, and have the honor to introduce.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
