<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-07-27 CH transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1930-06-18">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">18 Jun 1930</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Bennington Mothers' Club Speech</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422106</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">200 Hear Talk By Margaret Sanger</title>, <title
					type="journal">Bennington Herald</title>, June 18, 1930</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BH">Bennington Herald</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="age at"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="establishment of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>200 HEAR TALK BY MARGARET SANGER</head>
		<dateline><place reg="Bennington, NH">BENNINGTON</place>, <date value="1930-06-18">June
				18</date>.--</dateline>
		<p><q who="BH">The aims of the national <org
				reg="National Committe on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">committee on
				Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> were explained this evening by Mrs.
			Margaret Sanger of <place reg="New York, NY">New York city</place> to an audience of 200
			in the Baptist church here, when she spoke under the auspices of the <org
				reg="Bennington Mothers' Club">Bennington Mothers' club</org>.</q></p>
		<p><q who="BH">Mrs. Sanger declared that the committee is working to prevent transmission of diseases
			such as tuberculosis and other incurable maladies from mother to child. It favors the
			establishment of clinics where reputable and accredited physicians may give to
			responsible mothers such contraceptive knowledge and advice as applies to individual
			cases. She stated that 40 such clinics are now being conducted in the <place>United
				States</place> besides practically all the larger hospitals in New York city, where
			they are conducted by the staff physicians.</q></p>
		<p><q who="BH">Prevention of the marriage of immature or adolescent youths is another aim of the
			organization and the deferment of raising families until married people become adjusted
			to wedded life is also advised. The economic question is considered in the aims of the
			committee, as well as the health of mothers.</q></p>
		<p><q who="BH">Mrs. Sanger declared that <place>Vermont</place> is one of the most liberal states in its
			laws regarding these matters, although the <org reg="Vermont State Legislature">state
				Legislature</org> refused to pass a sterilization law several years ago. She pointed
			out the social problems involved when the birth rate is unlimited in the families of
			those who are mentally, physically, morally and economically unfit to raise families.
			She stressed the point that the organization does not advocate destroying life, but the
			prevention or limitation of the birth rate under certain conditions.</q></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
