<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-08-18 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-26 CH enter proofreading corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-11-12">12 Nov 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">First American Birth Control Conference
					Comments</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422111</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Birth Control: What It Is, How it Works, What it Will Do:
					Proceedings of the American Birth Control Conference Held at the Hotel Plaza,
					New York, November 11, 12, 1921</title> (New York: 1921), p. 121</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp>
				<name id="TODHE">Todd, Helen</name></resp>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's comments were made during the discussion after the third
			session of the <org reg="American Conference on Birth Control, 1st">First American Birth
				Control Conference</org>, comprised of papers by <person reg="Stoddard, Lothrop"
				>Lothrop Stoddard</person> on the population of Asia, <person reg="Maurer, James"
				>James Maurer</person> on birth control and infant mortality, and <person
				reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person> on war and population. Sanger responded
			specifically to a comment by <person reg="Todd, Helen">Helen Todd</person> which argued
			that based on government figures, working men and women would not be able to afford even
			one child, making woman "<q who="TODHE">simply an instrument of sex pleasure. She could
				not even have one child under our present system.</q>" </p>
		<p>For other speeches and comments made at this conference, see "<xref from="229953.xml"
				>Opening Address</xref>," "<xref from="422109.xml">Summary of the Second
				Session</xref>,""<xref from="229952.xml">The Use of the Pessary</xref>," "<xref
				from="422110.xml">Introduction for Harold Cox</xref>," "<xref from="238254.xml">The
				Morality of Birth Control</xref>," and "<xref from="231277.xml">Closing
				Remarks</xref>"</p>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="unfit to reproduce" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="women and girls" level2="enslavement of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>

		<p>I would say in answer to Miss Todd, and I appreciate her question, that she would like to
			have every woman have the expression of motherhood and be allowed to have it, and that
			today the economic conditions make it impossible for a great many women to have that
			expression. It seems to me that our problem of Birth Control, and where we have to
			differ in making our first step from all the other ideals that we would like to bring about
			is, that our first step in this work is to stop the propagation of the unfit and the
			diseased and those who are carrying on the race. What will evolve out of this movement
			when children have become scarcer, when motherhood has been more dignified, is another
			problem that we will reach later. I think that is a question not of the present but of
			the future, and it seems to me that Birth Control today is not confronted with that
			problem as much as it is with the many millions of mothers who already have too many
			children. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
