<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-07-27 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-05 CH clean up place</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-13 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1951-09-29">29 Sep 1951</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Government Subsidies for Babies</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422104</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">She's Telling the World We Have Babies to Get 3s. a
					Week</title>, <title type="journal">News of the World</title>, Sept. 30,
				1951</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NOTW">News of the World</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="population policies"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth rate in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>She's Telling the World We Have Babies to Get 3s. a Week</head>
		<byline>From ARCH MACDONALD</byline>
		<dateline><place>New York</place>, <date value="1951-09-29">Saturday</date>.</dateline>
		<p><q who="NOTW">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, a leader of the birth control movement in <place
					reg="United States">America</place>, said today that the </q>"old British habit"
				<q who="NOTW">of having babies was placed on a mercenary basis by Government
				Subsidies. She has just returned from a <place reg="London, England">London</place>
				meeting of the <org>International Committee on Planned Parenthood</org>.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="NOTW">Presumably referring to the allowance of 5s. a week for each child after
				the first, she complained that the subsidizing of large families was hampering the
				objectives of the planned parenthood movement.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"While I heartily agree that food should be provided for babies and small children," <q
				who="NOTW">she said,</q> "I think it is humiliating to parents to put parenthood on
			a mercenary basis of subsidies.</p>
		<p>"The measly two or three shillings a week is degrading and attracts only the most
			undesirable parents who have more children to get the miserably low subsidy money which
			they invariably squander."</p>
		<p>"It is certainly a sad commentary if the parents can't earn money any other way."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="NOTW">Mrs. Sanger, who is honorary chairman of the <org>Planned Parenthood
					Federation of America</org>, complained that though food shortages have made
				British parents more conscious of family problems, they had not produced any
				increased demand for birth control information.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"I think the <org reg="United Kingdom Government">Government</org> is short-sighted when
			it does not stop to consider that <place reg="Great Britain">Britain</place> is already
			overpopulated by some 20,000,000 people and that in five or 10 years the children of
			today will be competing with the adults for meat and eggs,"<q who="NOTW"> she
			added.</q></p>
		<p>"From my observations most Britons already are underweight and hungry. They seem to eat a
			vast quantity of buns for quick energy, but they need eggs, meat and cheese for a
			balanced diet."</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
