<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-03-27 JC transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-30 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-00-00">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">1929</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Foreword to Laws Concerning Birth Control in the United States</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp431940</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Laws Concerning Birth Control in the United States</title> (New
				York, 1929) pp. 5-7</bibl>


		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="INGWI">Inge, William Ralph</name>
			<name id="KEIAR">Keith, Arther</name>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For draft versions see Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections S71:187 and
			191.</p>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock  Laws"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="state"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="government and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Foreword</head>
		<p>This survey of the state laws concerning Birth Control is an interpretation of the law in
			each state and the particular section dealing with the subject is quoted.</p>
		<p>In a majority of states the Penal Code has been revised and while there have been few
			changes in the laws during the past ten years the section numbers have been changed for
			reference purposes, therefore it has been advisable in this survey to indicate the new
			section numbers.</p>
		<p>The laws of many states are so drawn that they cannot be definitely stated without
			consulting the decisions of the courts. This is particularly true of
				<place>Maryland</place>, <place>Kentucky</place>, <place>Kansas</place>,
				<place>Masachusetts</place> and <place>Connecticut</place>.</p>
		<p>There is a question of the rights of physicians to give information in some states. The
			statutes of Kansas and Massachusetts prohibit only the publication or advertisement of
			such information. They are very similar to the statutes of such states as
				<place>Arizona</place>, <place>Washington</place> and others listed under the
			heading of states where physicians may legally give information on prevention of
			contraception but cannot publish it.</p>
		<p>The law in Connecticut prohibits only the <emph rend="italics">use</emph> of any drug or
			medicine, article or instrument. Nothing is said prohibiting physicians from giving such
			information. The only state in the Union that clearly prohibits a physician from giving
			information is <place>Mississippi</place>.</p>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Preface</head>
			<p>
				<emph rend="italics"><q who="INGWI">"The Comstock legislation in America has done
						unmixed harm. It is worse than useless to put down by law a practice which a
						very large number of people believes to be harmless, and which must be left
						to the taste and the conscience of the individual."</q>--The Very Rev.
						<person reg="Inge, William Ralph">W. R. Inge</person>, Dean of <org>St.
						Paul's Cathedral</org>, <place reg="London, England">London</place>.</emph>
			</p>
			<p>Sir <person reg="Keith, Arthur">Arthur Keith</person> asserts that the <place
					reg="United States">United States of America</place> is now the field of the <q
					who="KEIAR">"unfolding of the greatest experiment in race building the world has
					ever seen."</q> To the successful fulfillment of this great
				experiment--co-ordination and co-operation of all the forces of intelligence are
				essential if we are going to carry it through consciously and creatively.</p>
			<p>In the creation of a race of strong, well-born children, fitted by proper heredity
				and breeding to transmit undimmed the life force to the succeeding generation, the
				instrument of Birth Control cannot be ignored: its importance is crucial and
				primary. By this instrument uncounted thousands of parents have been liberated from
				the bondage of unwilling parenthood. Fundamentally Birth Control, scientifically,
				hygienically and ethically exercised, places in the hands of all potential parents
				the power to master imperious reproductive instincts. To women in particular it
				confers the power of conscious and voluntary choice. It permits the potential mother
				to determine when, where, and under what conditions--social, economic and
				financial--she shall bring children into the world. She can control the number of
				her children; she can space their births to suit her physical resources and the
				conditions of family life, as well as to assure the well-being, the future health
				and happiness of all her children. Birth Control is thus revealed, in addition, as a
				beneficent social force closely and organically related to the well-being of the
				entire community--civic and national.</p>
			<p>The Birth Control Clinic, as a school for parenthood, and as a social agency strikes
				at the alarmingly high maternal death rate which is now so profound a disgrace to
				this nation. A system of standardized and efficiently functioning Birth Control
				Clinics operating in all American communities would accomplish much in the solutions
				of the nation-wise problems of dependency, delinquency, and the administration of
				organized charities. Eventually, it is predicted, conscious and voluntary parenthood
				would eliminate the necessity of the expenditure of vast funds in the maintenance of
				institutions which now harbor thousands of helpless dependents. These funds, it is
				our contention, should be utilized toward the development of American civilization
				in its finer aspects.</p>
			<p>Co-ordination and co-operation, to repeat, are the first essentials. The scattered
				forces of intelligence must be mobilized into a nation-wide unit, organized to
				influence all enlightened and intelligent American citizens to join in a campaign to
				remove the obstacles which now hinder the efficient functioning of existing and
				experimental schools of motherhood.</p>
			<p>The first duty is to effect the amendment of the United States Penal Code (Sections
					<name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">211</name>,
					<name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 245">245</name>,
					<name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 311">311</name> and
					<name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 312">312</name>)
				which prohibit the use of the United States mail for the transmission of any advice
				concerning contraception. Section 211, moreover, makes it unlawful for one physician
				to send through the mails the result or benefits of his practice or research. To
				send an applicant for information the address of any legally operating Birth Control
				Clinic is also illegal, according to the present Federal statutes.</p>
			<p>Necessary amendment of these sections of the Federal Penal Code cannot be effected
				without the organization of a definite, unified national body of distinguished
				leaders in various fields of endeavor, which, by the prestige of its intelligence
				and public-mindedness, can enlighten public opinion in widely separated communities
				concerning the national and racial necessity of removing legal obstacles which now
				hinder the successful fulfillment of the greatest experiment in race building the
				world has ever witnessed.</p>
			<p>MARGARET SANGER</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
