<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2Ol2—11—06 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Curt L. Heymann</docAuthor>
<docDate vaipe<"1952—l2—21">21 Dec l952</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>The 'Culmination‘ of Margaret Sanger's Life
Work</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp321965</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>Los Angeles Times</title> Dec 21, 1952. pg. B5</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<name 'a*"HEYCU">Heymann, Curtis-Lx/name>
<name ;d>"SANMA">Sanger, Margareti/name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNOte rest "MSPP">
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
,+ ~ i~"birth control" Q. ll "history of"/>
im*~”l "birth.control" io @1?—"international'V>
;eveQle"birth.control" ievcl§:"international conferences on7>
;eve;l:"Brownsville Clinic"level21"arrests and trial"/>
iev@li:"Catholic ChurchV>
levell1"Catholic Church"leviiQ>"birth control and"/>
lG“:‘1I"Child spacing"/>
le'\ilW"China" ievs,1="birth control in"/>
;cvQll*"China" Q, ;I:"birth rate in"/>
lCV€li;"EUIOpe" le*oi3<"birth control in"/>
,e"ell;"Gandhi, MahatmaV>
lo e.lt"India" i» ~iZ>"birth control in"/>
1.v¢ l "International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 3rd (l952 Bombay)"/>
iv ,_l:"Japan" qr'1 ,+"birth control in"/>
2 \.i="Japan"f~vr\¢<"overpopulation andV>
.@Ye E "Japan" ,@ 1,~"U.S. occupation of"/>
_a:e.k"Sanger, Margaret"lc¢el2:"arrests"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>The 'Culmination‘ of Margaret Sanger's Life Work</head>
<byline>BY <person :@@~"Heymann, Curt lh'>CURT L.
HEYMANN</person></byline>
<div>
<p>“<q whw:"SANMA">The international conference of the<org>World
Planned Parenthood Federation</org> which I helped
organize and just attended in<place>Bombay, India</placez
is the culmination of my lifek work,</q§'confided Margaret
Sanger as we settled down for an interview in the lobby of the
Hotel Crillon. “<q wno:"SANMA">I have waited 40 years for



\
., |\
1/6
ﬁle:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/NewDocs/321965.xmI
<?md.version="l.O" encoding="UTF—8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc PUBLIC "Public Speeches and Articles of Margaret Sanger"
"http://www.nyu.edu/projects/sanger/webedition/xml_added/meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc *§;e""Published interview$
<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2Ol2—11—06 AW Initial Tag</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Curt L. Heymann</docAuthor>
<docDate vaipe<"1952—l2—21">21 Dec l952</docDate>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>The 'Culmination‘ of Margaret Sanger's Life
Work</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<idno>msp321965</idno>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><title>Los Angeles Times</title> Dec 21, 1952. pg. B5</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
<respStmt>
<name 'a*"HEYCU">Heymann, Curtis-Lx/name>
<name ;d>"SANMA">Sanger, Margareti/name>
</respStmt>
</mepHeader>
<headNOte rest "MSPP">
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
<index
,+ ~ i~"birth control" Q. ll "history of"/>
im*~”l "birth.control" io @1?—"international'V>
;eveQle"birth.control" ievcl§:"international conferences on7>
;eve;l:"Brownsville Clinic"level21"arrests and trial"/>
iev@li:"Catholic ChurchV>
levell1"Catholic Church"leviiQ>"birth control and"/>
lG“:‘1I"Child spacing"/>
le'\ilW"China" ievs,1="birth control in"/>
;cvQll*"China" Q, ;I:"birth rate in"/>
lCV€li;"EUIOpe" le*oi3<"birth control in"/>
,e"ell;"Gandhi, MahatmaV>
lo e.lt"India" i» ~iZ>"birth control in"/>
1.v¢ l "International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 3rd (l952 Bombay)"/>
iv ,_l:"Japan" qr'1 ,+"birth control in"/>
2 \.i="Japan"f~vr\¢<"overpopulation andV>
.@Ye E "Japan" ,@ 1,~"U.S. occupation of"/>
_a:e.k"Sanger, Margaret"lc¢el2:"arrests"/>
</headNote>
<docBody>
<head>The 'Culmination‘ of Margaret Sanger's Life Work</head>
<byline>BY <person :@@~"Heymann, Curt lh'>CURT L.
HEYMANN</person></byline>
<div>
<p>“<q whw:"SANMA">The international conference of the<org>World
Planned Parenthood Federation</org> which I helped
organize and just attended in<place>Bombay, India</placez
is the culmination of my lifek work,</q§'confided Margaret
Sanger as we settled down for an interview in the lobby of the
Hotel Crillon. “<q wno:"SANMA">I have waited 40 years for



Z6
ﬁle:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/NewDocs/321965.xm|
it.</qik/p>
<p>The worlds most outstanding crusader for birth control, who had
circled the globe to be present at this historic event of which
she said it would influence plans for the future of the whole
world, seemed to be satisfied with the results of her latest
crusade.</p>
<p>It was a trip that took her from the<place>United States</place>
across the Pacific, first to<place>Japan</place>, then by way
of<place gag "Hong Kong, China">Hong Kong</place> and
<place>Singapore</place> to<place>India</place>. From
<place>Asia</place> Mrs. Sanger flew straight back to
<place>Europe</place> and she was on the last leg of her
global voyage here in<place reg<"Paris, France">Paris</place>
before returning to<place reg:"New York, NY">New York</place>
and<place :eae"Tucson, AZ">TuCsOn, Ariz.</place>, where she now
makes her home.</p>
</div>
<div>
<p>The 40 years she mentioned were a reflection upon her four
decades of crusading. And as she referred to them with emotion,
her thoughts probably went back to the days before and during
World War I when she fought against a formidable array of
opponents, including the U.S. government itself.</p>
<p>Th0se were the days when she was persecuted and suffered from
mental anguish, served a prison term and was indicted for the
violation of the<title type:"law">Comstock Act of l873</title> which
classified contraceptive information as obscene. She left the
country in 1914 on the eve of the trial which never came off.
The indictment was quashed, but the Comstock Law was not
changed.</p>
<p>Three years later she and her sister served 30-day prison
sentences for operating a birth control clinic in New York. But
the vigorous little red—haired woman, one of ll children, had
inherited her rebellious nature from her Irish father,<person
1~Q»"Higgins, Michaelf>Michael Higgins</person>, and decided
to fight for “<q pa:r"SANMA">freedom.of the mind from dogma and
cant.</q>"</p>
</div>
<div>
<p>On New YorKs<place>Lower East Side</place> she had nursed women whose
pregnancy was what she called a “chronic condition." In despair
she gave up nursing and embarked on a powerful idea for which
she was finally awarded world recognition.</p>
<p>Wistful and fragile, Mrs. Sanger is a quiet and unassuming
person. Now close to 70, the protagonist of a once controversial
movement for which she fought with the courage of a lion still
speaks with the eloquence of a crusader. But there is a
contentment in her voice when she reviews the last 20 years of
her work.</p>
</div>
<div>



3%
ﬁle:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/NewDocs/321965.xm|
<p>Thanks to her efforts, birth control in the United States has
been recognized by the<org>American.Medical Association</0rg>
and is legalized in 46 States. Only two,<place rcqr"MA"
>Massachusetts</place> and<place r»g:"CT"
>Connecticut</place>, have laws against it. Birth control
under medical supervision is sanctioned by many church groups.
Only the<org>Roman Catholic Church</org> remains, on religious
grounds, its principal opponent.</p>
<p>In 1914, when Mrs. Sanger chose the name<org>National Birth
Control League</org> for her young venture, she probably
didn't dream that the movement would ever grow to world
proportions. In the 30s all her efforts to win Congressional
support and all measures contemplated to legalize the idea were
defeated.</p>
<p>Today, child spacing is part of public health in a number of
States and Mrs. Sanger is honorary chairman of the<org>Planned
Parenthood Federation of America</org> which has its
headquarters in New York. Herself the mother of three children
(a daughter died but her two sons are practicing physicians in
Arizona and New York) she has eight grandchildren.</p>
</div>
<div>
<p>Recalling that she visited Japan 30 years ago, Mrs. Sanger told
me that she predicted a Japanese war in<place
»ng:"Tokyo, JaparV>Tokyo</place> in 1922, because of the
countrys high birth rate and Japanr restricted territory, too
small to accommodate her overpopulation.</p>
<p>“<q w3@—"SANMA">But then only a group of intellectuals listened
to me,</q>" she said. “<q wio="SANMA">The military turned
the idea of birth control down and the subject was not to be
discussed. Japan, at the time, had a population of
60,000,000, a birth rate of l,200,00 per year and a
territory two—thirds as large as<place feg+"CA"
>California</place>. The country could have remained
without war and slowly increased her birth rate, but
evidently Japan wasn't ready for birth control.</q></p>
<p>"<q wi@Y"SANMA">Today, 84,000,000 Japanese must live on a much
smaller territory and the nation’s birth rate has risen to
2,000,000 annually. Japanese women are quite conscious of
the fact that a high birth rate meant and still means war.
So they have been resorting to abortions. There were
1,500,000 reported abortions in Japan last year. That's not
our idea of birth control.</q>"</p>
<p>“<q ii "HEYCU">But aren't abortions illegal in Japan?</q>"</p>
</div>
<div>
<p>“<q ‘£?'"SANMA">No, they are not. They are legalized under the
<title fypea"law">hygienic protection law of 1949</title>. The sale of
contraceptives
is also legal, but they are being used without general
knowledge or information.</q>"</p>
 .



1
4%
ﬁle:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/NewDocs/321965.xm|
<p>“<q "~11:""HEYCU">If my information is correct, you were supposed to visit Japan
several years ago to advise on contraceptives. What prevented
you from going there?</q>"</p>
<p>“<q wM ~"SANMA">The occupation authorities. I was invited by the editor of
Tokyo's<title>Mainichi Press</title> to visit Japan in
1949, shortly after the protection law was passed. But my
American visa was refused by Gen.<person
5;‘ "MacArthur, Douglas$DouglasMacArthur</person»
who considered my presence'outside interference.'After the
end of our military occupation, Mainichi invited me again
and I combined my visit to Japan with my trip to
Bombay.</q>"</p>
<p>“<q ;nc~"HEYCU">And what are the results of your Japanese visit?</q>"</p>
<p>“<q wt@¢"SANMA">I spent two weeks in Tokyo,<place re$="Kyot0, Japan"
>Kyoto</place> and<place req:"Osaka, Japan"
>Osaka</place> where three large meetings were arranged
for me. They were open to the public and held late in the
afternoon so that both men and women could attend. I talked
at each gathering for 40 minutes on the subject and it took
an interpreter about three hours to translate my
speeches.</q></p>
<p><q who'"SANMA">There were in addition round tables for
professional people, physicians, nurses and social workers.
Wherever I spoke people were very much interested and alert,
much more so than in any other country, not excluding the
United States. The poorest people would arrange street
meetings in Tokyo and I would stand on top of a bus talking
to them. And I would tell them that birth control means
prevention——not interference.</q>"</p>
<p>“<q u;":"HEYCU">Is birth control objectionable to Buddhisn1or any other Eastern
religion?</q>"</p>
<p>“<q M“q‘"SANMA">NO, it isn't. There's no remonstrance on
religious grounds. And as far as the Japanese are concerned
they saw the light of truth through war: no more political
objections——only economic and hygienic
considerations.</q></p>
<p><q wno—"SANMA">It will take awhile for them to get organized, set
up clinics, manufacture contraceptives and get used to the
formulas which I gave them. But eventually they'll be used
and distributed by the public health authorities.</q>"</p>
<p>“<q w;r:"HEYCU">I suppose the Chinese Communists are not interested in birth
control?</q>"</p>
<p>“<q mQu—"SANMA">NO, of course not. Like all Communist countries
and nations behind the Iron Curtain they have been giving
prizes for large families, regardless of social, economic
and hygienic conditions. That, in the Far East, is in strong
contrast to the situation in Hong Kong and Singapore, which
in the last two years have established excellent birth
control committees and clinics.</q></p>
</div>
<div>
 



7 I
56
ﬁle:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/NewDocs/321965.xml
<p>“<q wtm<"SANMA">Those colonies are terribly overpopulated through
refugees. Hong Kong, which had a prewar population of
700,000, has now 2,400,000. Birth control is still private.
But eventually it will come under public health authorities
to make it more effective.</q>"</p>
<p>“From there you flew directly to Bombay for the<org>World Birth
Control Conference</org>?"</p>
<p>“YeS. The Indians called it the<org>International Conference for
Family Planning</org>. It was held from Nov. 21 to Dec. 2
and was attended by 500 delegates from l5 countries, including
India. There were 21 Americans in our delegation. Lady<person
xc; "Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Rama Rau</person> was president
of the conference and by unanimous vote was elected president
for the Orient. I was made honorary president for North American
and Dr.<person 1ic:"Blacker, Carlos Paton">C. P.
</div>
<div>
<pSkq
<p§Zq
<p>“<q
</div>
<div>
<pikq
<p>“<q
<p>“<q
Europe</q>?"</p>
<p>“<q
Blacker</person> of<place r¢:1"London, England"
>London</place> became director of the world federation.</p>
»“~ "SANMA">This is the culmination of my life's work and I
firmly believe that a new leaf has been turned in the
history book of birth control. Because for the first time
Orient met Occident in a planned parenthood conference held
in<place>Asia</place> on an international level.</q></p>
.ho="SANMA">In my address to the assembly I recalled my visit
to<person ;cg~"Gandhi, Mahatma5Gandhi</person> in 1936. We
talked about birth control in India and he agreed that some
form of control would have to be instituted or India would
remain enslaved. Gandhi thought the ideal number of children
for each Indian family would be four.</q>"</p>
:jc*"HEYCU">HOW excessive is the Indian birth rate?</q>"</p>
.a¢~"SANMA">There were 5,000,000 births in 1950 and the same
number in l95l——far beyond the countryﬁ possibilities of
feeding, clothing or housing them. In Bombay alone thousands
sleep in the streets and every Indian city tells the same
story. But birth control and reduction of births are not
enough.</q></p>
t,~"SANMA">The Indians must improve their land to produce
more food and in order to do that they must increase their
water supplies. But whatever they do——reduction of the birth
rate must precede these steps.</q>"</p>
3;.<"HEYCU">How do you find the birth control situation in free
.?><"SANMAF>It's lagging far behind because of the last war.
Chief antagonism does not come from the people but from the
hierarchy of the Roman Catholic Church which dominates
political action and threatens to boycott every activity of
the public health officials wishing to give birth control
information and advice.</q></p>
 



N6
ﬁle:/S:/TRANSCRIPTIONS/NGWDOCS/321965.Xm|
</div>
<div>
<p>“<q Pia "SANMA">While all Scandinavian countries, especially
<place>Sweden</place>, have made the greatest progress,
and countries like<place>England</placez
<place>Holland</place>, <place>Switzerland</place> and
<place>West Germany</place> practice birth control
freely, such predominantly Catholic countries as
<place>France</place>, <place>Italy</place)
<place>Spain</place> and<place>Belgium</place> have
banned contraceptives.</q>"</p>
<p>“<q sW"HEYCU">Will you or the world federation help Western
Europe to organize birth control?</q>"</p>
<p>“<q w5ne"SANMA">No, the people of free Europe have got to fight for that liberty
themselves.</q>"</p>
<p>The late<person ;,. "Broun, Heywood">Heywood Broun</person> once
complained that Mrs. Sanger had no sense of humor. I asked her
nevertheless to tell me an amusing anecdote that might have
occurred on her round—the—world tour. Now as then she retorted
with the same reply:</p>
<p>“<q w"c>"SANMA">I am the protagonist of women who have nothing to
laugh at.</q>"</p>
</div>
</docBody>
</doc>
