<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2009/08/04</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-11 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1928-00-00">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">1928</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>What is Birth Control?</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp106476</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Library of Congress</bibl>
			<bibl>Library of Congress Microfilm 8:721</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Handwritten additions and deletions made by Sanger's secretary, <person
				reg="Rose, Florence">Florence Rose</person>.</p>
		<index level1="population" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="population growth" level2="standard of living and"/>
		<index level1="mentally disabled and diseased" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="race suicide"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>WHAT IS BIRTH CONTROL?</head>
		<byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p> What is Birth Control?</p>
		<p>Why do we need it?</p>
		<p>What will it do for Humanity?</p>
		<p>Birth Control is the keynote of a new social program. It is interlocked with the future
			of our nation and the progress of the race.</p>
		<p>Birth Control does not mean race suicide. It teaches the simple lesson that all children
			should be brought into <del>this old</del>
			<add>the</add> world <del>of ours</del> not by chance but by choice.<del> It places
				quality before quantity.</del> It teaches mothers and fathers to aim for the
			creation of a <add>perfect</add> race <del>of thoroughbreds</del>.</p>
		<p>Birth Control is as old as the world. Nature’s methods of birth control are
				<del>considered</del> ruthless. Whenever there are too many people in a country,
			Nature kills them off by disease, by epidemics, by plague, by famine, by warfare.
			History records these facts. When there is a high birth-rate, there is a high
			death-rate.</p>
		<p>We want to prevent such calamities. We are trying to teach mothers and fathers hygienic,
			scientific methods which will enable them to have <add>only</add> as many children as
			they can care for <del>with loving affection--but so many:</del></p>
		<p>
			<del>Parenthood should not be undertaken under the following conditions:</del>
		</p>
		<p>Married people should never have children when either parent is the victim of a
			transmissible disease , such as insanity, feeble-mindedness, epilepsy.</p>
		<p>When the mother is afflicted with <del>a temporary disease like</del> tuberculosis,
			kidney or heart disease, she should not be forced into motherhood.</p>
		<p>
			<del>If the children born are subnormal, no further babies should be born.</del>
		</p>
		<p>A space of at least two or three years should separate the birth of each child. This
			interval <add>would</add> give the mother a chance to regain her strength <del>and the
				opportunity to prepare for the coming of her baby. Also it </del>
			<add>also it</add> assures the child greater attention and more thorough care during the
			first three years of its life.</p>
		<p>
			<del>This is a way to reduce the infant mortality rate.</del>
		</p>
		<p>Babies should never be brought into the world when the father’s income is too small to
			provide proper care, proper feeding, proper clothing, and shelter.</p>
		<p>Every newly married couple need a year or two <del>to get acquainted with each
				other</del>, to make sure that their marriage is not the kind that is going on the
			rocks <add>in which event the children always are the ones to suffer</add>.
				<del>Their</del>
			<add>It seems to me too that in marriage</add> love must be strengthened,
				<del>their</del> marriage cemented, before their undertake the difficult task of
			parenthood <add>is undertaken</add>.</p>
		<p>We cannot measure the greatness of our country only by the sigh of the almighty dollar.
			You can measure it only by the health and happiness of its children.</p>
		<p>Birth control <add>may</add> mean fewer children, but <add>it means</add> healthier and
			happier <del>ones</del>
			<add>children</add>.</p>
		<p><person reg="Lincoln, Abraham">Abraham Lincoln</person> freed the slaves of <place
				reg="United States">America</place>. Help us, all of you who are listening to these
			words through the medium of this miracle of Science, to strike the chains from the
			enslaved mothers of the world!</p>
		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
