<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Typed article draft">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-08-13 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1940-12-15">15 Dec 1940</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Birth Control, 1940</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp233646</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collections</bibl>
			<bibl><title>Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title> S72:238</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="HIMHE">Himmler, Heinrich</name>
			<name id="VF">Vichy France</name>
			<name id="NESPA">National Economic and Social Planning Association</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This article was written for the <title type="book">Britannica Book of the Year</title>
			for 1941.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="war and"/>
		<index level1="child spacing"/>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="decline in"/>
		<index level1="birth rate" level2="population growth and"/>
		<index level1="fertility"/>
		<index level1="population" level2="war and"/>
		<index level1="Australia"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="France" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="censorship"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control clinics in"/>
		<index level1="conferences" level2="All India Women's Conference" level3="1935-36 (10th)"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control clinics and leagues in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control laws and legislation in"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
		<index level1="New Zealand" level2="birth rates in"/>
		<index level1="Puerto Rico" level2="birth control laws and legislation in"/>
		<index level1="Sweden"/>
		<index level1="voluntary motherhood"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="in US"/>
		<index level1="Birth Control Federation of America"/>
		<index level1="Connecticut" level2="birth control"
			level3="birth control laws and legislation"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>BIRTH CONTROL, 1940</head>
		<p>With the outbreak of the present World War, the continued drive of the totalitarian
			nations for increased population and the subjugation of the democracies where birth
			control programs had been in progress, not only have activities ceased in large part in
			these countries but with the rigid censorship, no news on what is transpiring has
			filtered through.</p>
		<p>The forced migration of millions of people in <place>Central Europe,</place> the
			starvation of millions more, the separation of families with great bodies of troops
			either in movement or at the various fronts and away from home, have all acted as a form
			of birth control. The birth rate always drops during war and remains low for some time
			after it.</p>
		<p>The malnutrition extending over large areas in <place>Europe</place> will affect
			fertility adversely during and after the war. With these factors will come the fear of
			depopulation which manifested itself before the war, and will probably be intensified
			later. It is hoped that there will also follow increased recognition of the need for
			intelligent and honest efforts to solve the problems of population pressure, especially
			those dealing with population distribution in relation to national resources. Without
			such solution, a lasting peace can never be achieved for these causes are basic reasons
			for aggression.</p>
		<p>Emphasis in the <place>United States</place> birth control movement has been on the need
			for expanding birth control services as a means of strengthening the physical, and
			economic well-being of the nation as it plans for national defense.</p>
		<p>Where reports have come through from abroad, there is evidence of continued activity and
			expansion of birth control facilities in countries not affected directly by the war, and
			the recognition of birth control as a public health measure has been growing in several
			of the Latin-American countries and the <place>West Indies</place>.</p>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">FOREIGN</head>
			<list>
				<item>
					<p>AUSTRALIA Birth Control clinics continued to operate in
							<place>Australia</place>, but mothers in the low income group are given
						a maternity bonus of $20 on the birth of each child and in <place>New South
							Wales</place> a small weekly payment for each child after the first.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="Cuba">CUBA</place> In <place reg="Havana, Cuba">Havana,</place>
						films dealing with the "Technique of Contraception" have been widely
						presented to the medical profession and the leading medical associations.
						There is particular interest in the birth control program of its neighboring
						Island, <place>Puerto Rico,</place> where efforts to solve similar problems
						of overpopulation have been underway for several years.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="England">ENGLAND</place> Activities of the <org>Family Planning
							Association</org> continued in <place>Great Britain</place> up to the
						outbreak of the war. Birth control clinics still functioned, and while
						formal reports from them were few and irregular, visitors from England
						reported increasing attendance, particularly among younger women, attempting
						to carry on under conditions of physical uncertainty, economic insecurity,
						and family disruption. The clinic of <person reg="Stopes, Marie C.">Dr.
							Marie Stopes,</person> the first established in <place
							reg="London, England">London,</place> was bombed in an air raid in
						October, 1940, and partly demolished. The <title type="journal">NEW
							GENERATION</title> and the <title type="journal">BIRTH CONTROL
							NEWS</title> continued to present the health and welfare arguments for
						planned parenthood.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="France">FRANCE</place> The <name type="law"
							reg="France Code de la famille">new code</name> which went into effect
						late in 1939, not only provided new and drastic regulations against
						abortion, but prohibited the advertising of contraception. Because of
						censorship of everything published, including even a discussion of
						contraception, <title type="journal">LA GRANDE REFORME,</title> the French
						Neo-Malthusian Journal, edited by <person reg="Humbert, Eugene">Eugene
							Humbert,</person> suspended publication late in the year.</p>
					<p>Following the conquest of France, <person reg="Ibarnegaray, Jean">Jean
							Ibarnegaray,</person> Minister of Youth in the <org reg="French State"
							>Vichy Government,</org> announced a new policy to stimulate the birth
						rate. The young women of France will be educated for one purpose only! <q
							who="VF">"To return to their traditional purpose of life--being in their
							homes and living only to raise strong useful men."</q> Fathers of
						families will be given preference over bachelors in both public and private
						employment and will be paid in proportion to the size of their families.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="Germany">GERMANY</place> Germany continued an uncompromising
						opposition to any form of birth control. In December 1939, a new population
						policy was officially announced. All soldiers going to the front are
						expected to leave children or prospective children behind them. <q
							who="HIMHE">"It can become an exalted task even outside of wedlock,"
							says <person reg="Himmler, Herr">Herr Himmler,</person> "for German
							women and girls of good blood to become--not frivolously, but imbued
							with deepest moral concern--mothers of children begotten by soldiers
							moving to the front, without knowing whether they will return or die for
							the Fatherland".</q></p>
					<p>Since the outbreak of the present war, censorship in Germany has resulted in
						a complete cessation of all statistical material on population. It is
						impossible, therefore, to ascertain whether the new policy has resulted in a
						higher birth rate in Germany.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="Netherlands">HOLLAND</place> New birth control clinics were
						opened in <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands">Amsterdam</place> and <place
							reg="Enschede, Netherlands">Enschede</place>, both in industrial
						sections where many factory workers live. This progress took place prior to
						the invasion of Holland. Since then, no news has been received.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="India">INDIA</place> The <org>All-India Women's Conference,</org>
						which met in <place reg="Allahabad, India">Allahabad</place> in January
						1940, adopted a new resolution on family planning which urged that women
						medical officers in municipal and government hospitals, dispensaries and
						health centers advise married women on child spacing, and that the technique
						of contraception be taught these officers.</p>
					<p>The <org reg="India National Planning Commission">National Planning
							Commission</org> appointed by the <org reg="Indian National Congress"
							>National Congress</org> passed a Resolution that family planning and
						limitation of children are essentials in the interest of national economy,
						and urged the state to adopt a policy encouraging the establishment of birth
						control clinics and other necessary measures to encourage the spread of
						cheap and safe methods of birth control.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="Japan">JAPAN</place> Japan's official pressure for a higher birth
						rate during the war has resulted in an increase in the rate of infant
						mortality. Coupled with the demand for an increase in population, as a
						patriotic duty during the war, suppression of birth control clinics and
						discussion of birth control continues.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="New Zealand">NEW ZEALAND</place> The <org>Sex Hygiene and Birth
							Regulation Society of New Zealand</org> dissolved during the year to
						re-form as The <org reg="Family Planning Association of New Zealand">Family
							Planning Association,</org> affiliated with the <org
							reg="Family Planning Association">British organization.</org> A
						deputation of Workers from the Association in conference with the <org
							reg="New Zealand Ministry of Health">Ministry of Health</org> requested
						that contraceptive advice be given by physicians when necessary, at State
						Maternity Hospitals.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>PUERTO RICO With the legality of contraceptive advice, under medical
						direction, established in Puerto Rico by legal decision in 1939, clinic
						services have been established under the supervision of the <org>Puerto Rico
							Board of Health.</org> The <org>Associacion pro Salud Maternal e
							Infantil de Puerto Rico</org>, under the medical direction of <person
							reg="Beleval, Jose S.">Dr. J. S. Beleval,</person> continued its
						educational and research efforts to determine the type of contraceptive best
						adapted for use on the Island. Public interest in the medical and public
						health aspects of birth control were stimulated by a visit from Mrs. Sanger
						in 1940, and the medical films on contraception are being widely shown among
						scientific and medical groups.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="Sweden">SWEDEN</place> The new population measures instituted in
						Sweden which went into effect January 1, 1938, based on the principle that
						voluntary parenthood and a positive population policy must be brought
						together, are now in their second year. This policy emphasizes that only
						children welcome to their parents are wanted by the nation; but also
						recognizes that certain social conditions must be re-arranged that more
						children can be welcomed. Birth control services have been widely extended
						to reach all groups of society, but to reduce the economic motive for
						extreme family regulation, a series of measures involving, not cash premiums
						to parents, but health and environmental services benefiting the children
						themselves have been put into effect. Already skilled laborers and artisans
						in Swedish cities are having more children than the unskilled. It is to be
						hoped that the war will not destroy Sweden's interesting and historic
						experiment.</p>
				</item>
			</list>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">UNITED STATES</head>
			<list>
				<item>
					<p>CLINICS The growth of birth control centers in the United States continued.
						On November 1, 1940 these totalled 589, of which 106 were in hospitals, 178
						in Health Departments, and 305 in other quarters, largely extramural. Of
						these centers, 206 were supported wholly or in part by public funds.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>MEDICAL TEACHING OF CONTRACEPTION The <org>Association of Medical
							Students</org> published, in November, 1939, the results of its
						questionnaire, sent to 77 of the leading medical schools in the United
						States, on the teaching of contraception in these schools. An analysis of
						the replies received showed that (1) there had been a marked increase in the
						teaching of contraception since the survey in 1932; (2) some schools had
						special courses in clinical as well as didactic instruction; (3) general
						student opinion of the training in contraception was that it was grossly
						inadequate; (4) the majority of schools devoted less than six hours to the
						subject.</p>
					<p>The Association of Medical Students, at its Annual Meeting in December, 1939
						adopted a resolution that it "help to promote and increase the teaching of
						contraception in the medical schools, except in those where such teaching
						would be contrary to religious doctrine".</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>HUMAN FERTILITY In January of 1940 the <title type="journal">Journal of
							Contraception,</title> published by the Medical Department of the <org
							reg="Birth Control Federation of America">Birth Control
							Federation,</org> changed its name to <title type="journal">Human
							Fertility</title>, as more truly expressing its contents. It continues
						to bring together for scientists and the medical profession, the current
						developments in the biological and clinical aspects of human reproduction
						and its control.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>FIELD WORK Representatives of the Birth Control Federation of America, Inc.
						cooperating with various health agencies, extended birth control services to
						under-privileged mothers in eleven states not yet ready to undertake
						state-wide programs under their Health Departments. The services were
						medically supervised and simple contraceptives were advised.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>CONFERENCES The Federation cooperated and took part in the <org>Southern
							Conference on Tomorrow's Children</org> in <place reg="Atlanta, GA"
							>Atlanta, Georgia,</place> November, 1939 and in the <org>New England
							Conference for Tomorrow's Children,</org> held in <place
							reg="Boston, MA">Boston, Massachusetts,</place> July, 1940. The
						Federation also participated in the <org>National Conference of Social
							Work;</org> the <place><org reg="Texas State Medical Association"
								>Texas,</org></place>
						<place><org reg="Georgia State Medical Association">Georgia</org></place>
						and <place><org reg="Kentucky State Medical Association"
							>Kentucky</org></place> State Medical Association meetings; <org>the
							American Congress on Obstetrics and Gynecology;</org> and State
						Conferences on Social Work in <place><org
								reg="Pennsylvania State Conference on Social Work"
								>Pennsylvania,</org></place>
						<place><org reg="Tennessee State Conference on Social Work"
							>Tennessee,</org></place>
						<place><org reg="Georgia State Conference on Social Work"
							>Georgia</org></place> and <place><org
								reg="New Jersey State Conference on Social Work">New
							Jersey.</org></place></p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>PUBLIC OPINION Public interest in the movement was evidenced during the year
						by an increased number of articles favorable to birth control published in
						leading magazines--both lay and medical. Among these, a pictorial
						presentation, <title type="journal">LIFE</title> (May 6, 1940) entitled
							<title type="article">"Birth Control: South Carolina uses it for Public
							Health"</title> created wide interest. A <org>Gallup</org> poll taken
						during the year showed that 77% of those expressing opinions favored having
						government health agencies furnish birth control information to married
						women who wanted it.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>U.S. POPULATION POLICIES Wide attention has been given to a report by the
							<org>Population Committee of the National Economic and Social Planning
							Association</org> which advocated "<q who="NESPA">Provision for
							scientific information concerning appropriate methods of contraception
							for all potential parents is an essential measure for sound population
							policy.</q>" The Committee, composed of leading authorities, stated: "<q
							who="NESPA">IT is especially necessary as regards qualitative population
							trends including adequate provisions for child development. It will
							contribute to the more equitable distribution of population in relation
							to economic resources. It is also compatible with population maintenance
							if supplemented by other provisions favorable to voluntary
							reproduction.</q>"</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>SPECIAL NEGRO PROJECT The Federation, through a special grant of funds, has
						established a <org
							reg="Birth Control Federation of America, Division of Negro Service"
							>Division of Negro Service,</org> sponsored by a <org
							reg="Birth Control Federation of America, Natioanl Advosiry Council"
							>National Advisory Council</org> which includes Negro leadership in all
						fields. Two special Demonstration Projects have been established, one in
							<place reg="Nashville, TN">Nashville, Tennessee,</place> and one in
							<place reg="Berkeley County, SC">Berkeley County, South
						Carolina</place>, to study the effects of medically directed contraception
						upon the health and welfare of the Negro populations of these sections. The
						Urban project in Nashville is under the direction of the <org
							reg="Nashville City Health Office">City Health Officers</org> and the
						Rural project will be supervised by the Chairman of the <org
							reg="South Carolina State Medical Association, Committee on Maternal Welfare"
							>Committee on Maternal Welfare</org> of the <org>South Carolina State
							Medical Association.</org></p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>LEGAL ACTION The <org reg="United States Federal Trade Commission">Federal
							Trade Commission</org> was active during the year against false
						therapeutic claims for a number of commercial contraceptives. Cease and
						desist orders were issued against some and suits instituted against others.
						Such government action is welcomed by the organized movement for birth
						control, as a step in regulation of the boot-leg traffic in undependable
						contraceptives.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>Of special interest is the activity of the Federal Trade Commission against
						several concerns attempting to market various devices, slide-rules, etc.
						advertising and representing the theory that the "safe period" or so-called
						"Rhythm" method of birth control is a reliable method of birth control.
						These organizations have filed admissions that according to the weight of
						reliable medical opinion at present no known method of calculating such
						periods can be relied upon to indicate accurately periods of sterility and
						fertility in the menstrual cycle.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>LEGAL DECISIONS: <place reg="Connecticut">CONNECTICUT</place> On March 21,
						1940, the <org reg="Connecticut State Supreme Court of Errors">Supreme Court
							of Errors of the State of Connecticut</org>, by a vote of 3 to 2, handed
						down a decision patterned on that in <place>Massachusetts</place> in 1938.
						The Connecticut decision upheld the existing statute and ruled that under
						it, it was illegal for a physician to prescribe, or a patient to use
						contraceptives, even where definite medical indications existed.</p>
					<p>Connecticut is now one of the only two states in the Union where a doctor is
						forbidden to advise a patient on contraception, and remains the only state
						where the use of contraceptives is illegal.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p><place reg="Iowa">IOWA</place> A decision in a suit brought against a
						druggist in Iowa, in 1937, was handed down by the <org
							reg="Iowa State Supreme Court">Supreme Court of that State</org> in
						1939. The druggist was accused of violating the law by distributing a
						pamphlet entitled "<title type="book">Birth Control</title>". The Court
						ruled him not guilty because the code of laws of the state specifically
						exempts medical schools, physicians and druggists from the provisions of the
						Act governing distribution of contraceptive literature or materials.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>MASSACHUSETTS While previous Court decisions have declared it illegal for a
						physician to give contraceptive information under any conditions, the latest
						decision of the Massachusetts Supreme Court, September 17, by a vote of 3 to
						1, reversed a former ruling and declared a pharmacist not guilty in selling
						certain articles for the prevention of conception because there was no proof
						they were to be used for the prevention of conception. This decision adds to
						the existing legal confusion in Massachusetts, making it possible for
						bootleg traffic in questionable contraceptives to flourish, while legitimate
						medical contraceptive service remains outlawed. An Initiative Petition,
						distributed by the <org>Massachusetts Mothers Health Council</org> to amend
						the statutes involved was filed with over 45,000 signatures, though only
						20,000 were legally required.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>OPPOSITION Opposition to the Birth Control movement, emanating from the
							<org>Roman Catholic Church</org>, continued. In <place>Holyoke,
							Massachusetts,</place> where Mrs. Sanger was scheduled to speak in
						behalf of the Massachusetts Initiative Petition as part of a state-wide tour
						of 10 Massachusetts cities, this opposition culminated in pressure brought
						to bear against directors of the <org>Congregational Church</org> to
						withdraw permission, previously extended to Mrs. Sanger, to speak from its
						platform. The same opposition resulted in inability to rent any other public
						hall. The meeting was finally held in the quarters of the local textile
						Union.</p>
				</item>
				<item>
					<p>STATE BIRTH CONTROL FEDERATIONS There are now 33 organized state birth
						control organizations cooperating with the Birth Control Federation. <person
							reg="Rose, D. Kenneth">D. Kenneth Rose</person> became Executive Vice
						President of the Federation in 1940, and <person reg="Morris, Woodbridge E."
							>Woodbridge E. Morris</person>, M.D., former Director of the <org
							reg="Delaware State Board of Health, Division of Maternal and Child Health"
							>Division of Maternal and Child Health of the Delaware State Board of
							Health</org> became General Medical Director.</p>
				</item>
			</list>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
