<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/12/05 SC encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-12-19 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-22 CH enter tag corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-10 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-10 CH clean up docs title</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-17 CH enter proofreading corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-11-05 EK update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1924-01-10"><supplied resp="MSPP">10 Jan 1924</supplied></docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">American Birth Control League Meeting Speech Notes</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236407</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection</bibl>
			<bibl>
				<title type="mf">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>
				S70:1060</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TWAMAR">Twain, Mark</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger likely used these speech notes when she made the opening address at the Second
			Annual Meeting of the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, held in <place
				reg="New York, NY">New York</place>. Other speakers included <person
				reg="Ackermann, Frances B.">Frances B. Ackermann</person>, <person
				reg="Kennedy, Anne">Anne Kennedy</person>, and <person reg="Porritt, Annie Goodrich"
				>Annie Goodrich Porritt</person></p>
		<index level1="American Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p>I wonder how many of you here tonight realize just how much <add><unclear resp="MSPP"
					>significance</unclear></add> this gathering <del>means</del> is. How many of
			you realize that this meeting of intelligent representative citizens brought together by
			an interest in birth <del>means</del>
			<add>control</add> represents ten years of struggle and effort. Ten years! Ten years of
			battling against ignorance &amp; prejudice--&amp; a ten year fight <add>for the
				right</add> to get people to talk &amp; to think about the greatest problems that
			confront the human race.</p>
		<p>For there are few subjects which have so large a practical significance and at the same
			time cut so deeply into the foundation of social evolution as Birth Control. There are
			few other questions of equal importance left so long in equal obscurity &amp; yet none
			perhaps which can show so unequalled a leap in our social vista as birth control has
			done in so brief a period of time.</p>
		<p><add>Ten years ago to utter the words b.c. was a crime.</add> The fundamental reason for
			such interest are two:</p>
		<p>That Civilization is confronted with two serious problems. <list>
				<item>1 That of the pressure of <supplied resp="MSPP">population</supplied> upon the
					food supply. </item>
				<item>2 &amp; That of reconciling <supplied resp="MSPP">Humanitarianism</supplied>
					with race improvement.</item>
			</list>
		</p>
		<p>Many of us believe that birth control is the key to them both.</p>
		<p>Mark Twain said: "<q who="TWAMA">everybody talks about the weather but no one ever seems
				to do anything about it</q>"--</p>
		<p>Well--the <org reg="American Birth Control League">American B.C League</org> is doing
			something about these problems.</p>
		<p>We know that words, theories, sentiment, sympathy are all very well in themselves but we
			have got to have intelligent thinking put into intelligent action.</p>
		<p>If the program for birth control is to grow, to expand, if it is even to hold the ground
			it has gained through untold sacrifice &amp; seemingly hopeless effort, we must have
				<supplied resp="MSPP">cooperation</supplied> courageous, active cooperation of
			individuals &amp; organizations who <del>believe</del> accept the truth of birth control
			but do nothing about it. We need more English courage in American <add>intellectual
				life</add>.</p>
		<p>We need the kind of intellectual courage such as <person reg="Inge, William Ralph">Dean
				Inge</person>, <person reg="Shaw, George Bernard">Bernard Shaw</person>, <person
				reg="Wells, H. G.">Wells</person>, <person reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard
				Keynes</person>, <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand E.">Lord Dawson</person> the Kings
				physician<del>, have shown a personal conviction publicly expressed</del>. </p>
		<p>These men have had the courage to express their private convictions, publicly, nor have
			they lost in the estimation of the British public by doing so--</p>
		<p>The ABCL. is calling for the cooperation of the medical <supplied resp="MSPP"
				>profession</supplied> for scientific research, for investigation for unbiased
			study.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
