<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Autograph draft speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-24 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-30 MC enter corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1941-10-01">1 Oct 1941</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Ulster County Planned Parenthood
					League</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp236565</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="MS">Margaret Sanger Microfilm, Smith College Collections</title>,
				S72:279</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="article">Parenthood Group Hears Mrs. Sanger</title>, <title
					type="journal">Kingston Daily Freeman</title>, Oct. 3, 1941</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
			<name id="KDF">Kingston Daily Freeman</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger addressed the <org>Ulster County Committee on Planned Parenthood</org> at the
				<org>Nurses Home</org> of <org>Kingston Hospital</org>. She was introduced by Judge
				<person reg="de la Vergne, Charles">Charles de la Vergne</person> and followed by
			Dr. <person reg="Moore, Elizabeth">Elizabeth Moore</person>, who discussed local work
			done at the <org>Kingston Maternal Health Clinic</org>. Additional quotes were taken
			from news coverage.</p>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="need for"/>
		<index level1="New York" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="family size" level2="and poverty"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<div type="section">
			<dateline>
				<place reg="Kingston, NY">Kingston</place>
				<lb/>
				<date value="1941-10-01">Oct 1 1941</date>
			</dateline>
			<p><person reg="Hugo, Victor">Victor Hugo</person>--or Junior Story. There is no subject
				that has so large a practical significance which cuts so deeply--social evolution as
				Bc. </p>
			<p>No other subject of equal importance--equal obscurity 20 years Bc keynote of a New
				Social awakening. It is not only a health economic expedient social principle
				interlocked with the advance of a civilization +amp; her nation's future.</p>
			<p>Bc conscious control of birth rate prevent conception of life.</p>
			<p> Prevent, control conscious.</p>
			<p>Why--Three of every four essential factors in bringing a child into the worl.
				Mother's health, father's earning powers,standards of living +amp; heritage of body
				+amp; mind. </p>
			<p><org reg="United States Children's Bureau">Children's Bureau</org>--<person
					reg="Parran, Thomas, Jr.">Surgeon Gen Dr Parran</person>. 1937 60% babes born,
				increases 15.00 +amp; less 1938 50% babes born, increases 15.00 + less. </p>
			<p> Larges families--poverty--illiteracy ignorance slum child labor--maternal deaths
				infant deaths, juvenile courts social problems. Small families spacing children 2 or
				4 to develop potential talents civic leaders trade schools +amp; colleges personal
				but not social responsibility no quarrel with this group. </p>

			<p>Before we attempt to increase from this group. Cut down on inmates of institutions
				feebleminded </p>
			<p>Private Drs or refusal to Poor Mothers</p>
			<p><org>Gallup Poll</org> 77% American people wish to see Bc as part of Public Health
				Programs. </p>
			<p> Dr Parran Report.</p>
			<list>
				<item>1,000,000 mothers gave birth +amp; no after care</item>
				<item>The babes born +amp; mother's struggle to survive</item>
				<item>60,000 infants die in 2 <unclear resp="MSPP">weeks</unclear></item>
				<item>78,000 stillborn </item>
				<item> 150,000 mothers +amp; infants die each year</item>
				<item>68% die needlessly </item>
				<item>25% or 1/4 of mothers conditions known before pregnancy occurred.</item>
			</list>
			<p>Infant mortality is still high. </p>
			<p>
				<list>
					<item>3 factors</item>
					<item>father wage--</item>
					<item>spacing--2 to 3 years.</item>
					<item>place in family</item>
				</list>
			</p>

			<p>
				<list>
					<item>1 year apart 149 per 1000 births </item>
					<item>2 year apart 98 per 1000 births</item>
					<item>3 year apart 86 per 1000 births</item>
				</list>
			</p>
			<p>Dr Parran's report that 1/3 of our people are poorly <emph rend="underline"
					>clothed</emph>, <emph rend="underline">housed</emph>, and <emph
					rend="underline">fed</emph>. <unclear resp="MSPP" reason="illegible"
					>[Just]</unclear> the people who are kept in ignorance +amp; forced to bring
				children to birth regardless of circumstances.</p>
			<p>Danger Spots <place>Italy</place>, <place>Germany</place> +amp;
				<place>Japan</place></p>
			<p>In a Democratic Society where the vote of one is as good as that of another it is a
				dangerous procedure to accept a way of life where the poorest, most ignorant +amp;
				diseased as well as the mentally +amp; socially unfit maintain +amp; increase the
				stock of the population.</p>
			<p>Poverty +amp; ignorance seem <add>to be the factors to</add> stimulate a high birth
				rate. We can +amp; must abolish these factors as part of a Sound Population
				Policy.</p>
			<p>Not only health but social +amp; political factors enter into this subject. </p>
			<p>6,000,000 persons under 21 years of age are subnormal.</p>
			<p>5,000,000 can not pass beyond the 4th grades in our public school.</p>
			<p>Is <place reg="United States">America</place> Safe for Democracy? </p>
			<p>Who supports this army of people who are unfit to compete in the struggle for
				life!</p>
			<p>Not only the monetary costs <del>but the</del> to cause alarm--but the keeping alive
				+amp; allowing the increase of this stratum of our population who contribute nothing
				+amp; only use up the energies +amp; resources of the world.</p>
			<p>There are 7 conditions where birth control should be used. <list>
					<item>Qualified Drs to advise--best methods.</item>
					<item>680 Clinics in U.S.A.</item>
					<item>Legal <place reg="New York">N.Y. State </place> +amp; Federal.</item>
					<item>Public Health for poor.</item>
					<item>Kingston</item>
				</list></p>
			<p>
				<org reg="United States Department of Agriculture">USA Dept. of Agriculture</org>
			</p>
			<p>Pigs -- cows -- chickens -- USA <unclear resp="MSPP" reason="illegible"
					>Arizona</unclear> 18 acres. 1 head cattle. Increased 25 million in 20 years. </p>
			<list>
				<item>100 <unclear resp="MSPP" reason="illegible">acres</unclear> 200 people
					bread</item>
				<item>100 <unclear resp="MSPP" reason="illegible">acres</unclear> 40 people
					milk</item>
				<item>100 <unclear resp="MSPP" reason="illegible">acres</unclear> 9 people
					meat</item>
			</list>
			<p>Cereals feed 90% people in the world. </p>
			<p>3 acres to feed adult in USA.</p>
			<p>132 million in USA 1940.</p>
			<p>20 million unemployed up to the a few years ago.</p>
			<p>9 million on relief.</p>
			<p>Labor saving machinery will be a blessing to mankind if it goes hand in hand with a
				controlled birth rate.</p>
			<p>Only labor power to sell.</p>
			<p><person reg="Huxley, Julian">Julian Huxley</person> Bc will go down in the records of
				history as one of the greatest achievements of civilization--inventing of stone <gap
					extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> licensing of electricity art of Printing
				Press. </p>
			<p/>
		</div>

		<div>
			<head>Parenthood Group Hears Mrs. Sanger</head>
			<p>
				<q who="KDF">The speaker said in part,</q> "It had been said by an expert at the
				peace conference following the last World War that until a study and an attempt was
				made to control the quantity and quality of the population in regard to the natural
				resources of the world that there would be another war in 25 years. This prediction
				has come true. Until the density of population is solved in Germany, Japan,and
				Italy, they will always be potential danger spots. It is of little use to control
				armaments and not control population." </p>
			<p>"This is of even greater consequence in America if democracy is to survive. When
				there are 21 million of the population of the United States who are subnormal and 5
				million who are incapable of going beyond the 4th grade in school, but whose vote is
				as good as a college professors, there is a grave threat to democracy, since
				subnormal mentality can be transmitted." </p>
			<p><q who="KDF">She also said,</q> "The loss in this country of one of the greatest
				wealths was tremendous: 150,000 mothers are lost every year, 60% unnecessarily and
				25% needlessly because of their pre-natal condition was unknown. This is an
				irreparable loss and is the very weak spot in our otherwise splendid Public Health
				set-up. The shocking result of this weakness is on the shoulders of public
				officials. It is gradually being corrected and <org
					reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org> has
				already been made a part of the public health programs of three states: <place>North
					Carolina</place>, <place>South Carolina</place>, and <place>Alabama</place>."
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
