<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/12/18 JK encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-13 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-18 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1933-00-00">1933</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control, 1932</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp321976</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Social Work Yearbook</title> Vol. 2, (New
				York: Russell Sage Foundation: 1933), pp. 40-42</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="PHRC">Public Health Relations Committee</name>
			<name id="CCAR">Central Conference of American Rabbis</name>
			<name id="AUA">American Unitarian Association</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For an earlier entry in the same series, see "<xref from="156569.xml"
				>Birth Control, 1928</xref>."</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="birth control leagues"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="birth control leagues"
			level3="Birth Control League of New York"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="birth control leagues"
			level3="National Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation"
			level3="New York "/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="conferences"
			level2="White House Conference on Child health and Protection"
			level3="1930"/>
		<index
			level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="public health programs"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head> Birth Control 1933</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>The general aim of the birth control movement is to legalize the
				practice of contraception through scientific and hygienic
				methods, and to educate the public to its advantages as a health
				and economic expedient. Though the movement had its origin in
				England, it was in 1914 in <place reg="New York, NY">New York
					City</place> that Mrs. Margaret Sanger first coined the term
				“birth control” and challenged the federal laws by advocating
				birth control on feministic and economic grounds. There followed
				in 1917 the publication of the <title type="journal">Birth
					Control Review</title>, the formation of the <org>Voluntary
					Parenthood League</org> in 1919, and the organization in
				1921 of the <org>American Birth Control League</org>.</p>
			<p> The period from 1914 to 1921 was one of agitation, education,
				organization, and legislation. The <org>National Committee on
					Maternal Health</org>, organized in 1923, has for its
				purpose the scientific investigation of contraception,
				sterilization, and the general problems of sterility and
				fertility from the point of view of the practice of medicine and
				public health. In 1923 also the <org>Birth Control Clinical
					Research Bureau</org> was established in New York City. That
				Bureau--with which a large number of social and welfare agencies
				and hospitals are cooperating has instructed over 31,000 women
				since its organization. The first 10,000 case histories, under a
				grant from the <org>Bureau of Social Hygiene</org>, have been
				analyzed by a committee of specialists and the results are to be
				made available at a later date.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Legislative Campaigns, and Birth Control
				Clinics</head>
			<p>While efforts are being constantly made for needed legislation in
				the several states, the attention of leaders in the field has
				recently been centered more particularly upon obtaining federal
				legislation. For this purpose the <org>National Committee on
					Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org> was organized in
				1929. Federal laws forbidding the distribution of contraceptive
				information affect the use of the mails and common carriers, and
				impose a penalty of $5,000, or imprisonment for five years or
				both, on anyone who is convicted of a violation. In many states
				a physician may give oral contraceptive information to his
				patients, but scientific literature on the subject, or medical
				supplies for the purpose, cannot be legally sent to him through
				the <place>United States</place> mails, nor can he knowingly
				receive them without violating the law. Amendments to remedy
				this situation are now pending in <org
					reg="United States Congress">Congress</org>.</p>
			<p> At the present time not less than 100 so-called birth control
				clinics- through some of them, located in hospitals, are not
				generally known as such- are operating legally in the United
				States (covering 43 cities in 17 states). They are all places
				where contraceptive information may be obtained, but only under
				conditions within the limitation of the laws of each particular
				state. In <place>New York</place> State, for example,
				information can be given for the “cure or prevention of
				disease,” but not for economic reasons. In the Harlem section of
				New York City, through a grant from the <org>Julius Rosenwald
					Fund</org>, a branch clinic for colored women has been
				established as a part of the work of the Birth Control Clinical
				Research Bureau. A comprehensive study of the work and location
				of birth control clinics in different cities is contained in
					<title type="book">Seventy Birth Control Clinics</title>
				(infra cit.), issued in 1930. The latest information as to the
				location of such clinics may be obtained from the National
				Committee on Maternal Health.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">The Movement Endorsed and Opposed</head>
			<p>In recent years public opinion has been rapidly growing in favor
				of medically supervised instruction on birth control, as
				evidenced by the support and endorsements given by medical and
				other groups since 1930. Conspicuous among the former were the
					<org
					reg="New York Academy of Medicine, Public Health Relations Committee"
					>Public Health Relations Committee</org> of the <org>New
					York Academy of Medicine</org>. Its recommendations, adopted
				in 1931, included the following statement: <q who="PHRC">“A
					movement should be begun to include, in the curriculum of
					medical schools, instruction in modern contraceptive
					measures and in the indications therefor. The hospital
					clinics should likewise be asked to offer similar
					instruction to practicing physicians.” </q>At the <org>White
					House Conference on Child Health and Protection</org> in
				1930 a similar recommendation was made by the Sub-committee of
				the Section on Obstetric Teaching and Education of Physicians,
				Nurses, Midwives, Social Workers, and Laity. </p>
			<p>Many religious groups have recently made public statement
				favorable to the birth control movement, at least to the extent
				of recognizing that existing laws should be modified which
				prevent physicians from imparting information concerning the use
				of contraceptives to those entitled to receive it. Among the
				groups which have issued such statements are the following: the
				Committee on Marriage and the Home of the <org>Federal Council
					of the Churches of Christ in America</org>; <org>General
					Council of the Congregational and Christian
					Churches</org>;<org
					reg="Methodist Episcopal Church, New York East Conference">
					New York East Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church</org>;
					<org>Universalist General Convention</org>; and numerous
				political, lay, and social welfare organizations. In addition,
				the <org>Central Conference of American Rabbis</org> in 1929
				urged "<q who="CCAR">the recognition of the importance of the
					control of parenthood as one of the methods of coping with
					social problems</q>"; and the <org>American Unitarian
					Association</org> in 1930 recommended that its constituents
				consider the subject “<q who="AUA">to the end that they may
					support all reasonable efforts in their communities for the
					promotion of the birth control movement.</q>” For the text
				of the statements by the specified organizations see Information
				Service (infra cit.) and <title type="book">The Gospel and the
					Family and Youth</title> (General Council of the
				Congregational and Christian Churches), 1931. In July, 1930, the
					<org reg="United Kingdom Ministry of Health">English
					Ministry of Health</org> issued a memorandum stating that in
				response to a widespread responsible demand, public health
				authorities would be authorized to give birth control
				information in the maternal and infant welfare centers of which
				there are several thousand throughout the <place
					reg="Great Britain">British Isles</place>. This announcement
				was preceded by a favorable, though guarded, pronouncement by
				the <org reg="United Kingdom House of Lords">House of
					Lords</org>, the <org>Lambeth Conference of Bishops</org>,
				and the <org reg="British Medical Association">British Medical Society</org>. </p>
			<p>The principal organized opposition to the movement comes from the
					<org>Roman Catholic Church</org>, and since the publication
				of the Encyclical Letter of <person reg="Pius XI (Pope)">Pope
					Pius XI</person>, <title type="article">On Christian
					Marriage</title>, 1931, many Catholic organizations-
				including the <org>National Council of Catholic Men</org>, the
					<org>International Federation of Catholic Alumni</org>, and
				the <org>National Council of Catholic Women</org>--have
				registered formal protests against the passage of birth control
				legislation. It is safe to say that all Catholic organizations
				are similarly opposed. The <org>United Lutheran Church of
					America</org>, <org>Evangelical Lutheran Augusta
				Synod</org>, <org>Lord’s Day Alliance</org>, and a small number
				of local religious denominations are also reported as opposed to
				the pending birth control legislation. </p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
