<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2009/03/20 ch Initial transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-13 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-04 ch clean index</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-05 CH clean up index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1930-11-00">Nov 1930</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Shall We Have Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp400300</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Estes' Back to Nature Magazine</title>, Nov. 1930, pp. 4,
				26, and 30</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="WHITJW">Williams, J. Whitbridge</name>
			<name id="EDETH">Eden, Thomas Watts</name>
			<name id="EBTN">Estes' Back to Nature</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>An editorial box indicates the importance of the topic of birth control and notes that
				<title type="journal">Back to Nature</title> will open a series including "all the
			different views on the subject," beginning with Margaret Sanger.</p>
		<p>The article was previously published in <title type="journal">American Medicine</title>,
			Mar. 1920, and as Chapter XVI of <title type="book">Woman and the New Race</title>, (New
			York: Brentano's, 1920), pp. 198-209.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="health risks"/>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="Australia" level2="birth rates in"/>
		<index level1="Netherlands, the" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
		<index level1="physicians" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="socioeconomic benefits of"/>
		<index level1="Germany" level2="birth rate in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Shall We Have BIRTH CONTROL</head>
		<head type="sub"> Why Not Birth-Control Clinics in America?</head>
		<byline>By Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p>"The absurd cruelty of permitting thousands of women every year to go through abortions
			to prevent the aggravation of diseases for which they are under treatment assuredly
			cannot be much longer ignored by the medical profession," <q who="EBTN">said Mrs.
				Sanger.</q> "Responsibility for the inestimable damage done by the practice of
			permitting patients suffering from certain ailments to become pregnant, because of their
			ignorance of contraceptives, when the physician knows that if pregnancy goes to its full
			term it will hasten the disease and lead to the patient's death, must in all fairness be
			laid at his door. </p>
		<p>What these diseases are and what dangers are involved in pregnancy are known to every
			practitioner of standing. Specialists have not been negligent in pointing out the
			situation. Eager to enhance or protect their reputations in the profession, they
			continually call out to one another: "Don't let the patient bear a child--don't let
			pregnancy continue."</p>
		<p>The warning has been sounded most often, perhaps, in the cases of tubercular women.</p>
		<p>"<q who="WHIJW">In view of the fact that the tubercular process becomes exacerbated
				either during pregnancy or after child-birth, most authorities recommend that
				abortion be induced as a matter of routine in all tubercular women,</q>" says Dr.
				<person reg="Williams, J. Whitridge">J. Whitridge Williams</person>,
			obstetrician-in-chief to the <org reg="Johns Hopkins University Hospital">Johns Hopkins
				Hospital</org>, in his treaties on Obstetrics. Dr. <person reg="Eden, Thomas Watts"
				>Thomas Watts Eden</person>, obstetrician and gynecologist to <org>Charing Cross
				Hospital</org> and member of the staffs of other notable British hospitals, extends
			but doesn't complete the list in this paragraph on page 652 of his <title>Practical
				Obstetrics</title>: "<q who="EDETH">Certain of the conditions enumerated form
				absolute indications for the induction of abortion. These are nephritis,
				uncompensated valvular lesions of the heart, advanced tuberculosis, insanity,
				irremediable malignant tumors, hydatidiform mole, uncontrollable uterine hemorrhage,
				and actute hydramnios.</q>"</p>
		<p>We know that abortion, when performed by skilled hands, under right conditions, brings
			almost no danger to the life of the patient, and we also know that particular diseases
			can be more easily combated after such an abortion than during a pregnancy allowed to
			come to full term. But why not adopt the easier, safer, less repulsive course, and
			prevent conception altogether? Why put thousands of women who undergo such abortions to
			the pain and danger they endure?</p>
		<p>Why continue to send home women to whom pregnancy is a grave danger with the futile
			advice: "Now don't get this way again!" They are sent back to husbands who have
			generations of passion and passion's claim to outlet. They are being sent back without
			being given information as to how to prevent the dangerous pregnancy and are expected,
			presumably, to depend for their safety upon the husband's continence. The wife and
			husband are thrown together to bring about once more the same condition. Back comes the
			patient again in a few months to be aborted and told once more not to do it again.</p>
		<p>Does any physician believe the picture is overdrawn? I have known of many such cases. A
			recent one that came under my observation was that of a woman who suffered from a
			disease of the kidneys. Five times she was taken to a maternity hospital in an ambulance
			after falling in offices or in the street. One of the foremost gynecologists of America
			sent her out three times without giving her information as to the contraceptive means
			which would have prevented a repetition of this experience. </p>
		<p>Why does this situation exist? We do not question the good intent nor the high purposes
			of these physicians. We know that they observe a high standard of ethics and that they
			are working for the uplift of the race. But here is a situation that is absurd,
			hideously absurd. What is the matter?</p>
		<p>Several factors contribute to this state of affairs. First, the subject of contraception
			has been kept in the dark, even in medical colleges and in hospitals. Abortion has been
			openly discussed as a necessity under certain conditions, but the subject of
			contraception, as any physician will admit, has not yet been brought to the front. It
			has escaped specialized attention in the laboratories and the research departments. Thus
			there has been no professional stamp of approval by great bodies of experimenters. The
			result is that the average physician has felt that contraceptive methods are not yet
			established as certainties and has, for that reason, refused to direct their use.</p>
		<p>Consultation rooms in charge of reputable physicians who have specialized in
			contraception, assisted by registered nurses--in a word, clinics designed for this
			specialty--would meet this crying need. Such clinics should deal with each woman
			individually, taking into account her particular disease, her temperament, her mentality
			and her condition, both physical and economic. Their sole function would be to prevent
			pregnancy. In accomplishing this purpose, a higher standard of hygiene is attained. Not
			only would a burden be removed from the physician who sends a woman to such a clinic,
			but there would be an improvement in the woman's general condition which would in a
			number of ways reflect itself in benefit to her family.</p>
		<p>All this for the diseased woman. But every argument that can be made for preventive
			medicine can be made for birth control clinics for the use of the woman who has not yet
			lost her health. Sound and vigorous at the time of her marriage, she could remain so if
			given advice as to by what means she could space her children and limit their number.
			When she is not given such information, she is plunged blindly into married life, and a
			few years is likely to find her with a large family, herself diseased and damaged, an
			unfit breeder of the unfit, and still ignorant! </p>
		<p>What are the fruits of this woeful ignorance in which women have been kept? First, a
			tremendous infant mortality--hundreds of thousands of babies dying annually of diseases
			which flourish in poverty and neglect.</p>
		<p>Next, the rapid increase of the feeble-minded, of criminal types, and of the pathetic
			victims of toil in the child-labor factories. Another result is the familiar
			overcrowding of tenements, the forcing of children into the street, the ensuing
			prostitution, alcoholism and almost universal physical and moral unfitness.</p>
		<p>Those abhorrent conditions point to a blunder upon the part of those to whom we have
			intrusted the care of the health of the individual, the family and the race. The medical
			profession, neglecting the principle involved in preventive medicine, has permitted
			these conditional to come about. </p>
		<p>In <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, for instance, where the information
			concerning contraceptives has been accessible to the people, through clinics and
			pamphlets, since 1881, the general death rate and the infant mortality rate have fallen
			until they are the lowest in <place>Europe</place>. <place reg="Amsterdam, Netherlands"
				>Amsterdam</place> and <place reg="The Hague, Netherlands">The Hague</place> have
			the lowest infant mortality rates of any cities in the world. </p>
		<p>It is good to know that the first of the birth-control clinics of Holland followed
			shortly after a thorough and enthusiastic discussion of the subject at an international
			medical cognress in Amsterdam in 1878. The <org reg="Nieuw Malthusiaansche Bond">Dutch
				Neo-Malthusian League</org> was founded in 1881. The first birth-control clinic in
			the world was opened in 1885 by Dr. <name reg="Jacobs, Aletta">Aletta Jacobs</name> in
			Amsterdam. So great were the results obtained that there has been a remarkable increase
			in the wealth, stamina, stature and longevity of the people, as well as a gradual
			increase in the population.</p>
		<p>These clinics must not be confused with the white enameled rooms which we associate with
			the term in <place reg="United States">America</place>. They are ordinary offices with
			the necessary equipment, or rooms in the homes of the nurses, fitted out for the work.
			They are places for consultation and examination, opened by specially trainied nurses
			who have been instructed by Dr. <person reg="Rutgers, Johannes">J. Rutgers</person>, of
			The Hague, secretary of the Neo-Malthusian League, who has devoted his life to this
			work. There have been more than fifty nurses trained specially for the work by Dr.
			Rutgers. As a nurse completes her course of training, she establishes herself in a
			community and her place of consultation is called a clinic. </p>
		<p>The general results of this service are best judged by tables included in the <title
				type="book"
				reg="Annual Report of the Registrar General of Births, Deaths, and Marriages In England and Wales"
				>Annual Summary of Marriages, Births and Deaths in England, Wales</title>, etc., for
			1912.</p>
		<p>In Amsterdam, the birth rate dropped from 37.1 for the period of 1881-'85 to 24.7 for
			1906, and 23.3 in 1912. During the same periods, the death rate fell from 25.1 to 13.1,
			and in 1912, to 11.2. Infant mortality for the same period fell from 203 for each
			thousand living births to 901, and in 1912 to 64. Illegitimate fertility also decreased.
			Results in other cities, as shown by the table at the end of this chapter, are exactly
			similar.</p>
		<p>In the <place reg="Australia">Australian Commonwealth</place>, where birth control is
			taken as a matter of course, and information concerning contraceptives is available to
			all the masses, the births were so well distributed in 1915 that while the birth rate
			was 27.3, there was a general death rate of only 10.7. <place>New Zealand</place>, which
			is also one of the typical birth-control countries, had a birth rate of 25.3 and a
			general death date of only 9.1 for the same year. These figures are in marked and happy
			contrast with those for the birth registration of the United States, where the reports
			for 1916 show a birth rate of 24.8, but an infant death rate of 14.7. A similar
			comparison may be made with the <place reg="Germany">German Empire</place> in 1913,
			where there was a birth rate of 27.5 in 1913 and a mortality rate of 15. In these
			countries, birth-control information is not so generally within the reach of the masses
			and, consequently, the largest percentage of births come to that class least able to
			bring children to full maturity, as indicated in the mortality rates. </p>
		<p>In conclusion, I am going to make a statement which may at first seem exaggerated, but
			which is, nevertheless, carefully considered. The effort toward racial progress that is
			being made today by the medical profession, by social workers, by the various charitable
			and philanthropic organizations, and by state institutions for the physically and
			mentally unfit, is practically wasted. All these forces are in a very emphatic sense
			marking time. They will continue to mark time until the medical profession recognizes
			the fact that the ever increasing tide of the unfit is overwhelming all that these
			agencies are doing for society. They will continue to mark time until they get at the
			source of these destructive condition and apply a fundamental remedy. That remedy is
			birth control. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
