<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/11/04 YG</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-27 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1935-08-20">20 Aug 1935</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Archbishop John Gregory Murray's
					Dictate</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421066</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Corrects Birth Control Critic</title>, <title
					type="journal">New York Herald Tribune</title>, Aug. 20, 1935 </bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NYHT">New York Herald Tribune</name>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p> For related statements, see Statement on Archbishop John
			Gregory Murray, <xref from="421928.xml">Aug. 19, 1935</xref> and <xref from="421067.xml">Oct. 1935</xref>.</p>
		<index level1="Catholic Church"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="freedom of speech and"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Corrects Birth Control Critic</head>

		<p>
			<q who="NYHT">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth control leader, drew a sharp distinction
				between abortion an[d] contraception in replying today to the edict of Archbishop
					<person reg="Murray, John Gregory">John Gregory Murray</person> of <place
					reg="St. Paul, MN">St. Paul</place> directing Roman Catholics under his
				jurisdiction to hold aloof from all organizations advocating birth control. The
				archbishop likened birth control advocates to the “<person
					reg="Dillinger, John Herbert">Dillinger</person>mob,” saying that both were
				organized for murder.</q>
		</p>
		<p> “Personal opinions matter little,” <q who="NYHT">Mrs. Sanger said in her statement
				today, </q>“however much one may regret the ignorance and misinformation behind
			them. But when such opinions appear in the public press and create confusion and
			misunderstanding, it becomes a public duty to challenge them. </p>
		<p>“The crux of the matter is that abortion is one thing and birth control is something
			totally different. Abortion destroys life. It kills the unborn child. It is a terrible
			and tragic thwarting of nature and one which takes its toll in ill health, in sterility
			and in women’s lives. Birth control, as the medical term contraception implies, prevents
			contraception. You cannot destroy what does not exist. You cannot use birth control and
			abortion as interchangeable terms. To do so is to misrepresent the facts.” </p>
		<p>
			<q who="NYHT">Birth control is one of the chief ways in which abortions and the maternal
				deaths resulting from them can be checked, she insisted.</q>
		</p>

		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
