<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-02-06 JC encoding</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-06 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-17 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Crisler, R. R.">R. R. Crisler</person></docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1931-05-14">14 May 1931</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Debate with Judge Richard B. Russell</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421043</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Given Verdict At Debate Over Birth
					Contol</title>, <title type="journal">Atlanta Constitution</title>, May 15,
				1931, p. 1 and <title type="article">Jurist, Father of 18, Debates Birth
					Control</title>, <title type="journal">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, May 15,
				1931, p. 8</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="RUSRI">Russell, Richard B.</name>
			<name id="BIB">Bible</name>
			<name id="AC">Atlanta Constitution</name>
			<name id="CDT">Chicago Daily Tribune</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger's debate text was not found; excerpts were taken from press coverage.</p>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
		<index level1="family size"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Given Verdict At Debate Over Birth Control</head>
		<byline>by R. R. Crisler</byline>
		<div>
			
			<p> <q who="AC">Margaret Sanger, the mother of three children, met Chief Justice <person
						reg="Russell, Richard B.">Richard B. Russell</person>, the father of 18, in
					a debate on birth control Thursday night at the <org reg="Erlanger Theater"
						>Erlanger theater</org>. And the result--while it seemed to be pretty
					decisively in favor of the lady (as the gallant chief justice himself would be
					the last to deny) at the same time completely justified everybody’s expectations
					with regard to the gentleman. If he went down, under the onslaught of these new
					and somewhat bewildering ideas, he went--like the noble old Roman he is--with
					the standards of the legion intact. </q></p>
			
			<p>
				<q who="AC">Mrs. Sanger was first in the field, trotting out her light cavalry of
					statistics, her portable and compact artillery of logic and of modern ideas. And
					like a good strategist, she had not failed to provide her forced with an
					inexhaustible commissary of information. The old Roman, whose eloquence played
					no small part in winning him the place of honor on <place>Georgia</place>’s
					supreme court bench, must have realized that here was a different and somewhat
					disconcerting antagonist to deal with.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AC">>But the lady’s opening speech was merely a ruse; merely a skilled
					maneuver to draw the enemy out: for she is the sort of fighter who must have
					something definite to strike at: and there was a very clever little ambush
					prepared!</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AC">The enemy marched into it, too, with trumpets blowing and flags whipping
					spectacularly in the breeze. It was the Roman phalanx going grandly and
					unsuspectingly into a nest of machine guns. Taking his text from the Scriptures,
					Chief Justice Russell reminded his opponent of the Biblical injunction to
						<person reg="Noah (Biblical)">Noah</person>, <q who="BIB">“increase and multiply.”</q></q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AC">“Rat, tat, tat,” the machine guns, in rebuttal, spat like so many
					snakes.</q> “And it might be opportune to remind my opponent,” <q who="AC">Mrs. Sanger
					parried,</q> “that when <name type="deity">God</name> laid this command upon
				Noah, there were only five people on Earth. My opponent must admit that the
				situation has altered a little since then.” </p>
			<p>
				<q who="AC">But people, the phalanx contended, are motivated by pure selfishness
					when they refuse to have children. In glowing words he painted the picture of a
					happy family group- the more numerous the better--with the mother and father
					actuated by feelings of self-sacrifice, willing to bear the pains and economic
					tribulations of life as well as its merely sensual pleasures. Once more the
					machine guns spat.</q> “I love,” <q who="AC">Mrs. Sanger remarked, laconically,
				</q>“to hear men talk about the pain and sacrifice entailed by childbirth! They have
				so much first hand knowledge.” </p>
			<p>
				<q who="AC">It was too much for the phalanx. Placed so unceremoniously outside the
					pale, he was obliged to waste a perfectly good rebuttal in a tribute to
					womanhood, just to offset any possible misunderstanding. By a ruse, the lady had
					forced the chief justice to forsake his cause in order to defend himself. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AC">The question at issue in the debate, whether or not the mails should be
					open to birth control information, was not always strictly adhered to by the
					debaters, for in spite of everything one can do the question of birth control
					always remains a broader one than that. It was the importance of birth control
					to the individual family that Mrs. Sanger stressed, the fact that it lowers
					infant mortality, increases the happiness and health of woman, and effectually
					prevents the economic disasters which threaten the large family with a small
					income.</q> “It is for us to choose,”<q who="AC"> she asserted,</q> “a decreased birth rate or
				an increased death rate.”</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AC">Judge Russell, on the other hand, would lump all birth controllers into
					the same class with communists, bolsheviks, and infidels. His most pronounced
					antipathy, however, is for those who profess the doctrine; he admitted that its
					practice if common.</q><q who="RUSRI"> “Otherwise," </q><q who="AC">he added,</q> <q who="RUSRI"
					>“how does it happen that Georgia has lost two congressmen?” </q><q who="AC">The
					audience, highly appreciative of the witticisms with which Judge Russell’s
					remarks had been so generously interlarded, seemed to regard this as one of them
					and burst into laughter.</q><q who="RUSRI"> “But maybe you won’t miss them,”
					</q><q who="AC">he said, good-humoredly. There was a round of applause and more
					laughter. It looked as though the audience really wouldn’t---indiscernible.
				</q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>Jurist, Father of 18, Debates Birth Control </head>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Richard B. Russell, chief justice of the <org>Georgia Supreme
						Court</org>, engaged in debate tonight with Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth
					control advocate.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">The jurist, father of 18 children, whose son, <person
						reg="Russell, Jr., Richard B.">Richard B. Russell Jr.</person>, is the
					governor elect of Georgia, said a</q>
				<q who="RUSRI"> “flood of advertisements, fakers, false contraceptives, and
					quacks”</q>
				<q who="CDT"> would be loosed if the law which prohibits dissemination of birth
					control information in the mail were repealed. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Mrs. Sanger, the mother of three children, said that since the law was
					passed largely through the influence of <person reg="Comstock, Anthony">Anthony
						Comstock</person> 57 years ago 1,500,000 mothers have died of causes
					incident to motherhood, 90 per cent of whom might have been saved had not the
					law been in effect. </q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Mothers are Weakened</head>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Fifteen million children, she said, had been</q> “pushed out of life
				before they reached the first year because of weakened mothers, poverty, and
				neglect.” </p>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Judge Russell said the law is needed to protect the home. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="RUSRI">“Everyone in Georgia who needs to know about birth control already
					knows about it,”</q>
				<q who="CDT"> he declared.</q>
				<q who="RUSRI"> “Any state that wants contraception practiced can have it. But I
					don’t want the mails in my state opened to injurious matter to be placed before
					immature minds in the home. I object to opening the mails to depravity.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="RUSRI">“I think Mrs. Sanger is conscientious in her objections to the law,
					but when she gets this thing started she can’t control it. There will be a
					deluge of advertisements, fakers, false contraceptives, and quacks.”</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>Insists It Improves The Nation</head>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Birth control, said Mrs Sanger, is not only a health and economic
					expedient but also a means of improving the moral strength of the nation. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">The way of nature has been to control population by the death rate, but
					social consciousness of the modern world, she said, prevents nature from having
					its way by destruction of the weak and unfit. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Birth control, she said, has been practiced for a generation or more
					by</q> “a certain group, regardless of laws, where the best of this world’s
				things are found--intelligence, comforts, health, strength.” </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Points to Franklin</head>
			<p>
				<q who="CDT">Taking <person reg="Franklin, Benjamin">Benjamin Franklin</person> as
					an example, Justice Russell said,</q>
				<q who="RUSRI"> “great men have always come from the poor,”</q>
				<q who="CDT"> and advocated mothers’ pensions to help them take care of the
					children,</q>
				<q who="RUSRI"> “some of whom will bless the nation.”</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="RUSRI">“It is not the self-sacrificing, home loving, man making woman who
					wants this,”</q>
				<q who="CDT"> he said,</q>
				<q who="RUSRI"> “but the so-called ladies who want to attend the theater and the
					club instead of staying at home caring for their children.” </q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
