<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/11 Initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-13 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-04-30">30 Apr 1929</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Illinois Birth Control League Talk</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421037</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Plans New Drive for Birth Control</title>, <title
					type="journal">Waterloo Evening Courier</title>, Apr. 30, 1929</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Says Forces Are Gaining</title>, <title
					type="journal">Billings Gazette</title>, Apr. 30, 1929</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BG">Billings Gazette</name>
			<name id="WEC">Waterloo Evening Courier</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's speech before the Illinois Birth Control League at the
				<org>Chicago Women's Club</org> was not found, newspaper coverage has been
			provided.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="in Chicago"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Plans New Drive for Birth Control</head>
		<dateline>April 30 <date value="1929-04-30 "/> Chicago<place/></dateline>
		<div>

			<p><q who="WEC"> Mrs. Margaret Sanger in a talk today before the <org>Illinois Birth
						Control league</org> of the Chicago Woman’s club here, will open a campaign
					for extension of birth control clinics and a more lenient attitude toward
					dissemination of information. </q></p>
			<p><q who="WEC"> Before leaving <place reg="Chicago, IL">the city</place>, she said, she
					will devote time to active organization work, and plans to carry her campaign to
					the Pacific coast. </q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="WEC">Her activities came as an aftermath of the police raid and arrests are
					her <org reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"><place reg="New York, NY"
							>New York</place> clinic</org>.</q>
			</p>

		</div>
		<div>
			<head>Mrs. Sanger Says Forces Are Gaining</head>

			<p><q who="BG">Crime, overpopulation, and disease would be checked by scientific birth
					control, Mrs. Margaret Sanger noted birth control advocate, said here
					Tuesday.</q>
			</p>

			<p>
				<q who="BG">Mrs. Sanger opened her midwestern campaign for amendment of the <name
						reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211">federal laws</name>
					prohibiting the spread of contraceptive information with a speech before the
					Illinois Birth Control league and representatives of the <org
						reg="Brush Foundation">Brush Foundation for the Study of Birth Control</org>
					at <place reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland</place>.</q>
			</p>

			<p> “In the five years we have been conducting clinics in New York,” <q who="BG">she
					said,</q> “we have cared for 13,000 women and we know we have saved 90 percent
				of them from death.”</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Cites Alleged Good</head>
			<p> “We have reduced maternal and infant mortality by insisting on a three-year interval
				between children, and thus relieved the crowding of homes.” </p>

			<p><q who="BG"> Mrs. Sanger denounced the prosecution of Mrs. <person
						reg="Dennett, Mary Ware">Mary Ware Dennett</person>, grandmother-author of a
					sex book, who was fined $300 by a <person reg="Burrows, Warren B.">New York
						judge</person>. </q></p>

			<p> “All New York is indignant about Mrs. Dennett’s trial,” <q who="BG">she
					declared.</q> “Her pamphlet has been used by religious organizations for 10
				years. The <org reg="Union Theological Seminary">Union Theological seminary</org>,
				the <org reg="Young Women's Christian Association">Young Woman’s Christian
					association</org> and the <org reg="Young Men's Christian Association">Young
					Men’s Christian association</org> have been using it as textbook.”</p>

			<p><q who="BG"> Mrs. Sanger plans to organize a <org
						reg="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control">committee
						of 1,000</org> here to work for amendment of the federal penal code
					provisions in regard to birth control. </q></p>

		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Sees Progress</head>
			<p> “Chicago has five birth control clinics and will eventually be a greater field for
				our work than New York,” <q who="BG">she predicted.</q> “This city, with its large
				population of mixed nationalities, needs scientific birth control.</p>
			<p> “Under the present penal code even a reputable doctor may not legally furnish
				information or advice on this important matter. In 10 years, however, the government
				will be organizing birth control clinics as an essential part of the program of
				material and infant welfare.” </p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
