<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/11 YG</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-27 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1937-02-18">18 Feb 1937</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied>Interview with the Arizona Republic</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421913</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Margaret Sanger, Award Winner, Here; Plans Birth Control
					Clinic</title>, <title type="journal">Arizona Republic</title>, Feb. 19, 1937 </bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="AR">The Arizona Republic</name>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger was staying in <place reg="Chandler, AZ">Chandler, Arizona</place>at the
				<place>Hotel San Marcos</place> when the interview was conducted. For a similar
			interview, see <xref from="421921.xml">Interview with the United Press</xref>, Feb. 17,
			1937.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="in Arizona"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and marriage"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="medical community and"/>
	</headNote>

	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger, Award Winner, Here; Plans Birth Control Clinic</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>Resting briefly after the most decisive battle in a career which has been unceasing
				war waged on a front which ranged from crowded tenement districts to <org
					reg="United States Senate">U.S. senate</org> committee rooms, Margaret Sanger,
				noted birth control crusader, is a visit in the Salt River valley.</p>
			<p>With her husband, <person reg="Slee, J. Noah H.">J. Noah H. Slee</person>, retired
				president of the <org reg="Three-in-One Oil Company">3-in-1 Oil Company</org>, who
				has been vacationing in the valley for some time, she is a guest at Hotel San Marcos
				in Chandler and will remain in <place>Arizona</place> for several weeks.</p>
			<p>Shortly before leaving her <place reg="Fishkill, NY">Fishkill, N.Y.</place>home for
				Arizona, she was honored at a dinner by the <org reg="Town Hall Club">Town Hall
					Club</org> of <place reg="New York, NY">Manhattan</place>, composed of social
				elite of the East, and was presented with the club's award of honor for the year's
				most conspicuous contribution to the enlargement and enrichment of life. The award
				was made January 15.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Court Rules Favorably</head>

			<p>
				<q who="AR">From prison to palace Mrs. Sanger since 1914 has carried her crusade to
					permit the dissemination of scientific information which would enable parents to
					limit their families to a number for which they can care properly. On December
					7, the <org reg="United States Circuit Court of Appeals">U.S. Circuit Court of
						Appeals</org> removed the greatest obstacle in the way of success of the
					crusade when it ruled that physicians might send contraceptives by mail. This
					decision nullified a 63-year-old law which made sending such material by mail or
					common carrier a crime punishable by $5,000 fine and five years in prison. The
					court ruling also gives physicians the right to advise their patients when they
					deem it necessary for their general health and well-being.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AR">A measure embodying much the same idea introduced into the last session
					of congress with the support of the <org
						reg="General Federation of Women's Clubs">General Federation of Women's
						Clubs</org>, the <org
						reg="National Federation of Business and Women's Professional Clubs"
						>National Federation of Business and Professional Clubs</org>, <org
						reg="the Young Women's Christian Association">the Young Women's Christian
						Association</org> and other large groups, died in <org
						reg="United States Senate Committee on the Judiciary">the senate judiciary
						committee</org>, of which <person reg="Ashurst, Henry Fountain">Sen. Henry
						F. Ashurst</person>of Arizona is chairman.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Crusader Still Active</head>

			<p>
				<q who="AR">Elated over the victory which the court ruling gave the cause to which
					she has devoted much of her life, Mrs. Sanger has no thought of ceasing her
					efforts. Rather, two weeks after the verdict she celebrated with a birth control
					conference in Manhattan, and during her stay here she plans the establishment of
					a birth control clinic in <place reg="Phoenix, AZ">Phoenix</place>. Such a
					clinic would be operated along the same lines as the one opened in Tucson last
					June.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="AR">Improvement of the race through the limitation of families to a number
					for which the parents can provide proper physical, mental and spiritual support
					and lessening of the tax burden through reducing the number of indigents to be
					provided for from public funds are two important results which Mrs. Sanger
					expects from wide-spread birth control. She believes it also will reduce that
					some authorities refer to as the abortion </q>“racket.”</p>
			<p>“Add to that-call it sentimentality if you will--the happiness of the man and woman
				who, loving each other enough to marry, find themselves bound to the wheel in order
				to provide even the bare necessities for an ever-increasing brood. The mother, her
				strength sapped by constant child-bearing and attempts to care for her children, and
				the father, tired and careworn with the economic battle, have no times for that real
				companionship which is a right of marriage.</p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Holds Happiness Important</head>
			<p>“Human happiness IS important. It must be, else our forefathers who wrote the
				constitution would not have included ‘pursuit of happiness’ among the inalienable
				rights."</p>
			<p> “Society at large is adversely affected by addition to it of children for whom there
				is no chance of proper development. Families so large that the parents cannot care
				for them become the burden of the taxpayer who must provide funds for their care.
				Crime, too, breeds in the crowded districts, and again the taxpayers and citizens at
				large are the losers.” </p>
			<p>
				<q who="AR">More than 320 clinics have been established in the United States through
					the efforts of the dynamic little crusader, and her work has not stopped on this
					side of the <place reg="Atlantic Ocean">Atlantic</place>. Last year she spread
					her gospel in <place>India</place>, <place>Switzerland</place>, <place
						reg="Soviet Union">Russia</place>, <place>Canada</place> and
						<place>England</place> all know of Margaret Sanger.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="AR">Foreign nations-with the exception of <place>Italy</place>and
						<place>Germany</place>and other military nations </q>“where men are only
				cannon fodder and women sources of war material” <q who="AR">--are friendly toward
					the birth control movement, Mrs. Sanger said. In England clinics are established
					under the jurisdiction of the government and doctors must provide the
					information. Other nations have similar setups.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head>Compliments Phoenician</head>

			<p> “One trouble in the United States has been,” <q who="AR">Mrs. Sanger said, </q>“that
				physicians themselves do not all know proper contraceptive methods. Medical schools
				have not trained students in contraception. Even now only five schools so train
				their embryo physicians.”</p>
			<p><q who="AR">Mrs. Sanger paid high tribute to <person reg="Struckmeyer, Fritzi">Fritzi
						Struckmeyer</person> as the first woman in any state legislature or in
					congress to</q> "have the courage to introduce legislation which would remove
				obstacles to the movement which means so much to their own sex." <q who="AR">Last
					week, Miss Struckmeyer, serving her first term as a member of the <org
						reg="Arizona State Legislature, 13th District">13th legislature</org>,
					introduced such a bill.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="AR">Asked concerning activity of women in office in support of the movement,
					Mrs. Sanger expressed disappointment, saying it has been phraseology only with
					little actual support. To woman’s newness in official positions she attributes
					this attitude, believing that in many instances they have not gained the poise
					necessary to publicly espouse a movement which might prove unpopular.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AR">She does believe ardently that women's influence in legislative matters
					is making itself felt, to the benefit of the nation. Women on juries have been
					an active influence toward cleaning up the courts and influencing justice, she
					believes., expressing surprise at Arizona's continued attitude of banning women
					from jury service.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="AR">The fact that Arizona has the highest maternal and infant mortality rate
					of any state in the union except <place>New Mexico</place>she characterized
					as</q> "ridiculous--and unnecessary."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Gracious Personality</head>

			<p>
				<q who="AR">Looking back over Margaret Sanger's career and realizing that it has
					carried her into court many times, put her in prison and placed her before
					senate committees, it would be, for one who has not met her easy to imagine her
					the "Amazon type" woman. Nothing could be farther from a true description.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="AR">Gracious, vital, there is about her a sweetness which inspires belief in
					her sincerity when in answer to the question, “But how is it with you? Truly the
					fight is well on the way to being won--but at what a personal sacrifice to you!
					Has it been worth it, personally?”, she answered,</q> “A hundred fold. I feel
				that instead of being given the award of honor I should have given it. There is a
				great sense of peace in fulfilling one’s destiny.” </p>
			<p>
				<q who="AR">The red of her hair has been subdued somewhat by a generous sprinkling
					of gray--for Margaret Higgins was born in 1883--but there is no lessening of the
					fire with which she champions her cause. Her sparkling wit and quick perception,
					a heritage from Irish-born parents, highlight a magnetic personality.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="AR">She is the mother of two sons, one of whom is a <person
						reg="Sanger, Grant">practicing physician</person> and the other <person
						reg="Sanger, Stuart">studying to become a doctor</person>. Her <person
						reg="Sanger, Peggy">only daughter</person> she lost through death.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
