<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/07/03 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-13 CH proof, clean tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Black, Cobey">Cobey Black</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1956-03-13">Mar 13 1956</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Interview at the Reef Hotel, Honolulu</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421990</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Better Babies</title>, <title type="journal">Honolulu Star
					Bulletine</title>, Mar. 14, 1956</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BLACO">Black, Cobey</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This interview was published in the column, "Who's News. . . with Cobey Black</p>
		<index level1="children" level2="rights of"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="pill"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Better Babies</head>
		<p>
			<q who="BLACO">Forty years ago an attractive, red-haired trained nurse working in the
				slums of <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place> was horrified to hear of the
				death of a young mother in a nearby tenement.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BLACO">She knew the mother was passionately fond of her children, so much that
				she wanted no more offspring to divide her devotion, energies and the meager but
				adequate income of her husband. Her one wish was that her children, despite their
				slum environment would never become unwanted burdens of society. With her death that
				is exactly what they did become.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BLACO">But what horrified the nurse was that she also knew the mother had died
				of an illegal operation performed to prevent the birth of a fourth child. </q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BLACO">The mother is nameless, one of thousands who have died of interrupted
				pregnancies, but the nurse's name was Margaret Sanger, and it was this experience
				which inspired her to crusade for birth control, a term she herself originated.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"What I want is wanted children," <q who="BLACO">said Mrs. Sanger yesterday at the <org
					reg="Reef Hotel">Reef</org></q>.</p>
		<p>"You can't set a size for all families--the number of children depends on the particular
			situation of the parents--but a child should be wanted before it is born.</p>
		<p>"It should not have to be unwatned, abused, cruelly treated, or brought into an
			environment of misery and even death by parents who have no right to have children."</p>
		<p>"Recently, while I was in <place>India</place>, I asked mothers about the health of their
			pathetic babies. Often the answer was 'Baby hungry in my belly too long.'</p>
		<p>"The child was starving before it was born.</p>
		<p>"Do you realize 66 per cent of India's population never has one full meal a day? Ninety
			per cent has never known meat. The only milk they've tasted is their mother's.</p>
		<p>"<place>Asia</place> has more than one-half the population of the globe crowded in
			one-sixth of its land area, and 50,000 babies are added to it EVERY day.</p>
		<p>"The world population is far outdistancing the food supply, especially proteins.
			According to the <org reg="United States Department of Agriculture">Department of
				Agriculture</org>, it takes 100 good grazing acres to give nine people meat once a
			day.</p>
		<p>"In 1936 I traveled in India a year, setting up 65 birth control centers. War destroyed
			many of them, but the seeds were sown.</p>
		<p>"I just received a letter this week saying that the Indian government has agreed to
			allocate $8 million to be used solely for family planning work.</p>
		<p>"In 1954 I was invited to <place>Japan</place> by <person reg="Kawasaki, Hideji">Hidejo
				Kawasaka</person>, the minister of health, who is doing everything in his power to
			help the people of his country control the size of their families. The midwives are now
			instructed to teach birth control.</p>
		<p>"I predict that it won't take many generations for India and Japan to lead the world in
			eugenic populations because the governments are now directing their efforts in slum
			areas to controlling the increase of the transmissibly diseased and dysgenic portions of
			the population.</p>
		<p>"In America, which has as many new babies as India, we haven't touched the lower strata
			of society for whom the movement was started. The women are so family-bound that they
			are unable to visit one of the 600 clinics of the <org reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America">Planned Parenthood</org> League
			throughout America. </p>
		<p>"The public health officials are also the sinners; they make no effort and have no policy
			for teaching birth control.</p>
		<p>"Also the movement lacks funds for research. We are using today the same methods that I
			brought back from <place>Germany</place> and <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>in
			1915.</p>
		<p>"Fortunately it is a method which requires a doctor's advice in adjustment, so the
			medical profession has been brought into the movement. But it is a method which is
			outdated compared to the advances made in other fields of science.</p>
		<p>"The oral contraceptive, or pill, called Progesterone, which is being developed in the
			research laboratory of <person reg="Pincus, Gregory Goodwin">Dr. Pincus,</person> of
				<place reg="Worcester, MA">Worcester</place>, has proved 100 per cent satisfactory
			with animals as well as with the controlled number of women tested.</p>
		<p>"The woman is immunized against conception for periods which last four months. But the
			pill does not sterilize, and she can conceive when the four month's immunization wears
			off.</p>
		<p>"I feel like the ideal solution is an injection which can be administered every six
			months. Science has developed vaccinations against cholera, diphtheria, polio and
			countless other threats to the health of mankind. It is not impossible that the day will
			come when family planning will be as simple and universal.</p>
		<p>"On that day you will see the birth of a happier, healthier world population."</p>

	</docBody>
</doc>
