<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2014/07/03 MM</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2015-04-13 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1956-05-29">29 May 1956</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Rochester-Monroe County League for Planned Parenthood
                    Annual Meeting Address</supplied></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp421989</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Offers 'Key to World Peace'</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Rochester Democrat and Chronicle</title>, May 30, 1956, p.
                29</bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
        <index level1="Japan" level2="population policies of"/>
        <index level1="overpopulation" level2="threat to peace as"/></headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Mrs. Sanger Offers 'Key to World Peace'</head>
        <p><q who="RDC">Birth control was embraced by it pioneer advocate yesterday as a key aid to
                maintaining world peace.</q></p>
        <p><q who="RDC">The speaker, Mrs. Margaret Sanger, argued that family planning must be
                pursued to eliminate overpopulation, a cause of wars.</q> "It is," <q who="RDC">she
                said,</q> "the keynote of a new social awakening."</p>
        <p><q who="RDC">She addressed the annual meeting of the <org><place reg="Rochester, NY"
                        >Rochester</place>-Monroe County League for Planned Parenthood</org> in the
                    <org reg="Rochester Chamber of Commerce">Chamber of Commerce</org>. About 400
                persons--including health and welfare leaders--heard her speak.</q></p>
        <p>"It would have been laughable to talk about overpopulation in this country," <q who="RDC"
                >she grinned. But, Mrs. Sanger added, not so in <place>Asia</place>.</q></p>
        <p><q who="RDC">In 1952, when <place>Japan</place>'s population was 90 million, Mrs. Sanger
                returned to the country to find that her proposals had at least been endorsed by the
                government and accepted by women.</q></p>
        <p>"They are going about it in a very scientific way,"<q who="RDC"> she explained.</q> "In
            fact, I would say they are leading the world."</p>
        <p>"When this work is properly directed, it can relieve untold suffering for countless
            number of women. It is an essential step we must take if we are to eliminate war and
            bring peace to the face of the world."</p>
        <p><q who="RDC">Mrs. Sanger, who had three children, reaffirmed her belief that</q> "many
            people are parents today who have no right to be parents."</p>
        <p>"We believe firmly," <q who="RDC">Mrs. Sanger said,</q> "that a man who can take care of
            two children well should not have eight children. But many of them do."</p>
        <p><q who="RDC">Mrs. Sanger also suggested that young couples wait at least two years before
                they have children. She said:</q> "They should postpone parenthood until they are
            sure they are going to be happy so as to prepare a harmonious atmosphere for the
            child."</p>
        <p><q who="RDC">The bulk of Mrs. Sanger's address was devoted to her early--and often
                stormy--work in the birth control movement.</q></p>

    </docBody>
</doc>
