<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/07/08 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-14 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate><prepDate>2015-05-27 CH clean up citation</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Brooks, Gene">Gene Brooks</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1961-10-02">2 Oct 1961</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Episcopal Church Decision on Birth
					Control</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421994</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Lauds Birth Stand of Episcopalians</title>,
					<title type="journal">Tuscon Daily Citizen</title>, Oct. 2, 1961, p. 56</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="KINAR">Kinsolving, Arthur B.</name>
			<name id="ECGC">Episcopal Church General Convention</name>
			<name id="FOWJO">Fowler, John Clinton</name>
			<name id="TDC">Tucson Daily Citizen</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">

		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Lauds Birth Stand of Episcopalians</head>
		<byline>By GENE BROOKS</byline>
		<p><q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger, world leader in the birth control movement, today lauded the
					<org>Episcopal Church</org> for endorsing artificial birth control</q> "<q
				who="ECGC">when used in Christian conscience.</q>"</p>
		<p><q who="TDC">The Right Rev. <person reg="Kinsolving, Arthur B.">Arthur B.
					Kinsolving</person>, Episcopal bishop of <place>Arizona</place>, just returned
				from the Detroit convention, said today:</q> "<q who="KINAR">I am four-square behind
				the convention's endorsement of planned parenthood.</q>"</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">But a <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place> Episcopal <person
					reg="Fowler, John Clinton"> minister</person> was not enthusiastic about action
				taken Thursday at the <org reg="Protestant Episcopal Church General Convention"
					>general convention of Protestant Episcopal Church</org> in Detroit.</q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="TDC">The governing committee said family planning was a</q> "<q who="FOWJO">right
				and important factor in Christian family life.</q>"</p>
		<p><q who="TDC">Bishop Kinsolving said: </q>"<q who="KINAR">I started backing Mrs. Sanger's
				leadership in this crucial problem 30 years ago in <place reg="Long Island, NY">Long
					Island, N.Y.</place> We feel that the church convention's action is a triumph
				for our nation and for much of the world's congested populations.</q>"</p>
		<p><q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger said,</q> "This is one of the important steps I've been hoping
			for. It's the action we expect from an enlightened church."</p>
		<p><q who="TDC">Contacted at her home, 65 Sierra Vista, Mrs. Sanger said,</q> "This is the
			way we expect a church of intelligence and responsibility to act. Naturally, I am very
			pleased."</p>
		<p>"The importance to the nation and the world by the Episcopal Church's action can't be
			underestimated. I am especially glad to see that the church's convention goes on record
			to recommend government assistance (on birth control information) when it is officially
			sought by other nations."</p>
		<p>"This is the action we need," <q who="TDC">Mrs. Sanger added.</q> "When
				<place>India</place> asked the <place reg="United States">U.S.</place> for
			information on birth control, former President <person reg="Eisenhower, Dwight D."
				>Eisenhower</person> wouldn't touch it. He was wrong. Public education of all kinds,
			especially in this crucial matter, is certainly a part of our government's
			responsibility."</p>
		<p><q who="TDC">The Very Reverend John Clinton Fowler, of <org>St. Michael's &amp; All
					Angels Episcopal Church</org>, said he is </q>"less than enthusiastic about
			birth control action taken at the Detroit convention."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="FOWJO">"I wish the declaration hadn't been made," <q who="TDC">he said.</q> "The
				artificial prevention of birth is a theological matter and ought to be decided by
				moral theologians. It certainly shouldn't be decided by a majority vote of lay and
				clerical representatives to a convention.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"It is my opinion," <q who="TDC">Father Fowler said,</q> "that the conscience of
			Christian people need not necessarily be guided by this decision of the general
			convention of the Episcopal Church."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">The Rev. <person reg="Ferguson, George">George Ferguson</person>, minister
				of <org>St. Philip's in the Hills Church</org>, said he had not comments on the
				convention's action. But he pointed out that the birth control endorsement reaffirms
				earlier endorsements of birth control by the <org reg="Church of England">Anglican
					Church of England</org>, the U.S. Episcopal Church's parent church.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">The birth control pronouncement was one of the last official actions of the
				week-long Episcopal convention in <place reg="Detroit, MI">Detroit</place>.</q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
