<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/04 VS initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-24 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1936-11-16">16 Nov 1936</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">The Present Day Trend of Birth
				Control</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421910</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Gives Hearers Plenty to Think About</title>,
					<title>Buffalo Courier Express</title>, Nov. 17, 1936</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BCE">Buffalo Courier Express</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke under the auspices of the <org>Buffalo Family Relations
				Institute</org> at the <org>Hotel Fillmore</org> on November 16, 1936.</p>
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/><index level1="birth control"
			level2="economic rationale"/><index level1="Sanger, Margaret"
			level2="physical descriptions"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Gives Hearers Plenty to Think About</head>

		<div type="section">
			<p> That part of Buffalo that went to the Hotel Fillmore last night to hear Mrs.
				Margaret Sanger, greatest advocate of birth control in this country, discuss the
				subject that is nearest and dearest to her heart, came away impressed and admiring.
				The Buffalonians who heard her for the first time, this doughty reddish-brown-haired
				woman, who looks meek as the proverbial Moses, but is one of the greatest fighters
				of our time, was a revelation. To Margaret Sanger, adherents she was, as always, a
				delight. </p>
			<p>For she stood upon a brilliantly lit stage in a demure black gown, as gentle and
				feminine a feminist as ever breathed, and buried facts in the face of a remarkable
				audience that was at least one-half male. That she gained militant converts to her
				cause was apparent by an 80 per cent lineup at the conclusion of her lecture to sign
				pledge cards for campaign activities of the local Family Relations Institute. That
				she gave all who heard her something to think about and work about was also evident
				in the numbers of groups of persons who gathered to talk about her lecture for at
				least a half-hour after the verbal pyrotechnic display was off.</p>
			<p>Riding right into the thick of battle, little Mrs. Sanger was only a minute launched
				on her speech when she knuckled down to battle with religious antagonism to her
				cause.</p>
			<p> “Control of the population is one of the great problems of life, and the greatest
				problem of our age,” <q who="BCE">she said</q>. “When we call into the world a new
				life consciously, then we begin on a new and better civilization.</p>
			<p> “Birth control is, however first of all, an answer to the prayer of the poor--the
				sad, unfortunate people all over the world who are asking what they can do to keep
				from wrecking the lives of countless of mothers and keep fathers from becoming
				hopeless and despairing.”</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Tells About <place>India</place></head>

			<p>
				<q who="BCE">Mrs. Sanger's recent tour of India provided her with interesting
					material for part of her talk last night. Most people are badly informed about
					Indians she said. She labeled it the country of contrasts, filled with the
					horribly rich and the poor to whom life is a starved, living death, where the
					weather is either intensely hot or icy cold; where persons are either abysmally
					ignorant or deeply learned. India, she said, has tried everything, and she
					pointed out that, in the face of “Purdah,” that state where women as a majority
					were kept in virtual imprisonment never being seen by any man except their
					husbands. <person reg="Gandhi, Mahatma">Gandhi</person> had but to send out the
					call and the women heroically revolted to free themselves almost overnight.</q>
			</p>

			<p><q who="BCE"> Mrs. Sanger was invited to India as the guest of the <org
						reg="All-India Women's Conference">All India Women's Conference</org> and
					she traveled 10,000 miles setting up 50 birth control centers.</q>
			</p>
			<p> “There were no legal objections in India in my work and absolutely no religious
				interference like that in this country,” <q who="BCE">she continued.</q> “Because in
				India, the problem has become acute and leaders and educators have been forced to
				this action.”</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Reason for Control</head>
			<p> “But the identical factors necessitating birth control exist in this country that
				exist in India. First, the infant mortality rate; second, the father’s wage; third,
				the need to space children to give mothers and children a chance; and fourth, the
				place of the child in the family. Certainly to regard to this last point it is
				apparent that it makes little difference if the mother has waited two and three
				years between each child, if there are too many children in the family. Figures from
				any health report show that. When there are seven children in a family, the
				mortality rate jumps drastically. When we get up to twelve children in the family,
				the records show that 60 per cent of the twelve die. </p>
			<p> “Who, then, benefits from this? Does the community? Does the nation? Does the church
				gain by the unhappy deaths of hundreds of mothers and hundreds of children? I
				maintain that we are in a state of barbarism when we have the knowledge that will
				make these tragic lives happy, that will save these suffering mothers, that will
				insure children a right place in their family picture-- and we withhold it. Why not
				make life something constructive. Why waste it?</p>
			<p> “We are trying to make a new world,” <q who="BCE">said Mrs. Sanger</q>, “to pass on
				the torch of life in bodies, fit, perfect and beautiful. We want young people to
				look on marriage not filled with fear, to have women exist without the sword of
				death hanging over their heads. We want to give to the poor the same knowledge those
				of wealth have. We want to amend the federal laws so that all hospitals can
				distribute information and that the information can be transmitted through the
				mails.” </p>
			<p><q who="BCE">Mrs. Sanger was introduced to the assembly last night by Dean <person
						reg="Alden, Carlos C.">Carlos C. Alden</person> of the <org>University of
						Buffalo</org> and he followed her speech with a short resume of her
					remarkable life. Dr. <person reg="Clarke, Alfred">Alfred Clarke</person>,
						<person reg="Mitchell, Ellen">Mrs. Thomas Mitchell</person> of the Family
					Relations Institute at 73 West Eagle Street; <person reg="Sawyer, Esther Hoyt"
						>Mrs. Ansley W. Sawyer</person>, <person reg="Davis, Mrs. Herbert R.">Mrs.
						Herbert Davis</person>, <person reg="Penhey, Thomas Jr.">Thomas Penhey
						Jr.</person>, <person reg="Barkley, Mrs.">Mrs. Barday</person> and Miss
						<person reg="Gaylord, Gladys">Gaylord</person> of <place reg="Cleveland, OH"
						>Cleveland</place> were others on the platform at last night's meeting. Mrs.
					Sanger was the guest of <person reg="Schoellkopf, Olive Abbott">Mrs. J.
						Frederick Schoellkopf, Jr.</person> during her stay in Buffalo.</q></p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
