<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/04 Initials</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-09 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1952-04-26">26 Apr 1952</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">El Paso Planned Parenthood Center Speech</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421935</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Plans Tour in Far East</title>, <title
					type="journal">El Paso Herald Post</title>, Apr. 28, 1952</bibl>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Margaret Sanger Discusses Reasons for Birth Control</title>,
					<title type="journal">El Paso Times</title>, Apr. 1952 </bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="EPT">El Paso Times</name>
			<name id="EPHP">Herald Post</name>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger addressed the 15th anniversary meeting of the <org>El Paso Planned Parenthood
				Center</org>, at the <org>Country Club</org>, on April 26. The speech was not found,
			and newspaper coverage has been substituted. </p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="civilization and"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Plans Tour in Far East</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="EPHP">Margaret Sanger, foremost exponent of birth control, left El Paso
					yesterday after conferring with directors of the Planned Parenthood Centers.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPHP">She was guest of honor at a banquet in the Country Club, celebrating
					the 15th anniversary of Planned Parenthood in El Paso.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPHP">Directors of the first Planned Parenthood Center here were honored at
					the dinner. The Center was founded under Mrs. Sanger's supervision, April 26,
					1937. Two additional clinics were established later.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger praised the work of the three clinics in El Paso.</q>
			</p>
			<p>“This is one of the most encouraging spots in the nation,” <q who="HP">she told local
					workers</q> “You are doing wonderful work in <place reg="El Paso, TX">El
					Paso</place>.</p>
			<p>"I am also proud of the men here. They have given complete backing to their wives who
				are members of the clinic staffs. I am pleased at the support given to the work by
				the people and officials of El Paso."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Plan Foreign Program</head>
			<p>
				<q who="EPHP">Mrs. Sanger outlined her plans for expanding planned parenthood
					programs in <place>India</place>, <place>Japan</place>and <place>China</place>.
					She will leave early in the fall to supervise the establishment of new units in
					those countries. </q>
			</p>
			<p>“There is still a great need for constructive work in the Far East,” <q who="HP">she
					said.</q></p>
			<p> “Fifteen countries have asked for our help in setting up new programs. </p>
			<p>“The work is easiest in India, where the officials speak English and have been
				trained in English schools.”<note n="1">Here is a note.</note>
			</p>
		</div>

		<div type="section">
			<head>Margaret Sanger Discusses Reasons for Birth Control</head>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Margaret Sanger, the famous planned parenthood proponent, Saturday
					returned to El Paso to express her theories with freedom, 15 years after she was
					boycotted to prevent her from speaking in a local hotel.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger addressed the Planned Parenthood Center of El Paso at a
					dinner held at 6:30 p. m. in the Country Club, marking the local organization's
					15th anniversary.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">It was fifteen years ago last February that Mrs. Sanger's hotel was
					boycotted by a local group, and she was forced to speak in the mezzanine of
					another hotel. It was there that plans for the center were born, and now, El
					Paso can boast of three clinics.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">As a woman who for many years has fought an uphill battle for her ideas
					and gained world-wide recognition as one of the most famous American women, Mrs.
					Sanger is used to opposition. If it is dealt out in the right spirit, she does
					not mind it, she admits.</q>
			</p>
			<p>“We were lucky in <place reg="United States">America</place>to have opposition,” <q
					who="EPT">she said.</q> “It brought out the strength and conviction that we were
				right. We had something to fight for and against. We don’t mind the opposition, we
				just want the opportunity to express our views.”</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger, who lives in <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson,
					Ariz</place>., is en route to New York to make plans with the <org
						reg="International Committee on Planned Parenthood">International Planned
						Parenthood Committee</org>, of which she is chairman, for a visit to India
					and Japan. Mrs. Sanger's invitation to go to India in November to organize a
					planned parenthood program there stems from Prime Minister <person
						reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Nehru</person>'s recent public announcement that
					birth control will be part of India's five-year welfare plan. She is going to
					Japan thereafter at the request of the Japanese people. In that country, she
					will address 3000 people on Dec. 6 at a public meeting.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Two years ago, Mrs. Sanger was refused a visa to Japan by Gen. <person
						reg="MacArthur, Douglas">Douglas MacArthur</person>, who although he
					sympathized with her ideas, was forced to turn down her request under pressure
					to enter the country.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">The planned parenthood program cannot go much further in the United
					States until the public health departments take the responsibility for the
					future quality of our race, Mrs. Sanger believes.</q>
			</p>
			<p> “If the public health departments do not take it upon themselves to instruct the
				poor, ignorant people, they will multiply in numbers not only in poor physical
				condition but also in low mental conditions. If we keep on like this, we shall be
				reproducing toward a race of morons,” <q who="EPT">she asserted.</q> “It is a
				benighted opposition who ties the hands of our public health authorities. This
				opposition is cruel because these people will be forced to continue having the
				children they do not want or cannot afford to have.” </p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">The planned parenthood program gets no co-operation from county
					hospitals and clinics in its program, she added.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger, a widow, is the mother of two sons, both doctors. One
						<person reg="Sanger, Stuart">Stewart Sanger</person>, is the father of two
					daughters and lives in Tucson. The other, <person reg="Sanger, Grant">Grant
						Sanger</person>, of <place reg="Mount Kisco, NY">Mount Kisco, N.Y.</place>,
					last week became the father of his sixth child, an only <person
						reg="Sanger, Anne">daughter</person>.</q> "They are so excited about the
				little girl that they haven't named her," <q who="EPT">the proud grandmother
					revealed.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger was one of 11 children. Her <person
						reg="Higgins, Anne Purcell">mother</person> died in her early 40s after the
					birth of her 11th child.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">It was the memory of her mother's hard struggle, plus the fact that as
					a registered nurse, women were constantly asking her advice on birth control
					that turned Mrs. Sanger's efforts toward the planned parenthood program.</q>
			</p>
			<p>“I knew then that birth control was a human, a physical need,”<q who="EPT">she
					said.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">Mrs. Sanger's struggle to get her ideas accepted are described in her
					book, "<title type="book">Margaret Sanger: An Autobiography</title>."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="EPT">One of these days, she added, after the planned parenthood programs in
					India and Japan gain impetus, she will sit down to write again, and add to the
					number of books she has written about birth control.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
