<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/19 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-14 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-13 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Aldrich, Pearl">Pearl Aldrich</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1959-09-10">10 Sept 1959</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Phoenix Planned Parenthood Clinic</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421985</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Planned Parenthood Group Defended by Mrs. Sanger</title>.
					<title type="journal">Tucson Daily Citizen</title>, Sept. 10, 1959</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="ALPE">Aldrich, Pearl</name>
			<name id="ASL">Arizona State Law</name>
			<name id="HARIR">Hardy, Iris</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="planned parenthood"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="suppression of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head> Planned Parenthood Group Defended by Mrs. Sanger </head>
		<byline>By PEARL ALDRICH</byline>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE">A new round in the battle over birth control was shaping up today with
				Margaret Sanger of Tucson rushing to the defense of <org>Planned Parenthood of
					Phoenix</org>, Inc.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE">That organization was warned yesterday it apparently is violating a
				little-known. 20-year old law by distributing birth control literature.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"The Phoenix clinic has to get a good lawyer and show it is doing nothing illegal,"<q
				who="ALDPE"> Mrs. Sanger said here today.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE"><org>Planned Parenthood Clinic of Tucson</org>, 55 E. Jackson St., also
				distributed literature through individuals and by the mail.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE">Officials of the Phoenix organization were informed of the 20-year-old
				law yesterday when they protested a county ban in literature distribution at the
				County Hospital and Health Department.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE">County Mgr. <person reg="Sullivan, Tom M.">Tom M. Sullivan</person>
				quoted the law as follows:</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ASL">"Any person who willfully writes, composes or publishes a notice or an
				advertisement of any medicine or any means of producing or facilitating a
				miscarriage or abortion, or for prevention of conception, or who offers his services
				by notice, advertisement or otherwise to assist in the accomplishment of any such
				purpose is guilty of a misdemeanor."</q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="ALDPE">Mrs. Sanger said, </q>"We looked into that when we first started the
			clinic here (in 1935) and the only thing we could find that was illegal was to advertise
			publicly.</p>
		<p>"We went to Phoenix then, went through that with the attorney general's office up there
			and that was what we found. We've always told the Phoenix people not to advertise and I
			don't believe they have. The first thing they've got to do is get a good lawyer and show
			they're doing nothing illegal."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE">According to <person reg="Hardy, Iris">Mrs. Frank Hardy</person>, vice
				president of the board of directors of the local Planned Parenthood Clinic,</q>
			<q who="HARIR"> "This is so old hat, it isn't even funny. As far as I know, the local
				clinic isn't distributing literature in the County Hospital here or the Health
				Department but we try to get all the literature we can out to the public. People who
				come to the Clinic take literature and read it and pass it on to their friends and
				each year, during the campaign, we mail it out. Every organization in the country
				does."</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE">Violation of Arizona law is punishable by a fine not to exceed $300, a
				jail sentence not to exceed six months, or both.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="ALDPE"><person reg="Stidham, Charles C.">Charles C. Stidham</person>,
					<org>Maricopa County</org> attorney, said he would have to issue a complaint
				against the Phoenix clinic if called upon to do so by any citizen.</q>
		</p>
		<p>Mrs. Sanger indicated she will throw her weight behind the <place reg="Phoenix, AZ"
				>Phoenix</place> clinic in this fight. She said she would go to Phoenix, if
			necessary, after she ascertains the full extent of the problem.</p>
		<p/>
	</docBody>
</doc>
