<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/07/01 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-13 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person></docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1956-05-31">31 May 1956</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Planned Parenthood Center of Buffalo Speech</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421991</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Reports on Visit to Asia</title>, <title
					type="journal">Buffalo Courier-Express</title>, May 31, 1956, p. 9</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BCE"/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation and"/>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke to the annual luncheon of the Planned Parenthood Center of
			Buffalo at the Hotel Statler. The speech was not found. Portions of the article
			discussing other speakers, <person reg="Abbott, Lois P.">Lois P. Abbott</person> and
				<person reg="Greenberger, Jane">Jane Greenberger</person>, and the elections of the
			Buffalo Center were omitted by the MSPP editors.</p>
		<index level1="India" level2="overpopulation and"/>
		<index level1="International Planned Parenthood Federation"/>
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="eugenics" level2="positive"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Reports On Visit to Asia</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p><q who="BCE">Population problems in <place>Japan</place> and <place>India</place> are
					being met by the governments in a realistic way, Mrs. Margaret Sanger said here
					yesterday. She spoke at the annual luncheon of the <org>Planned Parenthood
						Center of <place reg="Buffalo, NY">Buffalo</place></org> at <org>Hotel
						Statler.</org></q></p>
			<p><q who="BCE">Mrs. Sanger, president of the <org>International Planned Parenthood
						Federation</org> visited Japan and India in 1954 and spoke before the <org
						reg="Japan House of Councillors">House of Peers</org> in Japan. She
					predicted that if the present plans are carried out Japan and India will be in
					two generations</q> "the most culturally and eugenically advanced countries in
				the world."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Industry's Aid</head>
			<p><q who="BCE">In India, she said, each medical school will teach the subject of family
					planning, industry will disseminate all available information to the workers and
					social agencies are instructed to give all the information possible in their
					work.</q></p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
