<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-05-07 JK initial tag</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-07 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-10 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1941-04-13">13 Jul 1941</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Corning Leader Interview</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421946</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">'Goal is in Sight' Says Mrs. Sanger, Birth Control Advocate,
					Corning Native</title>, <title type="journal">Corning Leader</title>, Jul. 13,
				1941</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="CL">Corning Leader</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Several paragraphs of biographical information about Sanger at the end of this article
			were omitted by the MSPP editors.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="distribution of information about"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="American opinion on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Goal is in Sight' Says <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Mrs. Sanger</person>, Birth
			Control Advocate, <place reg="Corning, NY">Corning</place> Native</head>
		<p>“Our sweat, blood and tears have not been in vain,” <q who="CL">declared Margaret Sanger
				after 27 years of single-hearted devotion to the cause of birth control.</q> “The
			goal is in sight.”</p>
		<p>
			<q who="CL">This goal, Mrs. Sanger explained, was to make it possible for the </q>“very
			poorest, migratory slum mother to have easily accessible, the best information about
			birth control. Already three states, <place>North Carolina</place>, <place>South
				Carolina</place>, and <place>Alabama</place>, have included the dissemination of
			birth control knowledge in their public health service.” </p>
		<p>
			<q who="CL">Mrs. Sanger tells of the achievements of the birth control movement in a
				gentle, quiet voice. Today there is about her nothing of the crusader which two
				decades ago drew down denunciation on her head, waves of praise and denunciation,
				and to cause her Corning friends and acquaintances to both disown and cheer the
				native daughter who had become a world figure. </q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
