<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 MC enter corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-10-11">11 Oct 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Return to the United States</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422069</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Japs Formed Birth Control Clinics, Says Mrs. Sanger </title>
				<title type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Oct. 11, 1922, p. 24</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control clinics"/>
		<index level1="conferences" level2="international0"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Japs Formed Birth Control Clinics, Says Mrs. Sanger</head>
		<p>"American missionaries of all religious denominations are practicing birth control in
			<place>Japan</place>, but in <place>China</place> they have large families," <q who="BDE">declared Mrs. Margaret
				Sanger, founder of the <org>American Birth Control League</org>, who has just
				returned from a propaganda trip of several months, during which she visited
					<place>Hawaii</place>, Japan, China,<place>
					Egypt</place>, <place>Arabia</place>, <place>Austria</place>,
					<place>Italy</place>, <place>France</place> and <place>England</place></q>.</p>
		<p>"I was warmly welcomed everywhere, especially in Japan, once I obtained admission to the
			country," <q who="BDE">said Mrs. Sanger.</q> "My lectures were well attended and
			committees on birth control established. I established a league in <place
				reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> with a clinic and branches in <place
				reg="Kobe, Japan">Kobe</place> and <place reg="Kyoto, Japan">Kyoto</place>; also in
				<place reg="Peking, China">Peking</place> and <place reg="Honolulu, HI"
				>Honolulu</place>.</p>
		<p>"The difficulty I had in entering Japan was due to the fact that the government had an
			idea I was sent by the <place>United States</place> to reduce Japan's birth rate and so
			weaken her army. The present population of Japan is 57,000,000 and the military wants a
			population of 100,000,000. However, when I made it clear that my own government took the
			same attitude towards me and that my object was to reduce the birth rate in every
			country in the world, they let me in. My meetings were called under the auspices of the
			best educated and most cultivated Japanese and through an interpreter I lectured on the
			population in Japan and all nations.</p>
		<p>"In <place reg="London, England">London</place> I acted as president of the general
			section of the <org reg="International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference, 5th"
				>International Conference on Birth Control</org>, where delegates from all countries
			assembled to discuss ways and means to make birth control a legal and social factor in
			family life in every country in the world.</p>
		<p>"<person reg="Wells, H.G.">H. G. Wells</person> presided at the public meeting of the
			Conference, and others who took a prominent part were <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand"
				>Lord Dawson</person>, the <person reg="George V (England)">King</person>'s
			physician; <person reg="Cox, Harold">Harold Cox</person>, former M.P.; Prof. <person
				reg="Keynes, John Maynard">John Maynard Keynes</person>, the well-known economist,
			and Prof. <person reg="Macbride, Ernest William.">E. W. MacBride</person>, who officially
			represented the <org>British Eugenics Society</org>."</p>
		<p><q who="BDE">Mrs. Sanger will be welcomed home at a meeting in <org>Carnegie Hall</org>,
					<place reg="New York, NY">Manhattan</place>, on Oct. 30</q>.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
