<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-15 JC transcribed and encoding</prepDate><prepDate>2015-05-27 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-01-14">14 Jan 1923</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Longer Honeymoons and Happier Wives 100 Years From Now</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422045</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="Journal">San Francisco Chronicle</title>, Jan. 14, 1923, p. 10</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control" level2="mainstreaming of"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Longer Honeymoons and Happier Wives 100 Years From Now</head>
		<byline>By MARGARET SANGER<lb/>Leading Birth Control Advocate</byline>

		<p>Birth control will have become a part of education in health and hygiene. Women
			especially will be keen in demanding it. They will realize that it is a foundation of
			freedom and intellectual development for them. Women cannot make real progress today so
			long as they are haunted by the fear of undesired pregnancy.</p>
		<p>The results, in much shorter time than for or five generations, will be happier homes,
			greater mutual respect between husband and wife, honeymoons lasting two or three years
			before children arrive, with husband and wife thoroughly equilibrated to one another,
			because there has been for mutual understanding and development before parenthood is
			entered upon. There will be far more consideration for the mother and more understanding
			of her needs, with the result of better health and development for the infant, as well
			as greater comfort for the mother. Four or five generations will develop new men and
			women with finer susceptibilities, nobler sentiments toward each other and a worthier
			sense of responsibility toward the race.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
