<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-08-19 CH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-09-01 EK update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-11-15">15 Nov 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Letter to the Editor of the New York
				Times</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422076</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger's Opinion</title>, <title type="journal">New
					York Times</title>, Nov. 19, 1921, p 12</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>

		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger's letter was written in response to an editorial note published
			in the <title type="journal">New York Times</title>, which likened the behavior of birth
		control supporters at <org>Town Hall</org> to "a crowd of anarchists," who "started a riot--not a
			very fierce riot," and "gave the police justification for making against them the
			technical charge of disorderly conduct." (See <title type="article">Topics of the
				Times</title>, <title type="journal">New York Times</title>, Nov. 15, 1921, p. 15.) </p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonments"/>
		<index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="arrests, trials, and imprisonments"/>
		<index level1="Town Hall raid"/>
		<index level1="law breaking and direct action" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger's Opinion</head>
		<p rend="italics">To the Editor of the <title type="journal">New York Times</title></p>
		<p>In your editorial this morning, Nov. 15, you criticize the action of the birth control
			advocates who were arrested Sunday night at the <org>Town Hall</org> for not obeying the
			police when they told them to leave the hall. You further state that there is a legal
			way to adjust these matters, and that one has redress in the courts.</p>
		<p>Do you realize in making such statements that they are inconsistent with the facts of the
			case? Do you realize that the <person reg="Donohue, Thomas">officer</person> who placed
			me under arrest had absolutely no right or reason to enter that hall and to prohibit my
			addressing an audience? This was verified by the dismissal of the case before the
				<person reg="Corrigan, Joseph E.">Judge</person> the following morning.</p>
		<p>Had I left the hall in obedience to the deputy command, I would have had nothing upon
			which to go into the courts for a decision. It was necessary for the deputy to make an
			arrest in order to get a right interpretation of the law in this case.</p>
		<p>I think your criticism of our meeting was very unjust and does not stand up at all for
			the principle of right which is the essential thing that this <org
				reg="United States Government">Government</org> is based upon. </p>
		<closer>MARGARET SANGER.<dateline><lb/><place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>,
					<date value="1921-11-15">Nov. 15, 1921</date>.</dateline></closer>
	</docBody>
</doc>
