<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014-06-24 MM transcribe and encode </prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-08 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-09 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-07-10 EK correct proof and update index</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-07-08 MC transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-01-26">26 Jan 1923</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Excerpts from Speech to the Hagerstown Woman's Club</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422014</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Makes Plea For Birth Control Before A Large
					Audience Here </title>, <title type="journal">Morning Herald
				(Hagerstown</title>, Jan. 27, 1923, pp. 1 and 3.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="HMH">Hagerstown Morning Herald</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke at <org>Stouffer's Dance Academy</org> on behalf of the <org>Woman's Club of
				Halfway</org> after the <org reg="Young Women's Christian Association">YWCA</org>
			refused to allow her. For a a statement likely drawn from this speech see <xref
				from="422013.xml">"Statement on Flappers</xref>," Jan. 27, 1923.</p>
		<index level1="birth rate"/>
		<index level1="population size" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="population size" level2="and birth rate"/>
		<index level1="family size" level2="and poverty"/>
		<index level1="family size" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="family size" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="and natural law"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
		<index level1="client letters"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Makes Plea For Birth Control Before A Large Audience Here</head>
		<p>"Don't let prejudice and ignorance wipe out civilization," <q who="HMH">was the plea made
				by Margaret Sanger, <place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, President of the
					<org>American Birth Control League</org>, speaking to one thousand and 68 men
				and women who packed <org reg="Stouffer's Dance Academy">Stouffer's Academy</org>
				last night to hear her speak.</q></p>
		<p><q who="HMH">The "special officers" who <person reg="Bowman, Charles">Mayor
					Bowman</person> said he would have placed in the audience to safeguard the
				morals of the community by what Mrs. Sanger might say on rational parenthood, hid
				themselves well. If any special officers "chaperones" as Mrs. Sanger laughingly
				referred to them, were present they were in plain clothes, and as no one in the
				audience was sufficiently offended to start a riot, the officers did not make
				themselves conspicuous.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="HMH">Only one disturbance occurred during the lecture. Shortly after Mrs. Sanger
				started speaking a young lady was overcome by the closeness of the air and fainted.
				She was quickly revived however and there was no excitement.</q>
		</p>
		<p> "Countries having highest birth rates are those which have not increased in population
			while those having low birth rates--such as <place>Australia</place>--have increased in
			population. Control of the birth rate is an aid to increased population because higher
			death rates always acompany large birth rates, the speaker explained. Prejudice and
			ignorance are the two factors fighting the movement to allow control of the birth rate,
			and eventually will lead back to a degenerate civilization."</p>
		<p>"The world is divided into two groups--not the rich and the poor--but the small family
			group and the the large family group. In small families is found self-reliance,
			self-respect, happiness, leisure, comfort: the children in small families attend school
			and college and usually fill the highest positions in church and state."</p>
		<p>"On the other hand is the large family group where is found misery, ignorance, poverty,
			sickness, child labor--this misery perpetuating itself in increasing numbers."</p>
		<p>"For the alleviating of this suffering a whole social system has been erected, with
			thousands of social service workers employed devoting their lives to trying to ease the
			misery brought about by the unwise and endless reproduction."</p>
		<p>"More than 90% of children who die in infancy are of poverty or neglect, and yet there
			are no steps taken to prevent the parents of those children from bringing into the world
			300,000 more children to die of poverty and neglect the next year."</p>
		<p>"The trouble is," <q who="HMH">said Mrs. Sanger,</q> "we don't get at the real cause of
			human misery. We are like an ostrich who sticks his head in the sand and refuses to face
			facts."</p>
		<p>"I would like to see a civilization where parenthood is a privilege," <q who="HMH">she
				said.</q></p>
		<p>"Birth control is the keynote of a new social awakening. It is a principle interlocked
			with the spiritual progress of the race. Nature has always been a most ruthless advocate
			of birth control. Nature's methods are famine and pestilence and scourge and wars."</p>
		<p>"No wonder the world is in this state of chaos. We have got to put a check upon the
			growing population of the feeble minded, insane and diseased, until the world catches
			up."</p>
		<p><q who="HMH">Answering the arguments put forth by opponents of the move, Mrs. Sanger
				said:</q></p>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Answer Arguments.</head>
			<p>"They say it is 'against the laws of nature.' So is shaving against the laws of
				nature." <q who="HMH">(much laughter from the audience.)</q> "So is walking on two
				feet instead of all fours against the laws of nature. So is sailing in boats, and
				flying in the air, against the laws of nature."</p>
			<p> "But, if self-preservation is the first law of nature, then birth control is within
				nature's laws, for self-preservation depends on birth control."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HMH">Answering the argument that birth control would increase immorality,
					Mrs. Sanger said that of all the thousands of woman who have come to her for
					advice, there has never been an unmarried girl ask for information.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Morality From Character, Not Fear.</head>
			<p>"It is an insult to women, and an insult to Christianity to say that, if women are
				not capable of standing on their own inner strength of character, the generations of
				Christian teachings have failed. It is a weak morality that is moral because of fear
				of the consequences. People have to be taught the proper use of knowledge. They can
				be safeguarded only by the firmness, the intelligence, the strength within
				them."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="HMH">Mrs. Sanger was introduced by <person reg="Morningstar, Marie E.">Mrs.
						Morningstar</person>, president of the <org>Woman's Club of Halfway</org>,
					under whose auspices she spoke. The lecturer carried a corsage of violets and
					roses presented by the Club of Halfway.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="HMH">During the speech there was strict attention and hearty applause.
					People sat in the benches which line the walls of the <org>Stouffer's
						Academy</org>, they crowded into the tiny balcony where Prof. <person
						reg="Stouffer, Frank B.">Stouffer</person> keeps pianos and old records and
					victrolas, they stood in the back of the hall and sat on the steps.
						<person>Prof. Stouffer</person>, who offered his dancing academy after the
						<org reg="Young Women's Christian Association">Y.W.C.A.</org> had refused to
					allow Mrs. Sanger to speak, said that there had been exactly 1068 admission. The
					crowd lined the street before the First Hose Company building long before the
					doors were open, and in the audience were representative men and women of the
					cultured, intelligent type.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Many Inquiries.</head>
			<p>"Are people interested in the subject," <q who="HMH">Mrs. Sanger was asked.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="HMH">In reply, she told of letters received by her from women all over the
					country, averaging more than 1000 a day.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"These letters, coming for the most part from poor mothers of the tenements, the
				factories and the workshops--have to go unanswered because a Federal statute forbids
				the giving of such information through the mails."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
