<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-21 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 LH correct tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1930-12-28">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">28 Dec 1930</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Birth Control Clinics and the Depression</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422053</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Clinic Taxed by Depression</title>, <title
					type="journal"> The Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, 28 Dec 1930, p. 6 </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE"> The Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Comstock, Anthony"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="birth rate"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control Clinic Taxed by Depression</head>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE"> Birth Control derives new significance as a result of the change in
				economic conditions, in the opinion of Margaret Sanger, director of the <org
					reg="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau"> Clinical Research Bureau</org>.
				She declares that the number of patients at the clinic,whose husbands are among the
				jobless, has increased 65 percent during the last few months.</q>
		</p>
		<p> "We find particularly an increased number of women patients among the very poor
			classes," <q who="BDE"> Mrs. Sanger says,</q>"while the number of our regular patients
			steadily increases. We are handling from 1,500 to 1,800 cases a month at present and are
			running steadily three weeks behind in taking care of appointments." </p>
		<p> "I feel that this entire unsettled economic condition is definitely tied up with over
			population," <q who="BDE"> Mrs. Sanger asserts, </q> "and I am particularly pleased to
			see our work increasing at this time. Within the last 20 years we have displaced
			thousands of men with machines. The result is that we have an overproduction of
			population."</p>
		<div>
			<head> Need Lower Birth Rate</head>
			<p>"We could very easily do with a tremendous reduction of the birth rate in this
				country, as well as a further restriction of immigration during the next 10 years.
				In that time, we could absorb the present population, which is glutting the labor
				market today."</p>
			<p>"I feel that both national and international welfare are bound up in the population
				problem. A nation with surplus man-power is one suffering with economic depression
				and restlessness. One cannot forget the assertion of the veterans that they would
				rather be in the trenches than in the breadlines." </p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE"> Mrs. Sanger thinks religious opposition to her work is decreasing, and
					that women of all faiths are about equality represented among the patients at
					the clinic.</q>
			</p>
			<p> "There has been a change of attitude, too, on the part of the average woman toward
				our work," <q who="BDE"> she says.</q> "Women of all classes now come to the bureau
				for advice."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE"> As head of the <org> National Committee on Federal Legislation for
						Birth Control</org>, Mrs. Sanger predicts that the efforts to get a repeal
					of the <name type="law" reg="United States Criminal Code, Section 211"> Comstock
						laws</name>, which prohibit the sending of contraceptive information through
					the mails, will be renewed in the next session of <org
						reg="United States Congress"> Congress</org>.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head> Fights for Principles </head>
			<p> "I am fighting for the repeal of those laws partly because of the principles
				involved and partially because of their potentialities," <q who="BDE"> she said.</q>
				"As things stand now, doctors can get birth control to be bootlegged, and that is
				not self-respecting. I shall protest against the Federal laws in Congress, on the
				ground that they interfere with the rights of individuals." </p>
			<p> " Every physician at some time needs to have birth control information, to pass it
				on to his patients, but unless he gets that information in his medical school-- and
				that is very rare- he has no means under the present laws of procuring it other than
				by bootlegging methods, The booting methods may be followed, or we may repeal the
				law, come out in the open and go along intelligently with science. I prefer the
				latter method, and I believe economic conditions such as we are facing now emphasize
				the necessity for these doctrines." </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head> Old Feud Smoulders</head>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE"> The controversy between the <org>National Committee on Federal
						Legislation for Birth Control </org>, headed by Mrs. Sanger, and the <org
						reg="American Birth
							Control League"> American birth Control
						League</org>, headed by <name reg="Jones, Eleanor Dwight">Mrs. F. Robertson
						Jones</name>, which broke out last year over questions of policy, is still
					smouldering, Mrs. Sanger said.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="BDE"> The league, through its president, has repudiated the work of the
					national committee, asserting that</q> "contrary to the prevalent understanding,
				the Federal law does not actually interfere with our program, as it leaves
				physicians free to give contraceptive advice orally both in their private practice
				and in their clinics."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE"> Commenting on the league's position, Mrs. Sanger said:</q>
			</p>
			<p> "They forget that unless physicians can get reliable information themselves, they
				cannot give it to their patients."</p>
			<p> "The Federal laws most decidedly interfere with the getting and giving of
				information by physicians and, as long as they exist, our work is hampered."</p>
			<p> "I am not discouraged by this controversy between myself and the league, however.
				Our work has been like a growing cell. It gt to a certain point as a unit, and then
				it divided. We are still the same body, however."</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
