<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/06/17 AS</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-03 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-03 CH recheck tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-03-19 EK cprrect proof and update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-06-02"><supplied resp="MSPP">02 Jun 1916</supplied></docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Speech to the Friday Morning Club</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422000</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Start Talk on Taboo Topic</title>, <title type="journal">Los
					Angeles Times</title>, June 3, 1916, p. 112</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="LAT">Los Angeles Times</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>The last three paragraphs, which do not pertain to Sanger's speech, were omitted
			by the editors.</p>
		<index level1="abortion" level2="birth control and"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="class-based"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="access to"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="working classes" level2="and family size"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
		<index level1="mentally diseased or disabled" level2="as social burdens"/>
		<index level1="unfit to reproduce" level2="as social burdens"/>
		</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>START TALK ON TABOO TOPIC.</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>	<q who="LAT">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, the luncheon guest at the <org>Friday Morning
						Club</org> yesterday, spoke frankly and clearly on the once-taboo subject of
					birth control. It was for her activities in this connection that she has been
					indicted by the Federal authorities.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="LAT">Mrs. Sanger said that the knowledge essential to birth control should
					be spread--broadcast among the poorer population and that the laws restricting
					the dissemination of such knowledge should be repealed as unfair and inimical to
					the best interests of the <place reg="United States">nation</place>. Her
					contention was that through lack of knowledge the women of the poorer classes
					are bearing cruel and unwarranted burdens and bringing large broods of
					feeble-minded and otherwise seriously-handicapped children into the world, whom
					they are unable to support and eventually become a burden on the taxpayers.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="LAT">Mrs. Sanger insists that the scientists and doctors, the majority of
					the</q> "great thinkers" <q who="LAT">are in accord with the doctrine of birth
					control, and that among those classes where the information is obtainable,
					immorality is less rife and children better cared for, in that people can then
					afford to marry younger and avoid the production of a family until they are in a
					position to take care of them. She has had, she said, endorsements of her
					propaganda from such men as <person reg="Wells, H.G.">H. G. Wells</person> and
						<person reg="Bennett, Arnold">Arnold Bennett.</person></q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">CALLS IT UNFAIR.</head>

			<p>"The women of the working classes seek this knowledge and it is unfair to keep it
				from them when the higher strata of society, the very ones, in many cases, whose
				influence keeps the restrictions on the statute books, have long since practiced its
				advantages," <q who="LAT">she declared. She cited many cases of women who bear vast
					broods of children, only to see them die in child-birth or live in feeble
					health, to whom such knowledge would be an inestimable blessing. The present
					laws, Mrs. Sanger said, breed an army of harpy abortionists and create an
					unthinkable state of affairs, which a free dissemination of simple facts would
					do away with. Women, she maintained, are more than justified in many cases,
					under so many conditions, in availing themselves of such facts. She had nothing
					but condemnation for what she insists is a policy of reckless and careless
					breeding. To this door she laid the responsibility for what she said to be the
					fact that, in proportion to the population, the United States breeds few great men. This her hearers considered a weak point in her
					argument, for, they pointed out, European countries cannot be said to encourage
					birth-control, but rather to frown upon it even more emphatically than
					ourselves. They also questioned the accuracy of the comparison.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="LAT">Mrs. Sanger advocates the distribution of clear, concise pamphlets and
					clinic lectures for those women unable to read. She mentioned one mining
					district in which she deliberately violated the law by distributing pamphlets of
					her own among the miners, who assured her they were disappointed at the small
					supply which only enabled them to give them to women having more than nine
					children already.</q>
			</p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
