<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-28 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 LH edit</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-07-15 MC correct transcript</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-03-29">29 Mar 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Is Modern Marriage Conducive to Happiness?</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422078</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Finds Men Shy in Love Affairs</title>, <title type="journal"
					>Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, Mar 30, 1921, p. 23</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE">The Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This speech was not found; newspaper coverage was used instead. For another speech of the
			same title, see <xref from="422079.xml">Is Modern Marriage Conducive to
			Happiness</xref>, Jan. 19, 1921</p>
		<index level1="marriage"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="age at"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="and procreation"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="marriage" level2="reforms"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>FINDS MEN SHY IN LOVE AFFAIRS</head>
		<p>"Men of today are more shy than women in their love affairs," <q who="BDE"> said Mrs.
				Margaret Sanger last night at the <org>Broadway Casino</org>, <place
					reg="Brooklyn, NY">790 Broadway</place>. This shyness of men was not evident in
				the forum that followed her lecture on the subject, "Is Modern Marriage Conducive to
				Happiness?" All the questions were asked by young men.</q></p>
		<p> "The women of <place reg="United States">America</place> today differ very much
			organically from their mothers, grandmothers and great-grandmothers," <q who="BDE"> Mrs.
				Sanger continued.</q> "They are more temperamental and more fundamental in their
			primitive desires. They can't bear as much pain as their mothers. All the bubbling,
			joyous nature of a girl of 18 is but a part of her development."</p>
		<p> "A love of pretty clothes and of color is a natural expression. Oftentimes a girl who is
			deprived of the frivolity of this age by early marriage and motherhood at the age of 30
			or 35, shocks her neighbors by doing all kinds of things ordinarily done by a girl of
			18. This is just nature having its innings. Women are mothers only to their children. If
			we lived in a real civilized social state we would make parenthood a great privilege.
			The last fight of all the freedom of women will be that of freeing her from the slavery
			of married life as it is at present." </p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE"> In birth control lies much of the solution for the unhappiness of
				marriages, according to Mrs. Sanger. Lack of art in love making, crudeness on the
				part of men, and too early marriages were all given as reasons by her for the
				failure of many marriages.</q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
