<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-28 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1933-02-17">17 Feb 1933</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Senate Judiciary Committee</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422086</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Advocate of Birth Control Rejoices</title>, <title
					type="journal">Bluefield Daily Telegraph</title>, Feb 18 1933</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDT">Bluefield Daily Telegraph</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="United States Congress" level2="Senate"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>ADVOCATE OF BIRTH CONTROL REJOICES</head>
		<dateline><place reg="Washington, DC">Washington</place>, <date value="1933-02-17"> Feb.
				17</date> 9<org reg="Associated Press">AP</org>)--</dateline>
		<p><q who="BDE">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, campaigner for a law to legalize dissemination of
				birth control information, today bailed the results of a poll of the <org
					reg="United States Senate Judiciary
				Committee">senate judiciary
					committee</org> as a big advance for her cause and</q> "the best showing thus
			far made."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE"> The result was nine against, six for, and two not voting.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BDE">Listed as voting for such legislation were Chairman <person
					reg="Norris, George
			W.">Norris</person>, and Senators <person
					reg="Robinson, Arthur Raymond">Robinson</person> of <place>Indiana</place>;
					<person reg="Hastings, Daniel O.">Hastings</person>, <person
					reg="Schall, Thomas David">Schall</person>, <person
					reg="Schuyler, Karl Cortlandt">Schuyler</person> and <person
					reg="Black, Hugo L.">Black</person>. Against it were Senators <person
					reg="H&eacute;bert, Felix">H&eacute;rbert</person>, <person
					reg="Austin, Warren Robinson">Austin</person>, <person reg="Ashurst, Henry Fountain"
					>Ashurst</person>, <person reg="Walsh, David Ignatius">Walsh</person>, <person
					reg="King, William Henry">King</person>, <person reg="Stephens, Hubert Durrett"
					>Stephens</person>, <person reg="Dill, Clarence Cleveland">Bill</person>,
					<person reg="Bratton, Sam Gilbert">Bratton</person>, and <person
					reg="Neely, Matthew Mansfield">Neely</person>. Those reported as not voting were
				Senators <person reg="Borah, William Edgar">Borah</person> and <person
					reg="Blaine, John James">Blaine</person>.</q>
		</p>
		<p> "The poll by the judiciary shows an increasing understanding of what the subject means,
			and better than all it shows an increase of courage on the part of legislators to
			publicly go on record for what they think in private," <q who="BDE">said Mrs.
				Sanger.</q> "this is the best vote we ever had."</p>
		<p>"I have made a most careful check of that committee, all married men, and find that among
			the seventeen members are thirty-four children, an average of two children each." </p>
		<p>"Some have more, several have none, but the low average is a point, I think, that bears
			on the courage of public expression of personal opinion."</p>
		<p><q who="BDE"> Mrs. Sanger said that in the </q> "long picture" <q who="BDE"> of her
				cause, she counted the progress she felt she had made in congress the high point of
				a</q> "most victorious year."</p>
		<p>"No longer can there be a claim there is an overabundance in the land and we need an
			increasing population to consume it, in the face of the <org>American Federation of
				Labor</org> estimates that twelve million are jobless, forty five millions in
			poverty."</p>
		<p> "I confidently predict that within five years it will be unnecessary for physicians to
			bootleg information and supplies on which the health and happiness of a whole nation
			depends."</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
