<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-28 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 LH edits</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-02-03">3 Feb 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Brownsville Labor Lyceum Questions and Answers</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422080</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Evades Lyceum Hecklers</title>, <title
					type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title> Feb 3, 1921, p. 9</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Christianity" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="publicity"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="MS on"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MRS. SANGER EVADES LYCEUM HECKLERS</head>
		<p><q who="BDE">"Were will the new birth control clinic be located?" was a question put to
				Mrs. Margaret Sanger last night at the <org>Brownsville Labor Lyceum</org>,
				following her lecture in which she had said it was hoped to open a clinic soon, </q>
			"law or no law." </p>
		<p> "That's an up-to-date questions," <q who="BDE"> she said.</q> "I don't think it will be
			in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY"> Brownsville</place>. I don't like your police here." <q
				who="BDE"> She announced that she would take the risk of giving information in
				urgent cases, if those desiring it would call upon her at home in <place
					reg="New York, NY">Manhattan</place>. </q></p>
		<p><q who="BDE"> There were several hecklers in the audience. To these Mrs. Sanger gave but
				scant attention. One questioner asked he if there were not an element of
				perniciousness in placing birth control above all other social issues.</q> "Men
			cannot work for the goal of their ideals, the emancipation of the human race, alone. No
			free man was ever born of a slave mother. There is no greater slavery than maternal
			slavery."</p>
		<p> "The Church is as great a menace as legal barriers to birth control," <q who="BDE">
				continued the speaker.</q> "Countries where birth control is legal still have the
			Church to contend with. The Church's main job is saving souls, and it wants plenty of
			souls to save. It is said by the Church that birth control is unnatural. Isn't celibacy
			more unnatural? We have persons who talk in glowing terms of large families as honor
			guests at our functions. Jails, the courts, and penitentiaries await those who wish to
			perform a real service and who try to limit children." </p>
		<p>"The upper and middle classes have done pretty well with birth control for 30 to 40
			years. If we can't do better we might use their methods. Those who say the subject of
			birth control is sordid and lacking in common sense."</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
