<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 HD transcribed and encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-30 HD enter corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1925-12-03">3 Dec 1925</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Necessity of Birth Control</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422049</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Addresses Social Problems Club</title>, <title
					type="journal">Barnard Bulletin</title>, Dec. 11, 1925, p. 4</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BB">Barnard Bulletin</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger's speech was not found; newspaper coverage was used instead. The last paragraph,
			regarding unrelated upcoming events, was not included.</p>
		<index level1="mortality rates"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="infant" level3="American"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal” level3=”American"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="and war"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MRS. SANGER ADDRESSES SOCIAL PROBLEMS CLUB</head>
		<p>
			<q who="BB"><org>Earl Hall</org> was filled to its capacity, and many people were turned
				away on Thursday afternoon, December 3rd, when Margaret Sanger addressed the
				audience on the necessity of Birth Control. Before introducing the speaker, <person
					reg="Montague, William Peperell">Professor William Peperell Montague</person>,
				who presided, remarked that Birth Control is essential to make parenthood voluntary,
				not accidental; and to regulate the population--one of the greatest causes of war.
			</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BB">Mrs. Sanger defined birth control as the conscious control of birth rate by
				scientific means. According to the Malthusian theory, the natural increase of
				population must be checked, and it is only logical to decrease the birth
				rate--rather than increase the death rate--the only other alternative.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BB">No census has been taken on the subject, but it is quite obvious that
				poverty, disease, high percentage of infant and maternal mortality, slums, and
				various other evils are most usually the outcome of large families; and small
				families bear the burdens of taxation and charity of the larger ones.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BB">In the <place>United States</place> last year, 200,000
				infants died before one year old. Milk stations, visiting nurses,
				clinics--everything conceivable to reduce the mortality of infants is being done
				today and they do succeed--but at a terrible cost, for the basic reason is one of
				ignorance. Year after year, these 200,000 mothers and fathers are kept
				ignorant--with the result of an additional 200,000 infants dying the following
				year.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BB">Over-population is at the root of the problem of Child Labor; for in
				families where the children come too fast, they are necessarily forced to feed and
				clothe themselves. Until the population is regulated, there will never be peace
				between nations. Over-population seems to be the root of all evil.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BB">In answer to the argument that birth control would bring about race suicide,
				Mrs. Sanger stated seven rules:</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="BB">
				<list>
					<item>(1) No people who have transmissible diseases should have children.</item>
					<item> (2) No woman suffering from temporary disease should bear children. </item>
					<item> (3) If normal parents produce subnormal children, they should have no
						more. </item>
					<item> (4) There should be a space of at least three years between children. </item>
					<item> (5) Maturity should be reached before motherhood. </item>
					<item> (6) Parents should not have children they will not be able to support. </item>
					<item> (7) Women should have no children until two years after marriage.</item>
				</list>
			</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q>Birth Control is not a question to be generally decided upon, but one of individual
				application. The only solution to the problem is the establishment of scientific
				clinics where parents may come for advice (in existence in <place reg="Netherlands"
					>Holland</place> and <place>England</place>). Mrs. Sanger concluded with the
				statement that women must be free from the bondage of maternity before we can go
				forward to the emancipation of human races. </q>
		</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
