<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 LH edits</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH clean up</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
			<person reg="Vance, Don">Don Vance</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1952-12-31">31 Dec 1952</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Tucson Speech on Japan and Population</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422064</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Slee Deplores Japan's Million Abortions Yearly</title>,
					<title type="journal">Tucson Daily Citizen</title>, Dec. 31, 1952, p. 18</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name reg="TDC">Tucson Daily Citizen</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1952(Japan)"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Slee Deplores Japan's Million Abortions Yearly</head>
		<byline> By Don Vance</byline>
		<p><q who="TDC"><place>Japan</place>, a land of </q> "exquisite courtesy, beauty and charm,"
				<q who="TDC"> and a land of </q> "shockingly high" <q who="TDC"> infant mortality,
				of shrines and temples and 1,000,000 abortions yearly--</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC"> This Japan is the subject of Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee's first report to
				the friends and sponsors of the <org
					reg="International Confernce on Planned Parenthood, 3rd">international planned
					parenthood conference</org>. The report covers the first segment of a two months
				trip the far cast that ended in <place>India</place> with the first full-circle <org
					reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation">organization</org> for
				furtherance of the birth control throughout the world.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC"> Mrs. Slee, who became co-director and co-president of the organization,
				the <org>International Committee on Planned Parenthood</org>, was invited to speak
				about her work in Japan by the <org reg="Mainichi Press">Mainichi press</org> there.
				She had been refused admittance during the occupation period.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC"> She spent 10 days in conferences, making speeches and observing conditions
				throughout the Japanese cities and countryside.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"Japan," <q who="TDC"> she concluded,</q> "is making a heroic effort to adjust herself to
			postwar conditions. In 1922 her territory was too small to feed and supply her people
			and today she has less territory to maintain the increase of 34,000,000. The questions
			of decreased birthrate, family limitation, population control, birth control and family
			planning are being discussed everywhere."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC"> Mrs. Slee noted that two projects were operating. One sends nurses into
				three villages to talk to the parents and teach methods of contraception. The second
				is that of the <org reg="Population Problems Research Council">population problems
					research group</org> conducted by the Mainichi press.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"the need of a contraceptive, simple to adjust, cheap and harmless is almost the greatest
			need in Japan if she is to save herself from the consequences of an increased
			population," <q who="TDC">reported Mrs. Slee.</q></p>
		<p> "Abortions, stillbirths, infant mortality are increasing," <q who="TDC"> continued the
				birth control expert.</q> "The cruel necessity of these is the only <gap
				extent="one
				word" reason="illegible"/> she has to adjust population to arable
			land."</p>
		<p> "It is reported that over 1,000,000 abortions took place in 1951. These are legal under
			the law. It is unfortunate that in the modern contraceptive to immunize the ovum has not
			been developed to meet the world-wide need. It is perhaps, the only solution to the
			growing problem of Japan's population."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC"> These were her conclusions, but the report also was filled with the beauty
				of the country, as well as the interest of the people in her project.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC"> Mrs. Slee tells, at one point, of traveling through the temples and
				gardens of the old <place reg="Kyoto, Japan">Imperial city of Kyoto</place>.
				Again she describes a trek through the slums of <place reg="Tokyo, Japan"
					>Tokyo</place> by writing; </q>
		</p>
		<p> "People flocked out of their shop and doorways, thousands of them. Children in school
			yards ran into the street to learn what was going on. 'Sanger is here: She says no
			abortions... Sanger is here... she says no abortions.'" </p>
		<p> "It is a sad thing," <q who="TDC"> she observed,</q> "that there are no clinics, no free
			places for these women. Desire for birth control is surely far ahead of the materials
			and technique to meet that need."</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
