<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH enter corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-12-21">21 Dec 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Intelligence, Not Numbers, U.S. Need</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422067</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Washington Times</title>, Dec. 21, 1922, p. 20</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>No draft versions were found.</p>
		<index level1="population control" level2="government policies"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="population policies"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Intelligence, Not Numbers, U.S. Need</head>
		<byline>by Margaret Sanger</byline>
		<p>If the population of the <place>United States</place> increases during the past century
			we shall have a population in 2033 of 1,000,000,000, of half as much as the earth's
			present population.</p>
		<p>If the population of earth increases in like proportion, it would run up to more than
			10,000,000,000. It is doubtful whether a food supply to feed such masses could be
			produced.</p>
		<p>The population of such countries as <place>Japan</place> and the United States have been
			increasing quite rapidly. In other countries, such as <place>China</place>, it is
			standing still. And in certain portions of <place>Europe</place> it is receding. Hence
			it is difficult to forecast for the whole world with accuracy.</p>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Danger Recognized</head>
			<p>The increase of population in the United States has been 110 per cent in forty years,
				the result of flooded immigration. The dangers of the rapid increase have been
				recognized and now we have selected immigration.</p>
			<p>If our population and the population of the earth were to run ahead in proportion to
				the figures quoted above the result would be catastrophic for the race. It would
				mean a race where the struggle for existence would wipe out culture and
				intelligence.</p>
			<p>If, however, the United States combines selective immigration with selective
				breeding, the average of intelligence, at present fourteen years, could be raised to
				twenty-five years at the end of a century. There would also be an increase in our
				population, but not a flooded increase.</p>
			<p>Every grown person in our country would have the intelligence of present day
				university graduates. Each, for instance, would be able to understand and enjoy
					<person reg="Wells, H. G.">Wells</person>' "<title type="book">Outline of
					History</title>."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Quantity or Quality</head>
			<p>The standards of intelligence throughout the world could likewise be raised by
				selective breeding. The burning question for the United States and world during the
				coming century will be, "Do we want quantity or quality?"</p>
			<p>In all the world there is a battle between two groups. One represents the scientists,
				the thinkers, the poets, the idealists, forward-looking, practical people. These
				want a selected population of raised intelligence.</p>
			<p>Massed against them is the militarist-commercial group, which wants vastly increased
				populations, increased territory and the wars that accompany them.</p>
			<p>This group includes the majority of the men who make up most of the governments of
				the earth. They are self-centered, backward-looking people whose social
				consciousness and vision are undeveloped. </p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Japan as Example</head>
			<p>Japan at present offers perhaps the best example of this battle. The military party
				there wants to build up the present population of 67,000,000 to 100,000,000. Then
				they believe they can demand more territory from the world and get it. Without war,
				if possible, for they have learned a lesson from <place>Germany</place>.</p>
			<p>But their theories are questioned every day by another group that grows rapidly in
				Japan. This group challenges with:</p>
			<p>Why not be satisfied with a population of 50,000,000 and bend your energies to
				raising the quality of the people you already possess.</p>
			<p>Man is supposed to reach fullness of development at twenty-five. Really, he achieves
				only physical development at that age. There are two other factors in human
				development, the mental and the psychic. By 2023 man could be so improved that he
				would present a harmonious, full development of the three functions.</p>

		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
