<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-25 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1931-04-30">30 Apr 1931</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP"/>Brooklyn Assembly of Jewish Women Organizations
				Address</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422048</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Clinic Is Urged for Brooklyn</title>, <title
					type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>, May 1, 1931, p. 21</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BDE">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
			<name id="PETDO">Petchesky, Dora D.</name>
			<name id="MCGRI">McGoldrick, Rita Connell</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger's speech was not found; newspaper coverage was used instead.</p>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="establishment of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control Is Urged For Brooklyn</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">A birth-control clinic for <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">Brooklyn</place>,
					similar to that in <place reg="New York, NY">Manhattan</place>, was urged
					yesterday by Mrs. Margaret Sanger, director of the New York clinic.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Mrs. Sanger spoke of the need of the Brooklyn women, many of whom are
					now being treated in Manhattan.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Her address followed a meeting of the <org>Assembly of Jewish Women's
						Organizations</org> at the <org>Union Temple</org>, 17 Eastern Parkway.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="PETDO">"We are planning to take the matter under consideration,"</q>
				<q who="BDE">said <person reg="Petchesky, Dora D.">Mrs. Louis Petchesky </person>,
					president of the organization.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="PETDO">"In our next meetings we are going to investigate the possibility of
					starting such a clinic with our assistance."</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Cites Church Action</head>
			<p>"We won the greatest victory so far," <q who="BDE"> said Mrs. Sanger, remarking on
					the recent victories of the movement,</q> "When the <org>Presbyterian General
					Assembly</org> and the <org>Federal Council of Churches of Christ in <place
						reg="United States">America</place></org> both issued statements favoring
				birth control."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Mrs. Sanger debated the question with <person
						reg="McGoldrick, Rita Connell">Mrs. Thomas A. McGoldrick</person>, former
					president of the <org>Catholic Alumnae Association</org>, who took the negative
					side.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">The right to spiritual health and progress of women and of the family
					was pointed out by Mrs. Sanger as she drew a picture of the early years of
					married life.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"We owe to those starting out in life leisure in which to become acquainted, to make
				as much as possible out of their marriage."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">'To Blunder Along'</head>
			<p>"Instead we do what we would never do with a traveler in any other unknown country.
				We send them out with no directions to blunder along as best they can."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Too often, Mrs. Sanger thought, marriage means only parenthood. The
					wife has no sooner left her girlhood behind than she finds herself a mother with
					all a mother's cares.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Stresses Practical Side</head>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">The practical side of birth control, she added, was purely a medical
					one, which should be treated as an individual problem by properly qualified
					persons.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">There are many, Mrs. Sanger believed, who should not have more or any
					children. She said communicable disease and subnormal children as barriers.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">While she considers early marriage desirable, she does not believe that
					a girl under 22 years or a boy under 25 should be parents.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Cites Intellectual Control</head>
			<p>"The intellectual class, the artisan and skilled workmen all have a controlled birth
				rate. Of their fewer children the greater majority grow to maturity and fill the
				best places in society."</p>
			<p>"It is from their pockets that the costs of maintaining the children who should never
				have been born must come. We are today piling up huge debts fro our children and our
				children's children to pay."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Mrs. McGoldrick, mother of seven children, attacked the problem as that
					of a citizen looking ahead.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">More Buried than Born</head>
			<p>
				<q who="MCGRI">"America,"</q>
				<q who="BDE">she said,</q>
				<q who="MCGRI">"has become a decaying nation, burying more humans than it
					produces."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE"> She warned of an</q>
				<q who="MCGRI">imminently serious social problem facing us"</q>
				<q who="BDE">because of the widespread acceptance of birth control and she said the
					so-called intellectual group is shunning children.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Declaring her attitude was not entirely due to the dogmas of her
					family, she asserted</q>
				<q who="MCGRI">widespread birth control has a destructive influence and is tearing
					down something tangible that should not be disturbed."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Mrs. McGoldrick brought out the mingled joys and hardships of
					parenthood and touched on the more practical side of the question.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Cites <place>France</place>, <place reg="Netherlands"
				>Holland</place></head>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">She spoke of the compensation which overshadowed the physical and
					economic strain of a large family. No mother, she believed, would be willing to
					part with one of her family, no matter how numerous it might be.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MCGRI">"The problems of France and Holland,"</q>
				<q who="BDE"> she said,</q>
				<q who="MCGRI"> "both of which have had birth control, show what happens when a
					country concurs in the movement."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="MCGRI"> "In France they are seriously worried over the drop in birth rate.
					In Holland they have rescinded the ten-year-old law because of the spread of
					disease and immortality and the grave drop in the birth rate."</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">She also stated that birth control would open wide the door of</q>
				<q who="MCGRI">"lack of control"</q>
				<q who="BDE">to the youth of the nation.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">In answer to the point that many children were an unfair burden to the
					poor, she explained that many were</q>
				<q who="MCGRI">"gift-edged investments"</q>
				<q who="BDE"> to them.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
