<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-29 CH enter corrected tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-07-15 Ek correct proof and update index</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-10 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-08-02">2 Aug 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">International News Service Interview</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422072</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Says English Women Behind Sisters of U.S.</title>, <title
					type="journal">Springfield (Missouri) Republican</title>, Aug 3, 1922, p.
				3</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SMR">Springfield Missouri Republican</name>
			<name id="WOLCL">Wold, Clara</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="and physicians"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Comstock Laws"/>
		<index level1="birth control legal cases" level2="Crane Decision"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="arrests, trials and imprisonment"/>
		<index level1="Brownsville Clinic" level2="raid"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="women in"/>
		<index level1="England" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="American"/>
		<index level1="physicians" level2="and birth control"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922 (Japan)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922 (China)"/>
		<index level1="sex and sexuality" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="women in"/>
		<index level1="women and girls" level2="freedom and rights of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>SAYS ENGLISH WOMEN BEHIND SISTERS OF U.S.</head>
		<byline>by CLARA WOLD <lb/><org>International News Service</org> Staff
			Correspondent.</byline>
		<dateline><place reg="London, England">LONDON</place>, <date value="1922-08-02">Aug.
				2</date>.--</dateline>
		<div type="section">
			<p>"The English woman is one hundred years behind the American woman in her human and
				scientific attitude towards sex," <q who="SMR">declared Mrs. Margaret Sanger, leader
					of the <org reg="American Birth Control League">American Birth Control
						league</org>, today. We had been listening to vigorous statements made by
						<person reg="Wells, H. G.">H. G. Wells</person> concerning the liberty with
					which Birth control is regarded and discussed in <place>England</place> and the
					narrowness of <place reg="United States">America</place> in her attitude to the
					entire question.</q></p>
			<p>"It is true," <q who="SMR"> said Mrs. Sanger,</q> "that in America we still have laws
				that forbid educational propaganda concerning birth control, but American women have
				broken absolutely from the antiquated domination of the man over woman and are able
				to regard and discuss sex scientifically."</p>
			<p>"English women are so prudish in the free expression of opinion on sex subjects that
				it will take at least one hundred years for them to get out from under the influence
				of unclean and unscientific education."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="WOLCL">I asked her if this education came from the individual men of English
					homes. </q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> Church Teaches Passivity</head>
			<p>"I should say that it comes from the teaching in the church of dutiful passivity on
				the part of women, and also from the traditional belief that woman is the accessory
				of man. American women will not accept such an idea. Not even the American man will
				stand for such an attitude of mind. And this is true no less of the working class
				man than of the intellectuals. The younger Americans have never even considered such
				an idea as the subordination of woman to man and even the foreigners who come to
				America quickly imbibe the American feminist attitude."</p>
			<p>"The strange thing about this attitude is that it does not permit free public
				discussion of the sex question. England already permits before any mixed public
				audience freer discussion by specialists than we can ever hope for. This is probably
				because the laws of England do not forbid such discussion. Anyway it is notable that
				even the women who take part in an English discussion are fundamentally puritanical
				in their expression."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="WOLCL">"And what about the attitude of the English men towards the free
					discussion of sex questions?"</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">English Men Ahead</head>
			<p>"Well, one might say that the men of England are just as far ahead of the American
				men as the women are behind. It is true that the English birth control movement and
				every part of English life, is dominated by men, whereas in America the birth
				control movement has always been led by women and it has been most difficult to get
				man to take any part in it."</p>
			<p>"In the <place reg="Asia">Orient</place>, too, it is the men who will lead the
				movement. Our meetings in <place>Japan</place> and <place>China</place>, where I
				spent three months, were attended by thousands of men--scientists, psychologists,
				medical men, students, intellectuals, rickshaw men, the commonest laborers--and only
				a handful of women. The attitude from the first has been scientific and the Oriental
				man is preparing to introduce the ideas of birth control as the most expedient
				solution of their present economic situation."</p>
			<p>"In England the medical profession has devoted much time to the study and discussion
				of birth control. Such men as <person reg="Dawson, Bertrand E.">Lord
				Dawson</person>, one of the most notable British physicians, and Sir <person
					reg="Barr, James">James Barr</person>, leader of the <org
					reg="British Medical Association">British Medical association</org>, have come
				out frankly as supporters of the birth control movement in the face of condemnation
				of the majority of their profession."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">American Men Sheep-Like</head>
			<p>"In America, the men of the medical profession, characteristically, are more
				sheep-like. They will follow an idea, but they have not the courage to be leaders
				against popular opinion."</p>
			<p>"I have asked men like H. G. Wells and <person reg="Cox,	Harold"> Harold Cox</person>
				and other brilliant thinkers of England why their women are so puritanical--and let
				me say right here that I do not think Americans are ever half so puritanical as the
				English--and I have always been told that the expression of the women on sex
				questions is 'half hypocritical.' The other half is, I suppose, traditional."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="WOLCL">"And what will you do to change the attitude of the medical
					profession in America?" I asked Mrs. Sanger. </q>
			</p>
			<p>"It has been a long struggle of our organization to get medical men who believe in
				birth control to act courageously in dealing with the question. In 1916 I opened a
					<org reg="Brownsville Clinic">clinic</org> in <place reg="Brooklyn, NY">New
					York</place> for the spread of information on the question, I was arrested and
				the clinic was closed on the ground of 'violating the obscenity law.' In 1918 the
				court declared that information could be freely given by any one of the medical
				profession. Ever since then we have waited for the medical men to open a clinic."
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">She Awaits Action.</head>
			<p>"A year ago I promised my board of directors to wait another year for some action
				from the medical men. That year is nearly over and if nothing happens soon I am sure
				the women of America will rise up and begin a new campaign for clinics." </p>
			<p>"America does not follow passive propaganda. We are an aggressive people who like
				aggressive methods, most of all when they are directed against ourselves. And for
				that reason I am sure that unless the medical men take this matter up at once the
				women of America will open clinics, beginning in New York. The first woman arrested
				will be followed by another and another, and it will take America as long to arrest
				all the women who are willing to fight for birth control as it did to arrest all
				those who wanted suffrage."</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
