<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Interview">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-10 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-06-29 CH enter corrected tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-07 CH enter proofreading corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1922-09-05">5 Sept 1922</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Interview with the International News Service</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422070</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Japs Talk Nothing But War, Says Mrs. Margaret Sanger, After Long Tour
					In Behalf of Birth Control</title>, <title type="journal">Santa Cruz Evening News</title>,
				Sept. 7 1922, p. 6</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
			<name id="SCEN">Santa Cruz Evening News</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For a similar statement, see "<xref from="422071.xml">Statement on Japanese Trip</xref>," Aug. 9,
			1952.</p>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1922(Japan)"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="and war"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="effects of"/>
		<index level1="overpopulation" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="politics in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="overpopulation"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>JAPS TALK NOTHING BUT WAR, SAYS MRS. MARGARET SANGER, AFTER LONG TOUR IN BEHALF OF BIRTH
			CONTROL</head>
		<byline> By THOMAS C. WATSON, <org>International News Service</org>
			<lb/>Staff Correspondent</byline>
		<dateline><place reg="London, England">LONDON</place>, <date value="1922-09-05">Sept.
			5</date>.--</dateline>
		<div type="section">
			<p>"They talk war and nothing but war in <place>Japan</place>."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SCEN">This was the lasting impression left on the mind of Mrs. Margaret Sanger, who
					has returned to <place> Europe</place> en route for <place reg="United States">
						America</place> after an extensive tour in the <place reg="Asia">East</place> under
					the aegis of the <org reg="International Birth Control
					Association"> International
						Birth Control association</org>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SCEN">Mrs. Sanger traversed the East propagating an unknown and very delicate subject
					and was accompanied only by her <person reg="Sanger, Grant">twelve-year-old son</person>.
					She returns to Western civilization proud and happy with her accomplishments.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SCEN">None of the old pioneers had been beset with the difficulties that have hampered
					the progress of Mrs. Sanger. In the first place the <org reg="Japan Consulate">Japanese
						Consul</org> at <place reg="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</place>, acting under
					instructions from <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place>, declined to grant Mrs. Sanger
					her vise to enter Japanese territory. Nevertheless, this did not prevent Mrs. Sanger from
					boarding the ship sailing from San Francisco bound for <place reg="Shanghai, China"
						>Shanghai</place>, which was going to make Tokyo en route.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">JAPS HEAR HER SPEAK</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SCEN"> Happily aboard that ship was the Japanese delegation from America returning to
					Japan from the <org reg="Washington Naval Conference"><place reg="Washington, DC"
							>Washington</place> conference</org>. To <person reg="Kato, Keikichi"> Baron
						Kato</person>, chief of the delegation, she made her complaint, and the latter, after
					consulting with <person reg="Hanihara, Masanao">M. Hani Hari</person>, decided to listen
					to a speech from the plucky little American lady on the extremely delicate subject which
					she intended to propagate among the people of the East.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SCEN">So convinced were they after the address that they immediately wirelessed their
					government and suggested that it should let Mrs. Sanger into its country without
					restriction. The reply was that it would allow her in providing she did not give any
					public address. She took a chance and gave the undertaking.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SCEN">Then Mrs. Sanger's friends became annoyed with her, for on her arrival at Tokyo
					all the reporters from the whole of Japan boarded <name type="ship" reg="Taiyo Maru">the
						vessel</name> not with the intention of interviewing the returning Japanese delegation
					on their impressions of Washington, but to interview her on the question of birth
					control.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">WARNED BY AUTHORITIES</head>
			<p>
				<q who="SCEN">On arrival she was again warned by the authorities that she would be debarred
					from addressing a public meeting. Yet immediately she was asked by scores of independent
					societies to address their members on the subject. Naturally she complied. She was also
					obliged to bar the topic of birth control, but she circumvented that by renaming her
					subject "Population and War."</q>
			</p>
			<p>"I thought when I was able to stand up before a Japanese audience that my greatest difficulty
				was over, but I discovered it has just begun," <q who="SCEN">said Mrs. Sanger.</q></p>
			<p>"Every one of my speeches had to be interpreted item by item, and in Japanese it takes exactly
				four times as long as in English. Therefore a speech in English lasting exactly one hour took
				four hours to transpose into Japanese, and I had to stand throughout the whole translation, as
				it would have been discourteous had I sat down. So at the end of every lecture I was in a
				state of complete exhaustion."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">FINDS JAPS INTERESTED</head>
			<p>"I found them most interested in the subject. At first they were skeptical. I had to grope my
				way to find what angle of the situation most appealed to them. It was different from the
				American."</p>
			<p> "You know in America the American husband is just a big baby where the health of his wife is
				concerned, and therefore it was easy to get the sympathy of every American when it was pointed
				out to them that the health of their wives was impaired if they bore over three babies."</p>
			<p>"That angle was lost on the Japs. The health of their wives was nothing to them. They were
				listless when I played on that point. They still have the old Eastern idea that the women are
				merely created for their pleasure and the reproduction of their species." </p>
			<p>"But on the question of economics they were all agog. It is just as expensive to rear and
				educate a large family in Japan as it is in New York, and the matter of cost aroused the
				Oriental conscience to a great degree."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">ASKED MANY QUESTIONS</head>
			<p> "Then they became most interested in the subject. They questioned me on all angles of the
				problem. The most delicate points they wanted discussed to the most academic degree. With me
				they were very frank, but never objectionable, and afterward when I convinced them that our
				methods neither meant the taking of life nor demanded husbandly restraint they were with me to
				a man."</p>
			<p>"The result was that before I left Japan we had formed an <org reg="Japan Birth Control League"
					>association</org>, with branches in every big city, and clinics were in the process
				before I left. In addition, I addressed a meeting of the <org reg="Peers' Club">Peers
					club</org>. All who attended were from the aristocracy, and they displayed the greatest
				interest in the subject. Count <person reg="Kawamura, Tetsutaro">Kara Tara</person> presided,
				and at glowing terms. That was the most enjoyable lecture I delivered, because they all
				understood English."</p>
			<p>"The only opposition I encountered was from the high military castes, for they still look upon
				the common population as so much cannon fodder, and the more Japanese bred the more lives they
				have to play with in the securing of military advantages."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">EVERYBODY TALKS WAR</head>
			<p>"Everybody talks war in Japan, and everybody regards it as inevitable. The poor people hope to
				avoid it, but the rich and the manufacturing classes look forward to it."</p>
			<p>"My own impression is that war cannot be avoided; the Japanese population is too crowded, and
				they must have an outlet. Adequate outlet at the moment is not available, and hundreds are
				starving through overcrowding."</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub"> NO OPPORTUNITY OVERLOOKED</head>
			<p> "The military caste is not overlooking that opportunity to preach war in order that the
				Japanese Empire may be extended to accommodate their excess population. So plausible a story
				do they make of it that the hitherto pacifists are convinced that war is inevitable, and they
				are prepared for the worst."</p>
			<p>"The military caste is cynical as to the outcome. Even if they do not conquer fresh territory,
				at all events they will have disposed of a good deal of their surplus population."</p>
			<p>"Whether it can be avoided is doubtful. In the days gone by we sent out our Christian
				missionaries to preach the Gospel of good will, but it would have been a much more efficacious
				step toward peace had we a couple of generations ago sent birth control missioners, who would
				have convinced these Easterners that an overcrowded population means war and then to have
				taught them our remedy against over-population." </p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
