<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-21 LH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate> 2015-05-27 LH correct tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-29 CH clean up tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
			<person reg="Othman, Frederick C.">Frederick C. Othman</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-04-30">30 Apr 1929</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on New Birth Control
				Formula</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422050</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article"> Mrs. Sanger Tells About New Birth Control Drive</title>,
					<title type="journal">The San Bernardino County Sun</title>, May 15 1936, p. 3</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="SBCS">San Bernardino County Sun</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>

	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="birth control methods"/>
		<index level1="birth control methods" level2="chemical contraceptives"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Tells About New Birth Control Drive</head>
		<byline>by Frederick C. Othman</byline>
		<dateline>
			<place reg="Washington,DC"> WASHINGTON</place>, <date value="1936-05-14">May
			14</date>.--</dateline>
		<p/>

		<p><q who="SBCS"> Mrs. Margaret Sanger gave us a cookie today, a dish of
				raspberry ice and all the latest news concerning birth control.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SBCS"> The idea now is to tell here as much as possible about developments in
				birth control circles and yet not enough to get either Mrs. Sanger or ourself
				jailed. The law is tricky (Mrs. Sanger says it's foolish), the developments are of
				world-wide importance- and prison doors are yawning. Woe is us!</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="SBCS"> The newest thing in birth control (Mrs. Sanger said) is a chemical
				formula, with rice flour as its basic ingredient. After fighting for 20 years in a
				vain effort to liberalize American birth control laws, Mrs. Sanger recently took her
				formula to <place>Japan</place>, <place> China</place>, and
				<place>India</place>.</q></p>
		<div>
			<head> DEVELOPED IN FLORIDA</head>
			<p> "I was welcomed in those countries," <q who="SB"> she said, recalling the almost
					innumerable times she has been arrested in the <place>United States</place>.</q>
				"The governments in the <place reg="Asia">East</place> were interested and the physicians were
				enthusiastic."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SBCS"> The new contraceptive was developed by Mrs. Sanger's technicians in 
						<place>Florida</place>, where there are no state laws banning birth control
					information. It underwent extended tests there, she said and worked perfectly.
					She has not broadcast the formula in this country yet, but intends to soon,
					maybe even in <place> Connecticut</place>, where the use of contraceptives is
					illegal, and in <place> Mississippi</place>, where it is against the law for a
					physician to give a patient information about birth control under any
					circumstances.</q></p>
			<p> "The fine thing about this new formula," <q who="SB"> Mrs. Sanger continued,</q> "is
				that it will not cost more than 35 cents for a whole year's supply. The big trouble
				with present day birth control devices is their expense. They are to costly for poor
				people to afford. They have babies instead." </p>
			<p><q who="SBCS"> Mrs. Sanger said meantime that the laws, both Federal and state, were
					being evaded throughout the country.</q></p>
			<p> "contraceptive devices now are sold not only in drug store," <q who="SB"> she
					said,</q> "but in filling stations and news stands. It is a sorry
				situation."</p>
			<p><q who="SBCS"> The fact that the <org reg="American Medical Association"> American
						Medical association </org> at its convention in <place reg="Kansas City, MO"
						>Kansas City</place> turned thumbs down on widespread dissemination of birth
					control information makes it even sorrier, she added.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head>'SHORT SIGHTED'</head>
			<p> "I am appalled at this action of the medical association," she said. "The
				association is very short sighted and I think it does not represent the medical
				profession at large upon this question. Otherwise why is it that the birth rate
				within the profession is notably low?"</p>
			<p><q who="SBCS"> Finally, Mrs. Sanger advised strongly against placing too much
					dependence on so called </q> "rhythmic methods" <q who="SB"> of birth control.
					They frequently are disappointing, she said. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="SBCS"> She told us some other things too, but Mrs. Sanger wants to stay out
					of prison as much as we do. So that's all we can tell about developments in the
					birth control world until-and if-the laws are amended. </q></p>

		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
