<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-20 CH encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1923-03-05">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">5 Mar 1923</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Bridgeport Council of Jewish Women Address</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422047</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Women Jam Hall to Hear Address on Birth Control</title>,
					<title type="journal">Bridgeport Telegram</title>, Mar. 6, 1923, p. 1</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BT">Bridgeport Telegram</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger's speech was not found; newspaper coverage used instead. Page 2 of this article is
			missing.</p>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="establishment of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>WOMEN JAM HALL TO HEAR ADDRESS ON BIRTH CONTROL</head>
		<p><q who="BT">The <place>Connecticut</place> law that holds it to be a crime to be a crime
				for any person to use drugs, any article or any other means to prevent conception
				was attacked as</q> "perfectly absurd"<q who="BT"> by Mrs. Sanger, of <place
					reg="New York, NY">New York</place> internationally famous birth control
				advocate, in lecturing last night under the auspices of the <org>Council of Jewish
					Women</org> before several hundred women who crowded all available space in the
				assembly room of the <org reg="Business and Professional Women's Clubs">Business and
					Professional Women's club</org> in the Liberty Building. She advised that every
				woman, individually and each organization as a unit, work to have the law
				repealed.</q></p>
		<p><q who="BT">Poverty, feeble-mindedness, disease, child labor, human suffering in many
				forms and other social problems would be solved, Mrs. Sanger argued if women had
			</q>the "right kind of information" <q who="BT">that they could control the number of
				children in their families.</q>
		</p>
		<p>The laws should be amended, Mrs. Sanger asserted, to allow the establishment of birth
			control clinics, that physicians and nurses could advise the proper method of birth
			control, no one method being applicable to different individuals. There should be such a
			clinic in Bridgeport, she said.</p>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Speaks without Permit.</head>
			<p>
				<q who="BT">Introduced by <person reg="Capitman, Frances">Mrs. Samuel
						Capitman</person>, the president of the council, who presided over the
					meeting, as a "martyr," Mrs. Sanger spoke in Bridgeport for the first time,
					without a permit.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="BT">Superintendent of Police <person reg="Flanagan, Patrick J.">Patrick J.
						Flanagan </person>said last night he did not know anything about her
					appearance here, no member of the Council of Jewish Women or other organization
					consulting with him prior to her speaking last night</q>.</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BT">Mrs. Sanger was arrested during the scenes of turbulence before and in
					the <org>Town Hall</org>, New York, and not permitted to
					deliver the same lecture. The <person reg="Hackett, William Stormont">Mayor of
						Albany</person> refused to allow her to address a body of women in that
					city, even after he had read her speech in manuscript. Her appearance in <place
						reg="New Haven, CT">New Haven</place>, scheduled recently, was blocked. She
					has visited <place>Japan</place>, <place>China</place>, and <place reg="Europe"
						>European countries</place>, lecturing on birth control.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="BT">In striving to make this a</q> "cleaner, healthier, saner" <q who="BT"
					>world, Mrs. Sanger said, a number of suggestions were put out by friends of
					birth control to awaken a </q>"consciousness for a better race." <q who="BT"
					>These included</q>: </p>
			<p>
				<q who="BT">A couple should not have children when either parent has a <supplied
						resp="MSPP">transmissible</supplied> disease, nor should woman permit
					pregnancy when suffering from a temporary disease that would tend to injure the
					child or wreck her own health, and the parents of feeble minded and
					disease-wrecked children should not permit the birth of any more children even
					though they themselves are healthy, as </q>
			</p>
			<gap extent="rest of article" reason="missing"/>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
