<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 MC encoded and transcribed</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-26 CH proof tags</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-05-27 CH entered corrections</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1952-09-10">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">10 Sept 1952</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Japanese Trip</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422063</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Margaret Sanger Slee Will Be Able To Enter Japan This
					Time</title>, <title type="journal">Tucson Daily Citizen</title>, Sept. 10,
				1952, p. 18</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TDC">Tucson Daily Citizen</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>No other version found.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues" level2="establishment of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Slee Will Be Able To Enter Japan This Time</head>
		<p><q who="TDC">Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee, whose theories of planned parenthood have made
				her known around the world, will be off for <place>Japan</place> early next month,
				assured, this time, of being able to enter the country</q>.</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TDC">Two years ago the <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place> woman, more
				familiar to millions as Margaret Sanger, had planned to lecture and speak in the
				oriental land, but her visa was refused by occupation authorities.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"Japan is no longer an occupied country,"<q who="TCD"> Mrs. Slee said today,</q> "and
			there is certainly no indigenous religious group in the land that is hostile to the
			things I work for.</p>
		<p>"When certain groups in <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington </place>learned of my
			plans for making that last trip, they advised the Catholic mission in<place
				reg="Tokyo, Japan"> Tokyo</place>, and this group then brought pressure to bear on
				<person reg="MacArthur, Douglas">Gen. <q who="TCD">(Douglas)</q> MacArthur</person>
			to have me barred. A situation," <q who="TCD">she added</q>, "which cannot exist
			now."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TCD">Before leaving the city, Mrs. Slee is scheduled to speak at a luncheon
				meeting of the <org reg="Unitarian Alliance">Alliance</org>, an organization of <org
					reg="Tucson Unitarian Church">Tucson's Unitarian church</org>, at 1 p.m.
				Thursday, Sept. 18, in <org>El Merendero</org> restaurant.</q>
		</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TCD">Mrs. Slee said she plans a stopover in <place reg="Honolulu, HI"
					>Honolulu</place>, where she will lecture before going on to Japan. She is to
				arrive in the far east the first part of November and will stay for two weeks as a
				guest of <org reg="Mainichi Press">Tokyo's Mainichi press</org>.</q>
		</p>
		<p>After that there will be more speeches and lectures in <place>Singapore</place>, on the
			island of <place>Formosa</place>, in <place reg="Manila, Philippines">Manila</place> and
				<place reg="Thailand">Siam</place>, ending in <place>Bombay, India</place>, in time for the world
			conference there on planned parenthood and population which will last from Nov. 24 to
			Dec. 1.</p>
		<p><q who="TCD">As director of the American division of this<org
					reg="Planned Parenthood Federation of America"> world organization</org>, Mrs.
				Slee indicated she planned to stay in <place>India</place> for some time after the
				end of the conference to set up demonstration clinics and </q>"be of as much use as
			possible in that part of the world."</p>
		<p>
			<q who="TCD">The specialist on babies by schedule quoted India's <person
					reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal">Nehru</person> as saying birth control will have a
				significant place in the country's next five-year social welfare plan. She said the
				Indian government already has appropriated money to further birth control
				programs.</q>
		</p>
		<p>"In 1935,"<q who="TCD"> Mrs. Slee explained,</q> "I was in that land as a guest of the
				<org reg="All-India Woman's Conference">All-India Woman's conference</org> and
			helped set up clinics throughout the country. Most of them have gone by the way during
			the years of trouble and unrest, but the interest in them seems now to have culminated
			in this coming conference."</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
