<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/07/08 MM</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-04-10 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1953-09-28">28 Sept 1953</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Statement on Her Swedish Trip</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422008</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Birth Control Leader Ends Swedish Trip</title>, <title
					type="journal">Arizona Daily Star</title>, Aug. 28, 1953</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke to the press on arriving back in <place reg="Tuscon, AZ">Tuscon</place>
			after attending the <org reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 4th"
				>Fourth International Conference on Planned Parenthood</org> in <place>Stockholm,
				Sweden</place></p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="international"/>
		<index level1="Sweden"/>
		<index level1="planned parenthood"/>
		<index level1="Italy" level2="overpopulation and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Birth Control Leader Ends Swedish Trip</head>
		<p>"<place>Sweden</place> and the other Scandinavian countries are much more highly educated
			in sex matters than America," <q who="ADS">according to Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee, who
				returned to Tuscon last night after becoming president of the International Planned
				Parenthood federation last week in Stockholm.</q></p>
		<p>
			<q who="ADS">She arrived by plane from <place reg="Tulsa, OK">Tulsa, Okla.</place>,
				where she became fatigued from motoring from <place reg="New York, NY">New
					York</place> with her Tuscon friend and companion, <person
					reg="McNamee, Dorothy">Dorothy McNamee</person>.</q>
		</p>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Outstanding Advocate</head>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">The world's outstanding advocate of planned parenthood declared that
						<org reg="Riksforbundet fur Sexuell Upplysning">Sweden planned
						parenthood organization</org> has more than 100,000 members, and is
					subscribed to financially by the <person reg="Gustaf VI Adolf (Sweden)"
						>king</person>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">She said the Swedish nation has backed the organization for many years
					and with money raised through dues is actively extending the program to
						<place>Lapland</place>.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">The planned parenthood conference held great interest in Sweden, she
					said, and was top news in papers there all week, sharing page one headlines with
					the <person reg="Kinsey, Alfred">Kinsey</person> report on reviews which
					appeared during the conference.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Conference Work</head>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">The work of the conference, which was the fourth international assembly
					of the federation, was to establish a constitution. She said that a legal review
					of the constitution will be made soon in <place reg="United States"
						>America</place> by the national organization's attorneys. It will then be
					available to the public.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">Mrs. Slee visited cities in <place>Finland</place>,
						<place>Norway</place> and <place>Denmark</place> as well as in
						<place>England</place>, and said she was surprised to find her name so well
					known.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="ADS">She said her task as president of the federation is to </q>"explore"<q
					who="ADS"> the site of the next conference, which will be held in two years; set
					an agenda, and raise the money for the conference. Invitations to become host to
					the next conference have already been extended by <place reg="Netherlands"
						>Holland</place> and <place>Japan</place>, she said.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">600 Clinics</head>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">From a start in 1916, more than 600 clinics have been launched in
					America, of which more than 500 are still in existence. Tuscon's clinic is
					located at 28 East Corral street.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">Work of the organization and its new constitution will next be
					discussed in Tuscon by <person reg="Rama Rau, Dhanvanthi">Lady Rama
					Rau</person>, of <place>India</place>, with whom Margaret Sanger was
					co-president of the <org reg="International Planned Parenthood Federation"
						>federation</org> during the past two years. Lady Rau will speak before the
					Sunday Evening Forum Oct. 25. </q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">Mrs. Sanger commented that <place>Italy</place> as well as some other
					European countries have long been known to demographers as a "danger spot," with
					serious problems in respect to the living space for its population.</q>
			</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">Ambassador to Italy <person reg="Luce, Clare">Clare Luce</person>
					recently wrote an article for <title type="journal">Newsweek</title> and other
					national magazines that Italy needs a solution to her population problems.</q>
			</p>
			<p><q who="ADS">Commenting on the article, Mrs. Sanger said,</q> "Mrs. Luce is too
				intelligent a woman not to already know the solution to that problem."</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Now Practiced</head>
			<p><q who="ADS">She said planned parenthood is now being practiced surreptitiously in
					Italy. A doctor was recently arrested in Italy for giving planned parenthood
					information, she said, but he was acquitted.</q> "That is a good start," <q
					who="ADS">she said</q> "The Italian people are intelligent,"<q who="ADS"> she
					commented, </q>"It is just a matter of getting in there and replying to their
				questions."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="ADS">Mrs. Slee said she plans to remain in Tuscon for an extended time
					before she accepts speaking engagements in connection with her office. she has
					lived in Tuscon for many years at 65 Sierra Vista drive. </q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
