<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-06-09 CH transcribed and encoded</prepDate><prepDate>20-15-06-25 CH proof and enter tags</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1920-12-08">
			<supplied resp="MSPP">8 Dec 1920</supplied>
		</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Commodore Hotel Speech Comments</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422100</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Birth Control is Advocated</title>, <title type="journal"
					>Mount Carmel Item</title>, Dec. 9, 1920, p. 3.</bibl>
			<bibl><title type="journal">Advocates of Birth Control Open Fight for Change in
					Law</title>, <title type="journal">Brooklyn Daily Eagle"</title>, Dec. 9, 1920,
				p. 18.</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="MCI">Mount Carmel Item</name>
			<name id="BDE">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This text was taken from two newspaper articles. For a draft of Sanger's speech see <xref from="128168.xml">Excerpt from the Hotel
				Commodore Speech</xref>, Dec. 8, 1920. For other draft versions, see Margaret Sanger
			Microfilm, Smith College Collections, S70:862-866.</p>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="state"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="lack of knowledge of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<div type="section">
			<head>BIRTH CONTROL IS ADVOCATED</head>
			<dateline><place>NEW YORK</place>, <date value="1920-12-09">Dec. 9</date>.</dateline>
			<p>"Diplomats may form leagues of nations but so long as women continue to produce
				explosive populations all the leagues in the world will be merely proverbial scraps
				of paper." <q who="MCI">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth control advocate, declared in a
					commenting on the new campaign to legalize dissemination of birth control
					information in this <place reg="New York, NY">state</place>.</q></p>
			<p>
				<q who="MCI">The campaign was launched at a meeting of 500 women under auspices of
					the <org>New York Women's Publishing Company</org>, publishers of the <title
						type="journal">Birth Control Review</title>. Mrs. Sanger, who just returned
					from studying social condition in <place>Europe</place>, bore the following
					message to American women from European scientists, diplomats and
					economists:</q>
			</p>
			<p>"We agree with the advocates of birth control that no world peace is possible without
				a reduction of the birth rate and immediate action toward its international
				accomplishment."</p>
			<p><q who="MCI">A bill legalizing dissemination of birth control information will be introduced at
				the next session of the <org reg="New York State Legislature">legislature</org>.</q></p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head>ADVOCATES OF BIRTH CONTROL OPEN FIGHT FOR CHANGE IN LAW</head>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">Mrs. <person reg="Rublee, Juliet Barrett">Juliet Barrett
						Rublee</person> presided and introduced Mrs. Sanger. The latter, who is an
					attractive young woman with a clear cut, colorless face and dark eyes, wore a
					black cloth gown edged with fur at the throat and a close-fitting turban of ecru
					and black feathers.</q>
			</p>
			<p>"I understood," <q who="BDE">she said.</q> "that a scientific contraceptive has been
				invented in Germany which would solve the problem for all time. I did not find it,
				but I got in touch with scientists in <place>Germany</place>, <place
					reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>, and <place>England</place>, and owing to
				communications established between these countries I believe such and ideal things
				will be here, possibly within the year, for our benefit."</p>
			<p>"The time has come to apply fundamentals to the world's wounds. Birth control is the
				step which we must take to ensure world peace. Women who continue to produce
				explosive populations will make all pledges of peace between nations become so many
				scraps of paper."</p>
			<p>"Birth control is not new idea. It is as old as Nature itself. Nature has used famine
				and pestilence and disease to wipe out the unfit. But today we protect the unfit in
				our hospitals and seek to use science rather than Nature's cruel method. Today,
				because we have checked Nature's method and are not using the scientific method of
				birth control the world is in a condition of congestion, misery and poverty."</p>
			<p>"Scientists, diplomats, statesmen and reformers--we are disappointed in them all.
				There is not a nation today which is not dissatisfied with its government. We must
				attack this problem of congestion fundamentally."</p>
			<p>
				<q who="BDE">About three-fourths of the audience left at the conclusion of Mrs.
					Sanger's speech.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
