<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-0818 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-08-26 CH enter proofreading corrections</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-10-07 EK update index</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1921-11-12">12 Nov 1921</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">First American Birth Control Conference Second Session
					Summary</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422109</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="book">Birth Control: What It Is, How it Works, What it Will Do:
					Proceedings of the American Birth Control Conference Held at the Hotel Plaza,
					New York, November 11, 12, 1921</title> (New York: 1921), pp. 90-92</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name/>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger was asked to summarize papers given during the second session of the <org
				reg="American Birth Control Conference, 1st">First American Birth Control
				Conference</org>, including papers by <person reg="Rosanoff, Aaron J.">Aaron J.
				Rosanoff</person>, <person reg="Johnson, Roswell H.">Roswell H. Johnson</person>,
				<person reg="Little, Clarence Cook">Clarence Cook Little</person>, <person
				reg="Young, Virginia C.">Virginia C. Young</person>, <person reg="Lindeman, Eduard"
				>Eduard C. Lindeman</person>, <person reg="Dilla, Harriette M.">Harriette M.
				Dilla</person>, and <person reg="Bland, John O. P.">John O. P. Bland</person>, on
			topics ranging from psychiatry and birth control, eugenics, delinquency, birth control
			and rural social progress, and the population in Asia. A general discussion of the
			papers preceded Sanger's comments. For other speeches and comments made at this
			conference, see "<xref from="229953.xml">Opening Address</xref>," "<xref
				from="229952.xml">The Use of the Pessary</xref>," "<xref from="422111.xml"
				>Comments</xref>," "<xref from="422110.xml">Introduction for Harold Cox</xref>,"
				"<xref from="238254.xml">The Morality of Birth Control</xref>," and "<xref
				from="231277.xml">Closing Remarks</xref>"</p>
		<index level1="conference" level2="American Birth Control Conference" level3="1921 (1st)"/>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="philosophy"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="history of"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="propaganda and publicity"/>
		<index level1="birth control movement" level2="goals and strategies"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="MS on"/>
		<index level1="physicians" level2="and birth control"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<p> Madam <person reg="Hooker, Edith Houghton">Chairman</person>, and friends. It seems to
			me in listening to the papers, that I thoroughly agree with the last speaker, <person
				reg="Flanagan, Dr.">Dr. Flanagan</person> from <place>Virginia</place>, that the
			papers have been excellent, in a very splendid key. It seems to me that they have been
			of sufficient variety to bring in and to show all of us today how wide the subject of
			Birth Control is, and how important it is to include it into practically every program
			that we have for racial betterment and for national health.</p>
		<p>There is one thing that I feel has perhaps not been understood. One of the speakers in
			one of the very able papers spoke of the emotional, and told us to take principles out
			from the emotional, and I just want to call attention, whenever anybody says "emotional"
			in Birth Control, I know they mean me. I want to say this. That when you realize that
			six or ten years back the same conditions were there as are here today, the same kinds
			of people, the same abortions, the same working conditions, the same overcrowding
			conditions, and yet it would have been impossible to have gathered together a group such
			as is here today to discuss the subject. Everywhere you looked people said "Yes, that
			is important. But don't talk about it." And it was necessary for some one to come out
			and waken an inert people. You could not do it at that time by reasoned or logical
			discussion. I always said that when the house is on fire you don't criticize the voice
			that calls your attention to it. It may not be ladylike, and just the tone and quality
			of voice we would like to hear, nevertheless we are glad that that voice has aroused our
			attention to the fact that the house is on fire. Now, in planning to awaken an inert
			people to the importance of Birth Control, I felt that it was first necessary to agitate
			and to awaken their interest in the question. There had to be various means and methods.
			The first thing was the challenging of these laws that have been for more than one
			hundred years upon our statute books. We hold the law as a rather sacred thing, and the
			only way you can awaken people to the question that was here before us, was to challenge
			that thing which all of us held sacred. That arouses attention, and when this is done,
			then we come to plan the means of giving the message and of educating. So the process goes,
			agitate, educate, organize and legislate. We are now up to our third stage, of
			organization.</p>
		<p>Now, all of us know, as I do, having been a nurse for many years among all kinds of
			people, that while some people had knowledge to prevent conception, thousands of others
			did not have it, that the reason was not only the ignorance of the people themselves,
			but also the lack of attention or the lack of knowledge of the medical profession. I
			found that most physicians who were honest with me said "Well, there is very little that
			I know about it." So we had to arouse their interest as well, and I think that the
			victory of this agitation, of this education, is in the meeting that we are holding
			tonight, I suppose this is the first meeting of the kind that has been held in the
				<place>United States</place>, where we are to discuss the ways and means to prevent
			conception. We have been overwhelmed with requests for these tickets. I assure you it is
			most pleasing. We have also had a great many requests from nurses and social workers to
			attend that session, and we regret to say that we are unable to accommodate them tonight
			because so many physicians have applied for admission. Now out of this conference
			tonight I believe we will begin to get somewhere, and if, as <person
				reg="Konikow, Antoinette">Dr. Konikow</person> stated, there has been nothing new at
			this meeting, she must speak for herself, because I think there are many of us who have
			found new suggestions, new ideas. And even if they have not been new, we have been
			convinced once more of the strength of our own ideas. So I feel that all of us must feel
			today a strengthening of our conviction that Birth Control is absolutely an essential
			part of the program from every angle and from every platform that we have put into
			operation to make this a better country and a better race. </p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
