<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-07-27 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1959-12-27"><supplied resp="MSPP">27 Dec 1959</supplied></docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on President
				Eisenhower</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422103</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Challenges Ike on Birth Curb Issue</title>,
					<title type="journal">Tucson Daily Citizen</title>, Dec. 28, 1959</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="TDC">Tucson Daily Citizen</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>For a typed press statement on the topic with different content, see <xref
				from="237527.xml">Margaret Sanger on Television Channel 13 Tucson</xref>, Dec. 27,
			1959.</p>
		<index level1="United States" level2="population policies"/>
		<index level1="United States" level2="foreign aid"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth rate in"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="political influence of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Mrs. Sanger Challenges Ike on Birth Curb Issue</head>
		<byline>By <person reg="Ernenwein, Leslie">LESLIE ERNENWEIN</person></byline>
		<p><q>Mrs. Margaret Sanger, birth control advocate, challenged <person
					reg="Eisenhower, Dwight D.">President Eisenhower</person> last night to debate
				the question of governmental participation in planned parenthood for nations
				requesting help.</q></p>
		<p>"He needs to be straightened out on this," <q>Mrs. Sanger said,</q> "It is disgraceful
			that <place reg="United States">our country</place> does not respond when a poor,
			overpopulated country asks for aid."</p>
		<p>"Such countries do not know what to do," <q>she said.</q> "They want our health and
			welfare departments to show them what to do. If we are serious in wanting peace we
			should be glad to help them.</p>
		<p><q>Eisenhower, she said, knows only war.</q></p>
		<p>"He doesn't realize that the question of war or peace is primarily a question of
			population." <q>Mrs. Sanger said.</q> "He goes gallivanting off to various countries to
			talk peace. But he knows nothing about population problems in those countries--
			especially <place>India</place>."</p>
		<p><q><place>Japan</place>, she said, has reduced the birthrate 50 per cent since 1957 be
				practicing planned parenthood.</q></p>
		<p>"The movement started there in 1920 and met great resistance by the warmongering
			politicians. But the Japanese people kept at it even though some of them were jailed for
			sponsoring birth control."</p>
		<p><q>Does she believe the President will agree to a debate, or grant her an
			interview?</q></p>
		<p>"He certainly should, <q>Mrs. Sanger said.</q> "He's an intelligent man, but he just
			doesn't know about this problem. He has been misinformed. He has been influenced by the
			opposition--by the Irish-Catholic bishops."</p>
		<p><q>She said that the <person reg="Draper, William H., Jr.">Draper</person> report,
				requested by Eisenhower, had indicated that we should assist on request those
				nations needing population control. But Eisenhower apparently has rejected the
				report, after initially accepting it, she said.</q></p>
		<p>"If he will debate the question and learn something about this problem, I am confidant
			that he would change his views,"<q> Mrs. Sanger said.</q></p>
		<p><q>"We cannot have peace without halting the population explosion which is currently
				occurring in various countries such as India."</q></p>

	</docBody>
</doc>
