<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-07-21 CH transcribed and encoded</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-13 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1917-01-27">27 Jan 1917</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Ethel Byrne's Hunger Strike and Federal
					Bill</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422101</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Pro-Birth Control Agitator is Forcibly Fed After Going
					Without Food for 103 Hours</title>, <title type="journal">Leavenworth
					Post</title>, Jan. 28, 1917, p. 1</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="LP">Leavenworth Post</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="Byrne, Ethel Higgins"/>
		<index level1="birth control laws and legislation" level2="Federal"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>PRO-BIRTH CONTROL AGITATOR IS FORCIBLY FED AFTER GOING WITHOUT FOOD FOR 103
			HOURS</head>

		<dateline><place reg="New York, NY">New York</place>, <date value="1917-01-27">Jan.
				27</date>.--</dateline>
		<p><q who="LP">The first results of the hunger strike and forcible attempts to feed Mrs.
					<person reg="Byrne, Ethel Higgins">Ethel Byrne</person>, at <org
					reg="Blackwell's Island Penitentiary">Blackwell's Island</org> came
			tonight.</q></p>
		<p><q who="LP">A drive on <org reg="United States Congress">congress</org> Tuesday by Mrs.
					<person reg="Fassett, Lillian Griffs">Lillian Fassett</person>, and others to
				get national legislation was being organized.</q></p>
		<p><q who="LP">Meanwhile Mrs. Byrne, while striking in protest against her conviction and
				imprisonment for disseminating birth control information continued her battle, the
				first of its kind in the <place>United States</place>.</q></p>
		<p><q who="LP">It was not until Mrs. Byrne had gone one hundred and three hours without food
				or water and collapsed that <person reg="Lewis, Burdette G.">Commissioner
					Lewis</person> established a precedent in American prison annals by ordering her
				forcibly fed.</q></p>
		<p>"My sister," <q who="LP">said Mrs. Margaret Sanger, leader of the birth control
				movement</q> "is in a very critical condition since she was rolled in a blanket, and
			milk, meats and stimulants forced into her stomach through a rubber tube."</p>
		<p>"I am reliably informed from sources other than official statements by Commissioner
			Lewis, that she is in a little room not in the prison hospital ward but curtained off.
			There are two nurses and two attendants with her all the time and I understand the
			attitude of everyone around her is extremely sympathetic to her." </p>
		<p>"As for helping my sister, we are balked at every turn. The women of the <org
				reg="Committee of One Hundred">committee of one hundred</org>, Mrs. Fassett, <person
				reg="Pinchot, Gertrude Minturn">Mrs. Amos Finch</person> and others have therefore
			concentrated on getting favorable action by congress." </p>
		<p>"A canvas of congressmen will be made by Mrs. Fassett and others and one of our friends
			chosen to introduce the prospective bill." </p>
		<p>"The bill has not been completely drafted but it will seek the nullification of the
			federal statute against dissemination of birth control information and the establishment
			of the right to tell poor women who need it, all about it.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
