<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-07-27 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1938-04-06">6 Apr 1938</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Phoenix Woman's Clubhouse Speech</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422107</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Capacity Crowd Attends Talk By Margaret Sanger,
					Doctors</title>, <title type="journal">Unidentified Newspaper</title>, circa
				Apr. 6, 1938. </bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="UN">Unidentified Newspaper</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>This article was found in a scrapbook in the Arizona Historical Foundation and is likely
			from a Phoenix-based newspaper. Sanger's speech was given on April 6, 1938.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="socio-economic benefits"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="health benefits and risks"/>
		<index level1="mentally diseased or disabled" level2="unfit to reproduce"/>
		<index level1="Arizona" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Capacity Crowd Attends Talk By Margaret Sanger, Doctors</head>
		<p><q who="UN">Birth control as a method of lessening the relief burden and raising the
				health standard of the nation, or, indeed of the world, was the theme of address
				delivered Wednesday night in the <org>Phoenix Woman's Clubhouse</org> by Mrs.
				Margaret Sanger, whose efforts have been responsible for the success of the
				movement; Dr. <person reg="Mayer, Edgar">Edgar Mayer</person> of <place
					reg="Rye, NY">Rye, N.Y.</place>, associate professor of medicine at <org>Cornell
					University</org>; and Dr. <person reg="Baldwin, Louis">Louis Baldwin</person>,
					<place reg="Phoenix, AZ">Phoenix</place>, former head of the <org>Desert
					Sanatorium</org> at <place reg="Tucson, AZ">Tucson</place>. They were introduced
				by <person reg="Cuthbert, Hugh T.">Hugh T. Cuthbert</person>.</q></p>
		<p><q who="UN">The meeting, attended by a crowd which overflowed the clubhouse so that many
				were turned away, was arranged by the <org reg="Phoenix Mothers' Health Clinic"
					>Mothers' Health Clinic</org>, 711 East Adams street, whose board of directors
				is headed by <person reg="Cuthbert, Lucy S.">Mrs. Cuthbert</person>. Interest in the
				clinic, where birth control information is disseminated without cost if the
				circumstances of the family asking it make it desirable, was augmented by the
				meeting last night, it was apparent in a deluge of telephone calls yesterday, Mrs.
				Cuthbert revealed.</q></p>
		<p><q who="UN">The clinic organization of which was completed since Mrs. Sanger's visit here
				last spring, has been made possible through private subscriptions of prominent women
				and organizations. Ten prominent local physicians are on its advisory staff.</q></p>
		<p><q who="UN">Stressing the need of birth control information, Mrs. Sanger pointed out the
				fallacy which permits persons unfit for parenthood to bring children bearing the
				taint of mental defectiveness and other hereditary weaknesses into the work for lack
				of such information.</q> "Unfitness begets unfitness, and the mental defectives,
			such as morons, imbeciles, and idiots are begotten by parents or progenitors whose blood
			stream carries the taint,"<q who="UN"> she declared.</q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="UN">Pointing to the <place>United States</place>' exceptionally-high maternal
				death rate, she stated that science has gained control of all other causes of
				fatality more rapidly than this one.</q> "Too many mothers die in childbirth--and
			every child has the right to be born a wanted child," <q who="UN">she declared.</q>
		</p>
		<p>Dr. Mayer stressed the need for birth control information so that mothers having
			tuberculosis, heart disease and other ailments which would make child bearing for them
			dangerous, or which might cause the mother to pass along a weak constitution to the
			child, need not bear children.</p>
		<p><q who="UN">The goal of educating mothers in this important phase of living has been
				brought much closer by the <org>American Medical Association</org>'s acceptance of
				the idea, Dr. Baldwin said, and outlined the general public health aspect of the
				campaign.</q>
		</p>
		<p><q who="UN">Four clinics have now been established in <place>Arizona</place>, the first
				at <org reg="Tucson Mothers' Health Clinic">Tucson</org> several years ago. The
				others are the one here, <org reg="Benson Mothers' Health Clinic">one</org> in
					<place reg="Benson, AZ">Benson</place> and <org
					reg="Casa Grande Hospital Maternal Aid Clinic">one</org> in <place
					reg="Casa Grande, AZ">Casa Grande</place>. Mrs. Sanger's recently announced
				plans are to inaugurate a campaign to have the clinics throughout the United States
				subsidized through the government, in line with the general social welfare
				program.</q></p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
