<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published statement">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2015-07-27 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate><prepDate>2015-08-13 CH regularizing doc titles</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1959-03-18">18 Mar 1959</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Trip to India and Japan</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422102</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Margaret Sanger Tells of Orient</title>, <title
					type="journal">Arizona Republic</title>, Mar. 18, 1959</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="AR">Arizona Republic</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<index level1="India" level2="birth control in"/>
		<index level1="Japan" level2="birth control in"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>Margaret Sanger Tells of Orient</head>
		<byline>by <person reg="Estes, Jane">Jane Estes</person></byline>

		<p>"The <place reg="Asia">Orient</place> is well on its way toward becoming the most eugenic
			part of the world," <q who="AR">says Mrs. Margaret Sanger Slee, who with Mrs. <person
					reg="Sternberg, Grace">Grace Sternberg</person> returned Monday from the <org
					reg="International Conference on Planned Parenthood, 6th">sixth international
					conference on Planned Parenthood Assn</org>. in <place>New Delhi,
				India</place>.</q></p>
		<p><q who="AR">Mrs. Slee feels that in India Prime Minister <person reg="Nehru, Jawaharlal"
					>Nehru</person> has made the difference in the work of that country. </q> "I
			consider him the greatest living statesman. He includes every phase of Indian life in
			his five-year plan. . . economic and agricultural advancement, as well as care for and
			education of its poorer people. Nehru opened the conference and gave a very fine
			address. Under his leadership it seemed that all <place>India</place> was there
			together."</p>
		<p><q who="AR">From India the ladies went to <place reg="Tokyo, Japan">Tokyo</place> where
				they learned that 80 Japanese firms, employing thousands of workers, have undertaken
				educational programs in birth control.</q> "I predict,"<q who="AR"> says Mrs.
				Slee,</q> "that in two generations Japan will be the leading eugenic nation of the
			world, more so than the <place>United States</place>. They do not want to produce
			diseased children, and with the help of the <org reg="Japan Government"
			>government</org>, are seeing that they don't.</p>
	</docBody>
</doc>
