<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2017-07-27 CH transcribe and encode</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>
			<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
		</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1916-05-15">15 May 1916</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>Birth Control</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp422108</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Conference Hears Birth Talk Today</title>, <title
					type="journal">Indianapolis Star</title>, May 15, 1916, p. 1</bibl>

		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="IS">Indianapolis Star</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger gave her speech as part of the <org>National Conference on Charities and
				Correction</org> in <place>Indianapolis, IN</place>. For drafts of the texts Sanger
			used during this speaking tour, see "<xref from="236132.xml">Birth Control (Chicago
				Address on Women)</xref>," "<xref from="101859.xml">Birth Control and
			Society</xref>," Apr.-June, 1916, “<xref from="128002.xml">Woman and Birth
				Control</xref>," Apr-July 1916, and "<xref from="128003.xml">Condemnation is
				Misunderstanding</xref>," Apr.-Jun. 1916.</p>
		<p>Portions of this article not dealing with Sanger's speech have not been included.</p>
		<index level1="Sanger, Margaret" level2="tours" level3="1916 (U.S.)"/>
		<index level1="Woman Rebel, The" level2="suppression of"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>CONFERENCE HEARS BIRTH TALK TODAY</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>"Birth Control" will be discussed by Mrs. Margaret Sanger of New York city at the
				assembly room, <org>Claypool Hotel</org>, at 2:30 o'clock today. Mrs. Sanger is the
				woman who was tried last January in New York by Judge Dayton in the <org
					reg="United States District Court for the Southern District of New York">Federal
					Court</org> for advocating birth control. She was released and has since
				addressed many prominent audiences on the subject.</p>
			<p>The address of Mrs. Sanger probably has created more interest in advance among
				delegates to the convention and those here who are attending the sessions than any
				previous talk, because of the daring of her subject, her recent trial, and the fight
				she has been making all over the country for birth control, and predictions are that
				the assembly room will be filled to overflowing.</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Sees Much Quackery.</head>
			<p>Mrs. Sanger says that during her fourteen-years' experience as a trained nurse she
				found that quackery was thriving and that thousands of illegal operations were being
				performed every year. These, she says, were principally on the women of the working
				class, and since the law deters reliable physicians from performing these operations
				the working class have always been thrown into the hands of incompetent quacks with
				fatal results.</p>
			<p>"I found that physicians and nurses were dealing with the symptoms rather than the
					causes,"<q> says Mrs. Sanger.</q> Consequently, I decided to help remove the
				chief causes by imparting knowledge to prevent this system of things. I did this in
				defiance of existing laws and their extreme penalty through the publication of the
					<title type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>. The first issue of this magazine was
				suppressed, as were seven of the first nine.</p>
			<p>"After my word had gone broadcast the Federal Grand Jury in New York city indicted me
				on three counts. These indictments were based on articles in the <title
					type="journal">Woman Rebel</title>, which were branded as 'obscene.' The
				authorities were anxious to forestall the distribution of this knowledge and knew
				that this could only by done by imprisoning me. </p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">Published 100,000 Copies.</head>
			<p>"I decided to avoid imprisonment, at least until I had given out the information I
				wanted, so I published 100,000 copies of a pamphlet on "<title type="book">Family
					Limitation</title>." After this I sailed to <place>England</place> and made a
				study of conditions in England, <place reg="Netherlands">Holland</place>,
					<place>France</place> and <place>Spain</place>. I then returned to this country
				and found the case that the government had brought against me. <person
					reg="Clayton, Henry DeLamar">Federal Judge Dayton</person> acquitted me.
				Hundreds of requests have been made to me to renew '<title type="journal"
					reg="Woman Rebel">The Woman Rebel</title>,' but I feel it has already
				accomplished its purpose to arouse interest. Now more constructive work is needed,
				in meeting the people directly and interesting them in establishing free clinics in
				these sections where women are overburdened with large families."</p>
			<p><supplied resp="MSPP">The remainder of the article, which describes other speakers,
					has not been included.</supplied></p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
